<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" 
      xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" 
      xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" 
      xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" 
      version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>ZOOL430 Animal Physiology and Laboratory</title>
<link>https://mbutler808.github.io/animalphys-2025/labs.html</link>
<atom:link href="https://mbutler808.github.io/animalphys-2025/labs.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
<description>Course website for Animal Physiology</description>
<generator>quarto-1.6.40</generator>
<lastBuildDate>Wed, 27 Aug 2025 10:00:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
<item>
  <title>Lab 1: Heart Rate and Data Analysis</title>
  <dc:creator>Marguerite Butler</dc:creator>
  <link>https://mbutler808.github.io/animalphys-2025/labs/Lab1-heart-rate-and-data-analysis/Lab1.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p><strong><em>We will begin labs on the first week of class.</em></strong></p>
<section id="lab-information" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="lab-information">Lab Information</h2>
<p>Throughout the semester, <strong>Lab information</strong> can be found on the <a href="../../labs.html">Labs</a> page. Find it on the dropdown under “Course Materials”. Listed there are:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Lab manuals</strong> which are the experimental protocols for each week, named “Lab1-…”<br>
</li>
<li><strong>Standard Protocols</strong> for setting up, recording, and saving from the instrumentation. These are on the “Protocols” page.</li>
<li><strong>LabChart Quick Reference Guide</strong> for more details on and troubleshooting the LabChart software also on the Protodocs page.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="before-lab" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="before-lab">Before Lab:</h2>
<ul>
<li>Watch Instrumentation Podcast.</li>
<li>Read <a href="Lab1-data-aquistion-finger-pulse.pdf">Lab Manual 1</a> and <a href="../Protocols/p1-intro-finger-pulse.pdf">Protocol 1</a></li>
<li>Read the <a href="Lab1-Hlimonenko_et_al_2003.pdf">Hlimoneko Paper</a>.</li>
<li>Do Lab 1 PreLab Quiz in Laulima under Tests and Quizzes before lab (based on Hlimoneko). You get 2 tries. <em>Posted 24 hours before lab.</em> Since this is the first week, everyone who takes it will get full credit.</li>
<li>Please bring a bound notebook to lab for your lab notebook. (e.g., a $1 composition book, used is OK)</li>
</ul>
<div class="quarto-video ratio ratio-16x9"><iframe data-external="1" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/pujrG6zhTJE" title="" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen=""></iframe></div>
</section>
<section id="in-lab" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="in-lab">In Lab:</h2>
<ul>
<li>Review Lab Policies</li>
<li>Perform <a href="Lab1-data-aquistion-finger-pulse.pdf">Lab 1 Data Aquistion and Finger Pulse</a>. <em>Practical in week 3 on this material</em></li>
<li>Discuss Hlimoneko 2003 Paper [<a href="../../labs-misc/Lab1-discussion.html">html</a>][<a href="ZOOL430L-Lab1-Discussion_FA21.pdf">pdf</a>]</li>
</ul>
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-note callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
After today, you should know how to:
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<ol type="1">
<li>Set up PowerLab</li>
<li>Start LabChart with proper settings.</li>
<li>Set up the proper transducer (pulse)</li>
<li>Be mindful of cord hygiene</li>
<li>Distinguish signal from noise</li>
<li>Get a clean baseline</li>
<li>Be able to modify the scales (amplitude or time) to better display the signal</li>
<li>Add and edit comments</li>
<li>Calculate HR</li>
<li>Get a good recording with all events commented, save, and share data</li>
</ol>
</div>
</div>
</section>
<section id="after-lab-assignment-week-1" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="after-lab-assignment-week-1">After Lab: Assignment Week 1:</h2>
<ul>
<li>Write the Methods and Text of the Results for <a href="Wilkinson_et_al_2000_figures.pdf">select figures</a> in Wilkinson et al 2000 (<a href="https://docs.google.com/document/d/1xws5vA9Ea7rLIdbi-DPdS8KWevntsKiiqenWp7LZTYc/edit">assignment instructions</a>). Donʻt forget to follow the <a href="../../labs-misc/handouts/Revised_Zool430L_lab_report_guidelines.pdf">lab report guidelines</a></li>
<li>Turn in one copy (hardcopy) at the start of your next lab session. <em>Always one week after the lab</em></li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="notes" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="notes">Notes:</h2>
<p>A rough guide to length for this mini-lab is 1-2 pages. Content is more important than length. You do not need to fill up the 2 pages (if you finish in 1.5 pages, that’s even better).</p>
<p>The first lab will focus on data analysis to set you up well for the remaining labs in this class. Please try hard to understand the mechanisitic and conceptual connections between data and ideas/conclusions.</p>
<p>As this is a group assignment, you will be turning in one assignment per group. Include the full names of each lab member and who is Project Coordinator at the top, as well as a <strong>Respective Contributions</strong> section at the end.</p>
<p>If you are confused about any of the instructions or have any questions about the assignments, please send let us know.</p>
</section>
<section id="general-lab-course-info" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="general-lab-course-info">General Lab Course Info:</h2>
<ul>
<li><a href="../../labs-misc/handouts/Revised_Zool430L_lab_report_guidelines.pdf">Lab Report Guidelines</a></li>
<li><a href="../../labs-misc/handouts/Lab-Expectations.pdf">Lab Expectations</a></li>
<li><a href="../../labs-misc/handouts/notebookinstructionsMB.pdf">Notebook Instructions</a></li>
<li><a href="../../labs-misc/handouts/Agreement-for-Group-Lab-Report-Timeline.pdf">Lab Team Timeline Agreement</a></li>
</ul>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>week 1</category>
  <category>labs</category>
  <category>PowerLab</category>
  <category>LabChart</category>
  <category>finger pulse transducer</category>
  <category>LabChart Quick Reference Guide</category>
  <guid>https://mbutler808.github.io/animalphys-2025/labs/Lab1-heart-rate-and-data-analysis/Lab1.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 27 Aug 2025 10:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Lab 12: Human Renal Function</title>
  <dc:creator>Marguerite Butler</dc:creator>
  <link>https://mbutler808.github.io/animalphys-2025/labs/Lab12-human-renal/Lab12.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<section id="acknowledgements" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="acknowledgements">Acknowledgements</h3>
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-important callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
IMPORTANT Pre-Lab Procedures
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<ol type="1">
<li><p>Starting at dinner <strong>the night before lab</strong>, please attempt to consume a <em>normal amount of liquid</em>, and try not to intake unusual amounts of caffeine or (ahem) alcohol. Record what you eat and drink starting at dinner the night before your lab.</p></li>
<li><p><em>Do not drink or eat anything but water</em> during the <strong>2-hour period before lab</strong>. (have lunch before 11:30 AM for a 1:30 PM lab, or 12:30pm for a 2:30 PM lab). You may drink as much water as you wish.</p></li>
<li><p>Urinate <strong>one hour</strong> before coming to lab (<em>note the time</em>). <em>Do not urinate again</em> until the first collection at the beginning of laboratory.</p></li>
<li><p>If you have circulatory problems, poor kidney function or have any medical condition related to diet, do not volunteer as a subject for this experiment.</p></li>
</ol>
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-note callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
Standard lab prep:
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<ul>
<li>Read the lab manual below.</li>
<li>Write the [<a href="../../labs-misc/lab-notebook.html#sec-prelab">Prelab</a>] in your lab notebook. <em><strong>Please DO NOT copy the lab manual word for word.</strong> Your task is to <strong>summarize</strong> the important points that are useful for developing hypotheses for this experiment.</em></li>
<li>This week, draft hypotheses for each experiment.</li>
<li>To obtain feedback from your TAs, <strong>for the prelab please have the hypotheses, figuring out how many ideas you have to cover, and writing a topic sentence for each paragraph:</strong>
<ul>
<li>Motivating question/umbrella idea</li>
<li>introduce mechanism 1</li>
<li>introduce mechanism 2</li>
<li>…</li>
<li>end with a paragraph of your hypotheses</li>
</ul></li>
<li>For the <strong>methods</strong>, outline:
<ul>
<li>subjects</li>
<li>equipment</li>
<li>experimental treatments (be sure to note what <strong>variables</strong> are changing) and controls or comparisons</li>
<li>analysis</li>
</ul></li>
<li>Do Quiz on Laulima (open 24 hrs before lab).</li>
<li>Please bring a laptop with you to lab, if possible, to analyze your experimental results.</li>
</ul>
</div>
</div>
</section>
<section id="summary" class="level1">
<h1>Summary</h1>
<p>In this lab, we will examine renal responses to the intake of various solutions in the most convenient experimental animals available. Changes in urine composition will be analyzed in humans after the consumption of solutions hypo-, iso-, and hyper-osmotic to extracellular fluid, as well as basic, acidic, and sugary solutions.</p>
</section>
<section id="background" class="level1">
<h1>Background</h1>
<p>The mammalian kidneys play a major role in homeostasis involving both <strong>osmoregulation</strong> (the balance of water and electrolytes) as well as waste <strong>excretion</strong>. The are the primary organs involved in regulating the ionic content, pH, and osmotic pressure of the blood.</p>
<p>Kidneys filter the blood by glomerular filtration and form urine through tubular reabsorption and tubular secretion. Small molecules including water and small molecules filter out of the glomeruli (like through a sieve). As the filtrate passes through the nephrons some biologically important substances, such as sodium, calcium, glucose, and amino acids, are reabsorbed, whereas other substances, such as potassium and hydrogen ions which will become waste products, are secreted into the collecting duct.</p>
<p>Glucose is the universal energy molecule. The kidneys resorb glucose with such high efficeincy that sugar is typically not found in the urine. However, there is a limit. If the blood sugar level exceeds a value known as the <em>renal threshold</em>, the kidneys cannot reabsorb all the glucose in the glomerular filtrate and some sugar will appear in the urine. Many substances are normally reabsorbed in the kidney tubules, but most are not reabsorbed as completely as sugar.</p>
<p>Mammals do not have a salt gland, therefore the only mechanism for excretion of excess salts is dilution through the kidneys. Humans have the ability to concentrate the urine somewhat, to about 4x that of the plasma concentration, or about 1400 mOsm.</p>
<p>A massive amount of water (up to 99% of the glomerular filtrate) is reabsorbed both in the nephrons and collecting ducts of the kidneys. Therefore, the volume of urine excreted may represent less than 1% of the volume of glomerular filtrate. The volume of water is adjusted depending on the hydration level of the mammal.</p>
<p>Water resorption is enhanced by a hormone called <em>antidiuretic hormone</em> (ADH), which is released from the <em>posterior pituitary</em>. Changes in fluid intake or fluid volume (loss of fluid from the body) can change the rate of ADH release and therefore the rate water excretion and urine production (Figure&nbsp;1).</p>
<div id="fig-adh" class="quarto-float quarto-figure quarto-figure-center anchored">
<figure class="quarto-float quarto-float-fig figure">
<div aria-describedby="fig-adh-caption-0ceaefa1-69ba-4598-a22c-09a6ac19f8ca">
<img src="https://mbutler808.github.io/animalphys-2025/images/lab12-endocrine-control-blood-osmolarity.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img">
</div>
<figcaption class="quarto-float-caption-bottom quarto-float-caption quarto-float-fig" id="fig-adh-caption-0ceaefa1-69ba-4598-a22c-09a6ac19f8ca">
Figure&nbsp;1: Feedback regulation of blood osmolarity by action of ADH (Jay Swan <a href="http://www.slideshare.net/jayswan/chapter-45-endocrine-system-and-hormones" class="uri">http://www.slideshare.net/jayswan/chapter-45-endocrine-system-and-hormones</a>
</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-note callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
Feedback Control of the Kidneys
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<p>Human beings, like other osmoregulators, maintain osmotic and ionic conditions through homeostatic mechanisms. When a large volume of water is lost from the bodyʻs interstitial fluid (via dehydration or other mechanisms), plasma osmolarity will increase, be detected, and corrected mainly through feedback regulation. The control of water retention by the human kidney is a well-known example of <strong>physiological feedback control</strong>.</p>
<p>Changes in plasma osmolarity are sensed by osmotically-sensitive neurons located in the hypothalamus (Figure&nbsp;1). Increased plasma osmolarity causes these neurons to increase their rate of signal transmission to the posterior lobe of the <em>pituitary gland</em>, from which ADH (antidiuretic hormone) is releasted into the circulatory system. ADH travels through the blood and eventually finds its way to the epithelial cells that make up the walls of the kidney’s collecting ducts, where it causes the walls of the collecting duct to become more <strong>permeable</strong> to water. Water then flows from the collecting duct back into the kidney, so that the body retains more water and urine concentration increases (highly concentrated urine is very yellow in appearance).</p>
<p>Water conserved by ADH re-enters the circulatory system through the capillary network that surrounds the entire tubular system of the kidney. Water resorbtion will decrease plasma osmolarity (i.e., it dilutes solute concentrations in the blood). Eventually, the lower plasma osmolarity is sensed by the neurons in the hypothalamus and the firing rate of these cells decrease, resulting in less pituitary stimluation, reducing the secretion of ADH. The collecting duct becomes less permeable to water, so that more water flows out of the collecting duct, producing a more dilute urine.</p>
<p>Another feedback mechanism involves the synthesis and release of <strong>Aldosterone</strong>, a steroid hormone produced by the adrenal cortex in response to increased extracellular potassium (low extracellular Na+). Release of Aldosterone results in sodium reabsorbtion in the distal convoluted tubule (DCT) and the collecting ducts of the mammalian kidney. As sodium is reabsorbed from the kidney tubule, extracellular osmolarity increases (sodium is the main extracellular ion in human interstitial fluid). Eventually, extracellular osmolarity reaches a value that inhibits further release of Aldosterone. In the absence of Aldosterone, sodium is permitted to pass through the DCT/collecting ducts and finally is excreted in the urine. Osmoregulation via the kidneys are the result of a elegant anatomical design coupled with a beautiful system of feedback regulation.</p>
</div>
</div>
<p>The kidneys are extremely hard-working organs. Humans are born with all of the glomeruli that they will ever have, and they do not regenerate if they are damaged. With greater demand on the kidneys, individual glomeruli will enlarge in an attempt to compensate for the load. With serious renal disease the only options are kidney dialysis (which is not an ideal solution) or a kidney transplant for otherwise healthy patients who are lucky enough to have a donor. Unfortunately, artifical kidneys are not yet available although it is an active area of research. Therefore it is important to maintain renal health.</p>
<p>Today’s lab exercise is designed to illustrate human kidney function. You will measure the output of your own urine and (with data pooled from other class members) determine the effect of experimental intake of a range of solutions on urine physical, chemical, and biological characteristics.</p>
<section id="equipment" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="equipment">Equipment</h2>
<ul>
<li>Drinking cups</li>
<li>Graduated urine specimen cups</li>
<li>Test tubes and racks</li>
<li>Wash bottles</li>
<li>Combur Test chemstrip Urinalysis Tool</li>
<li>pipettes</li>
<li>Cl- determination reagents.</li>
</ul>
</section>
</section>
<section id="procedure" class="level1">
<h1>Procedure</h1>
<section id="analysis-of-urine" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="analysis-of-urine">Analysis of Urine</h2>
<p>We will measure the urine volume (using a graduated flask), chloride ion content, and the chemical/biological composition of urine using a chemstrip urinalysis test product (used for initial clinical diagnostic screening). The chemstrip tests for a number of different properties of urine, including specific gravity, pH, infection, immune system activity, insulin imbalance, blood chemistry, and liver function.</p>
<section id="here-is-a-detailed-description-of-what-the-chemstrip-measures" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="here-is-a-detailed-description-of-what-the-chemstrip-measures">Here is a detailed description of what the chemstrip measures:</h3>
<ul>
<li><p><strong>Specific Gravity</strong>: The specific gravity test permits the determination of urine specific gravity between 1.000 and 1.030. For increased accuracy, 0.005 maybe added to readings from urine with pH equal to or greater than 6.5. Elevated specific gravity readings may be obtained in the presence of moderate quantities (1‑7.5 g/L) of protein. The specific gravity of urine is a measurement of the density of urine; the relative proportions of dissolved solids in relationship to the total volume of the specimen. It reflects how concentrated or diluted a sample may be. Water has a specific gravity of 1.000. Urine will always have a value greater than 1.000 depending upon the amount of dissolved substances (salts, minerals, etc.) that may be present. Very dilute urine has a low specific gravity value and very concentrated urine has a high value. Specific gravity measures the ability of the kidneys to concentrate or dilute urine depending on fluctuating conditions. Normal range 1.005 - 1.030, average range 1.010 - 1.025. Low specific gravity is associated with conditions like diabetes insipidus, excessive water intake, diuretic use or chronic renal failure.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Glucose</strong>: The glucose reagent panel is specific for glucose. The reactivity of the glucose test decreases as the Specific Gravity of the urine increases. Small amounts of glucose may normally be excreted by the kidneys, these amounts are usually below the sensitivity range of this test but on occasion may produce a color between the ‘Negative’ and the 100/5 color block and may be interpreted by the observer as positive. Glycosuria is the condition of glucose in urine. Normally the filtered glucose is reabsorbed by the renal tubules and returned to the blood by carrier molecules. If blood glucose levels exceed renal threshold levels, the un-transported glucose will spill over into the urine. Main cause: diabetes mellitus</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Ketones</strong>: This test reacts with acetoacetic acid in urine. It does not react with acetone or β−hydroxybutyric acid. Some high specific gravity/low pH urines may give reactions up to and including ‘Trace’. Normal urine specimens usually yield negative results with this reagent. False positive results (trace or less) may occur with highly pigmented urine specimens. Ketone bodies such as acetoacetic acid, β−hydroxybutyric acid, and acetone can appear in urine in small amounts. These intermediate by-products are associated with the breakdown of fat. Causes: diabetes mellitus, starvation, diarrhea.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Blood</strong>: Blood is often found in the urine of menstruating females. This test is equally sensitive to hemoglobin and myoglobin. The sensitivity of this test may be reduced in urines with high specific gravity. False positives reactions can be caused by certain oxidizing contaminants such as hypochlorite and microbial peroxidase associated with urinary ’tract infection. Hemoglobinuria is the presence of hemoglobin in the urine. Causes: hemolytic anemia, blood transfusion reactions, massive bums, renal disease Hematuria is the presence of intact erythrocytes and is almost always pathological. Causes: kidney stones, tumors, glomerulonephritis, physical trauma.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>pH</strong>: The pH test area measures pH values within the range of 5 - 8.5. Average is 6.0, slightly acidic. High protein diets increase acidity. Vegetarian diets increase alkalinity. Bacterial infections also increase alkalinity.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Protein</strong>: The reagent area is more sensitive to albumin than to globulins, hemoglobin, and mucoprotein. A ‘Negative’ result does not rule out the presence of other proteins. Normally no protein is detectable in urine by conventional methods, although a minute amount is excreted by the normal kidney. A color matching any block greater than ‘Trace’ indicates significant proteinuria. For urine of high specific gravity, the test area may most closely match the ‘Trace’ color block even though only normal concentrations of protein are present. False positive results may be obtained with highly alkaline urines (pH &gt;8.5). Albumin is normally too large to pass through glomerulus tissue, therefore elevated results Indicate abnormal increased permeability of the glomerulus membrane. Non-pathological causes are: pregnancy, physical exertion, increased protein consumption. Pathological causes are: glomerulonephritis bacterial toxins, chemical poisons.&nbsp;</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Nitrite</strong>: This test depends upon the conversion of nitrate (derived from the diet) to nitrite by the action of principally gram-negative bacteria in the urine. The test is specific for nitrite and will not react with any other substance normally excreted in urine. Pink spots or pink edges should not be interpreted as a positive result. Any degree of uniform pink color development should be interpreted as a positive nitrite test suggesting the presence of 100,000 or more organisms per ml, but color development is not proportional to the number of bacteria present. A negative result does not in itself prove that there is no significant bacteriuria. Negatives may occur when urinary tract infections are caused by organism which do not contain reductase to convert nitrate to nitrite; when urine has not been retained in the bladder long enough (4 hours or more) for reduction of nitrate to occur; or when dietary nitrate is absent, even if organisms containing reductase are present and the bladder incubation is ample. Sensitivity of the nitrite test is reduced for urines with a high specific gravity. High abnormal readings indicate the presence of bacteria. Causes: urinary tract infection.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Leucocytes</strong>: Normal urine specimens generally yield negative results; positive results of small (+) or greater are clinically significant. Individually observed ‘Trace’ results may be of questionable clinical significance; however, ‘Trace’ results observed repeatedly may be clinically significant. ‘Positive’ results may occasionally be found with random specimens from females due to contamination of the specimen by vaginal discharge. Elevated glucose concentrations or high specific gravity may cause decreased test results. The presence of leukocytes in urine is referred to as pyuria (pus in the urine). Causes: urinary tract infection.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Urobilinogen</strong>: This test area will detect urobilinogen (a bile pigment derived from hemoglobin breakdown) in concentrations as low as 3 mIU/L in urine. The majority of this substance is excreted in the stool, but small amounts are reabsorbed into the blood from the intestines and then excreted into the urine. Causes: hemolytic anemia, liver diseases.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Bilirubin</strong>: Normally no bilirubin is detected in urine. Bilirubin comes from the breakdown of hemoglobin in red blood cells. The globin portion of hemoglobin is split off and the heme groups of hemoglobin is converted into the pigment bilirubin. Bilirubin is secreted in blood and carried to the liver where it is conjugated with glucuronic acid. Some is secreted in blood and some is excreted in the bile as bile pigments into the small intestines. The presence of trace amounts of bilirubin are abnormal, and require further investigation. Atypical result colors may indicate bile pigment abnormalities. Metabolites of drugs such as Pyridium and Serenium may cause false positives. Ascorbic acid concentrations of 1.42 mIU/L or greater may cause false positives. Causes: liver disorders, cirrhosis, hepatitis, obstruction of bile duct.</p></li>
</ul>
</section>
</section>
</section>
<section id="exercise-1-urinalysis" class="level1">
<h1>Exercise 1: Urinalysis</h1>
<p>The goal of the first exercise is to establish your baseline urine composition profile.</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>At the start of laboratory, clear your bladder by urinating into a graduated specimen bottle. Record the total volume of urine. Return to lab with at least 50 ml of urine. Dispose of the remainder. Record the time when this collection was made</li>
<li>Note the total volume of urine collected (in milliliters), the color (light yellow to amber) and transparency (transparent to cloudy).</li>
<li>Calculate the rate of urine production (ml/min) by dividing the urine volume (ml) by the number of minutes since your last urination.</li>
<li>Use a pipette (same as above, unless contaminated) to fill a CLEAN, DRY test tube with a sample of your urine.</li>
<li>Remove a Chemstick from the sealed darkened container. Minimize exposure of these strips to air and light (i.e., seal the container promptly after removing a strip). Do not touch the reagent area of the stick (the colored squares) with your fingers!</li>
<li>Fully submerge the reagent area of the strip in your urine and immediately remove. The Chemstick should not remain in urine for more than one second. While removing the strip from the test tube, run the edge of the strip against the rim of the container to remove any excess urine.</li>
<li>Hold the strip in a horizontal position to prevent any of the colors from the test squares from running together and lay the strip on a paper towel to prevent mixing of chemicals.<br>
</li>
<li>Use the indicator key on the Chemstick box to measure the value for each category. All reagent areas should be analyzed/read within two minutes! Record all these values in your laboratory notebook.</li>
<li>Rinse your test tube, and keep this test tube for future chemstick tests.</li>
<li>Measure NaCl concentration in your urine: The method we will use measures only Cl- ion concentration, but we will assume that Na+ ion concentration is equal.</li>
<li>Using a pipet, measure 10 drops of urine in a clean test tube.</li>
<li>Add one drop of 20% postassium chromate (K2CrO4) solution. The urine sample will turn bright yellow.</li>
<li>Add 2.9% silver nitrate (AgNO3) solution one drop at a time, and mix the fluid after each drop. Count each drop added. The solution will change brown where the drop of silver nitrate contacts the urine sample, but will return back to yellow after mixing until sufficient amounts of silver nitrate have been added to titrate the Cl- ions, after which time the solution will remain brown. Each drop of silver nitrate added during the titration represents 1.0 g/L NaCl.</li>
</ol>
</section>
<section id="exercise-2-effect-of-fluid-intake-on-kidney-function" class="level1">
<h1>Exercise # 2: Effect of fluid intake on kidney function</h1>
<p>The goal of this exercise is to examine how urine output and urine chemistry vary with intake of varying ionic strength fluids. &nbsp; Procedure</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>For this exercise, you will be assigned to one of 4 treatment groups (Table&nbsp;1). If you have any medical condition (i.e., kidney dysfunction, hypertension, diabetes) that prohibits you from participating in a particular treatment group, inform your TA.</li>
</ol>
<div id="tbl-treat" class="quarto-float quarto-figure quarto-figure-center anchored">
<figure class="quarto-float quarto-float-tbl figure">
<figcaption class="quarto-float-caption-top quarto-float-caption quarto-float-tbl" id="tbl-treat-caption-0ceaefa1-69ba-4598-a22c-09a6ac19f8ca">
Table&nbsp;1: Fluid consumption treatments
</figcaption>
<div aria-describedby="tbl-treat-caption-0ceaefa1-69ba-4598-a22c-09a6ac19f8ca">
<table class="caption-top table">
<thead>
<tr class="header">
<th>Treatment</th>
<th>Dosage</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr class="odd">
<td>Pure Water (hyposmotic)</td>
<td>7.5 ml / kg body weight</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>Pure Water - double volume</td>
<td>15 ml / kg body weight</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>Seawater (hyperosmotic)</td>
<td>7.5 ml / kg body weight</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>Gatorade (isosmotic)</td>
<td>7.5 ml / kg body weight</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>Coffee (caffeine)</td>
<td>1 cup</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</div>
</figure>
</div>
<ol start="2" type="1">
<li>Weigh yourself on the scale in the lab, and subtract 5 pounds (for clothing). Determine the appropriate volume you should drink (1kg = 2.2 lbs). Drink the entire volume of your beverage as quickly as possible. Do not ingest any fluids or eat any food for the rest of the laboratory period.</li>
<li>Record the time you finish drinking your beverage. Collect urine samples at 30, 60, 90, and 120 minutes after ingestion of the treatment. If you need to urinate more frequently, keep a record of the total volume of urine collected during each 60-minute interval. After the 120-minute urine collection, you may eat or drink at will (but outside of the laboratory, please).</li>
<li>For each urine collection, determine the total volume of urine produced using a graduated specimen cup. Calculate and record your urine production rate.</li>
<li>For each urine collection, use a fresh Chemstick.to measure urine chemical composition. Also, for each urine collection, determine NaCl content. Record the values for all of the chemstick categories in your notebook.</li>
</ol>
</section>
<section id="data-tabulation" class="level1">
<h1>Data Tabulation</h1>
<p><em>The analyses of the effect of each beverage treatment on urine production and chemical composition will be done using the entire data set from all of the students in the class.</em></p>
<ul>
<li>We will compile a shared table for each individual’s urine data, grouped by treatment. Each student should enter their data for urine volume, production rate, pH, specific gravity, [NaCl], [glucose], and protein for each timepoint (0 @ start of class; and 30, 60, 90 and 120 min post beverage consumption).</li>
</ul>
<p><strong><em>Clean Up Your Work Area and wash your specimen cups before you leave!</em></strong></p>
</section>
<section id="things-to-consider-for-your-lab-report" class="level1">
<h1>Things to consider for your Lab Report</h1>
<section id="introduction" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="introduction">INTRODUCTION</h4>
<ul>
<li><p>Briefly describe the feedback regulation of the human kidney. How could each beverage/treatment potentially affect this feedback regulation loop?</p></li>
<li><p>We studied a number of physical, chemical, and biological parameters of human urine. Describe the parameters relevant to this experiment in the context of what they might reveal about kidney regulation.</p></li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="questions-for-thought" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="questions-for-thought">QUESTIONS FOR THOUGHT</h4>
<ul>
<li><p>How did the results of your Chemstick Tests compare to the normal, expected values? Were any of your test results abnormal? If so, explain (e.g.,: women who are menstruating may test positive for red blood cells in their urine).</p></li>
<li><p>How did each treatment affect the results? Think about urine production (volume and overall osmolarity) as well as the time course of the response. How does this correspond to what is known about kidney regulation?</p></li>
<li><p>Did specific gravity change over time? If so, in which direction? Explain the results in relation to each treatment.</p></li>
<li><p>Which treatment group had the highest average specific gravity? Is this what you would expect? Why or why not?</p></li>
<li><p>Which treatment group had the lowest average specific gravity? Is this what you would expect? How can the results be explained?</p></li>
<li><p>During the experiment, which group(s) probably had the highest concentration of ADH in their bodies? Which had the least? Explain your answers.</p></li>
</ul>
</section>
</section>
<section id="after-lab" class="level1">
<h1>After Lab:</h1>
<ul>
<li>This will be a group lab report.</li>
<li>Please divide the work of writing the report <strong>by type of regulation</strong>, so that each person benefits from the experience of writing the intro, methods, results, and discussion. This will also ensure that the ideas are better connected between sections.</li>
<li>Please think about effective figures for this interesting lab. Again you should think about interesting questions you can answer with regard to osmoregulation and excretion and design your figures to reveal the answers to them.</li>
<li>Be sure to brainstorm together now in class</li>
<li>Please submit a draft for feedback from your TAs<br>
</li>
<li>Please discuss with your lab group before the final draft is submitted.</li>
<li>In the discussion circle back to the hypothesis and really try to interpret your results in light of muscle physiology mechanisms.</li>
<li>Please remember to include respective contributions.</li>
</ul>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>week 15</category>
  <category>labs</category>
  <category>renal function</category>
  <category>kidneys</category>
  <category>urine</category>
  <category>osmoregulation</category>
  <category>excretion</category>
  <guid>https://mbutler808.github.io/animalphys-2025/labs/Lab12-human-renal/Lab12.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 03 Dec 2024 10:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Lab 11: Human Electroencephalography (EEG)</title>
  <dc:creator>Allison Fisher and Marguerite Butler</dc:creator>
  <link>https://mbutler808.github.io/animalphys-2025/labs/Lab11-human-eeg/Lab11.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<section id="acknowledgements" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="acknowledgements">Acknowledgements</h3>
<p>Originally written by Allison Fisher and Marguerite Butler 11/06/2023</p>
<p>Additional material for this lab was borrowed and adopted from</p>
<ul>
<li>Electroencephalography Protocol. Written by Staff of ADInstruments for LabChart 8.</li>
</ul>
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-note callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
Prepare for lab by:
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<ul>
<li>Read the lab manual below.</li>
<li>Write the [<a href="../../labs-misc/lab-notebook.html#sec-prelab">Prelab</a>] in your lab notebook. <em><strong>Please DO NOT copy the lab manual word for word.</strong> Your task is to <strong>summarize</strong> the important points that are useful for developing hypotheses for this experiment.</em></li>
<li>This week, draft hypotheses for each experiment.</li>
<li>To obtain feedback from your TAs, <strong>for the prelab please have the hypotheses, figuring out how many ideas you have to cover, and writing a topic sentence for each paragraph:</strong>
<ul>
<li>Umbrella idea</li>
<li>introduce mechanism 1</li>
<li>introduce mechanism 2</li>
<li>…</li>
<li>end with a paragraph of your hypotheses</li>
</ul></li>
<li>For the <strong>methods</strong>, outline:
<ul>
<li>subjects</li>
<li>equipment</li>
<li>experimental treatments (be sure to note what <strong>variables</strong> are changing) and controls or comparisons</li>
<li>analysis</li>
</ul></li>
<li>Do Quiz on Laulima (open 24 hrs before lab).</li>
<li>Please bring a laptop with you to lab, if possible, to analyze your experimental results.</li>
</ul>
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-note callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
Summary
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<ul>
<li>We will explore the electrical activity of the human brain while doing various activities, using a technique called electroencephalography (EEG). There has been a lot of debate on various modes of study, we will test these ideas by measuring brain activity in two regions of the brain.</li>
</ul>
</div>
</div>
</section>
<section id="background" class="level1">
<h1>Background</h1>
<p>The <strong>cerebral cortex</strong> of the brain is the most developed in mammals and is a major center of information processing and integration (Figure&nbsp;1). It plays a key role in many cognitive processes including attention, motor control and sensory-motor integration, memory, and language. The electrical activity of the brain can be measured non-invasively through <strong>electroencephalography</strong> <span class="citation" data-cites="Vibell:2023">(EEG, Vibell in prep, <a href="&quot;Chapter 3 - EEG.docx-1.pdf&quot;">link</a>)</span>, and furthermore can be used to monitor brain waves associated with behaviors.</p>
<p>In humans the different regions of the cerebral cortex have been mapped to different functions (Figure&nbsp;1). For example the <strong>frontal lobe</strong> <em>integrates</em> many different processes including inputs, outputs, and control of movements (motor behavior), speech, and other behaviors, as well as cognitive and emotional processes. Humans are able to synthesize and prioritize the numerous inputs to produce optimal responses to changes in our environment. The <strong>occipital lobe</strong> plays a major role in visual processing. It is involved in object and facial recognition, depth perception, color recognition, and relays visual information to other regions of the brain. It receives visual information from the retina, but also receives input from other regions of the brain.</p>
<div id="fig-brain" class="quarto-float quarto-figure quarto-figure-center anchored">
<figure class="quarto-float quarto-float-fig figure">
<div aria-describedby="fig-brain-caption-0ceaefa1-69ba-4598-a22c-09a6ac19f8ca">
<img src="https://mbutler808.github.io/animalphys-2025/images/lab11-cerebrum-lobes.png" class="img-fluid figure-img">
</div>
<figcaption class="quarto-float-caption-bottom quarto-float-caption quarto-float-fig" id="fig-brain-caption-0ceaefa1-69ba-4598-a22c-09a6ac19f8ca">
Figure&nbsp;1: The human cerebrum, annotated with functional regions (lobes). Bectorized by <a href="http://training.seer.cancer.gov/module_anatomy/unit5_3_nerve_org1_cns.html">Jkwchui</a>, CC BY-SA 3.0, <a href="https://commons.wikimedia.org/w/index.php?curid=29055751">original</a>
</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>EEG is measuring electrical activity from cerebral cortex using skin surface electrodes on the scalp. Although the human brain has about 100 billion neurons, the electrical signals emitted by neurons are weak and have to pass through the cerebrospinal fluid, skull, scalp, and hair before being detected by the electrodes. The EEG technique takes advantage of the fact that the outermost portion of the cerebral cortex have neurons with a particular arrangement of their synapses such that they are all aligned and pointed outward (called “open field”) so that their electrical dipoles align and their signals sum <span class="citation" data-cites="Vibell:2023">(Vibell in prep)</span>. Thus what we are actually measuring are the summed activities of a large number of so-called pyrimidal neurons (Figure&nbsp;2 (a)) near the electrodes.</p>
<p>Pyrimidal neurons are the most numerous excitatory neurons in the cerebral cortex <span class="citation" data-cites="Bekkers:2011">(Bekkers 2011)</span>. They transform the sum of synaptic inputs into patterns of action potentials which may travel to other regions of the brain, or to muscle targets far away in the body to signal motor behavior. When we perform EEG we are measuring the activities of many (100s of thousands of) pyrimidal neurons as they go about processing information and coordinating activity.</p>
<div id="fig-neurowave" class="quarto-layout-panel">
<figure class="quarto-float quarto-float-fig figure">
<div aria-describedby="fig-neurowave-caption-0ceaefa1-69ba-4598-a22c-09a6ac19f8ca">
<div class="quarto-layout-row">
<div class="quarto-layout-cell-subref quarto-layout-cell" data-ref-parent="fig-neurowave" style="flex-basis: 50.0%;justify-content: flex-start;">
<div id="fig-neurons" class="quarto-float quarto-figure quarto-figure-center anchored">
<figure class="quarto-float quarto-subfloat-fig figure">
<div aria-describedby="fig-neurons-caption-0ceaefa1-69ba-4598-a22c-09a6ac19f8ca">
<img src="https://mbutler808.github.io/animalphys-2025/images/lab11-pyrimidal-neurons.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" data-ref-parent="fig-neurowave">
</div>
<figcaption class="quarto-float-caption-bottom quarto-subfloat-caption quarto-subfloat-fig" id="fig-neurons-caption-0ceaefa1-69ba-4598-a22c-09a6ac19f8ca">
(a) Pyrimidal neurons are the most common neuron in the cerebral cortex. The name comes from the triangular shape of their soma. UC Regents Davis campus, <a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0">CC BY 3.0</a>, via Wikimedia Commons
</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</div>
<div class="quarto-layout-cell-subref quarto-layout-cell" data-ref-parent="fig-neurowave" style="flex-basis: 50.0%;justify-content: flex-start;">
<div id="fig-brainwaves" class="quarto-float quarto-figure quarto-figure-center anchored">
<figure class="quarto-float quarto-subfloat-fig figure">
<div aria-describedby="fig-brainwaves-caption-0ceaefa1-69ba-4598-a22c-09a6ac19f8ca">
<img src="https://mbutler808.github.io/animalphys-2025/images/lab11-brainwaves.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" data-ref-parent="fig-neurowave">
</div>
<figcaption class="quarto-float-caption-bottom quarto-subfloat-caption quarto-subfloat-fig" id="fig-brainwaves-caption-0ceaefa1-69ba-4598-a22c-09a6ac19f8ca">
(b) EEG wave bands differ in temporal frequency, which can be seen on a very clean raw data trace. Typically as the frequency goes up, the amplitude goes down. Figure from <span class="citation" data-cites="Vibell:2023">Vibell (in prep)</span>
</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<figcaption class="quarto-float-caption-bottom quarto-float-caption quarto-float-fig" id="fig-neurowave-caption-0ceaefa1-69ba-4598-a22c-09a6ac19f8ca">
Figure&nbsp;2: Pyrimidal neurons and the most common EEG wave bands.
</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Brain waves can be classified by frequency bands. This means that they have characteristic patterns of oscillation over time (Figure&nbsp;2 (b)). One of the earliest uses of EEG was characterizing brain activity during sleep, which led to the definition of alpha (7-13Hz), beta (13-30Hz), theta (3.5-7Hz) and delta (0.5-3.5Hz) waves Table&nbsp;1. These waves were originally defined during sleep, with the dominance of the different frequences changing with different stages of sleep. They were later discovered to occur with other behavioral states and brain activities.</p>
<div id="tbl-eegpatterns" class="quarto-float quarto-figure quarto-figure-center anchored" data-tbl-colwidths="[20,20,70]">
<figure class="quarto-float quarto-float-tbl figure">
<figcaption class="quarto-float-caption-top quarto-float-caption quarto-float-tbl" id="tbl-eegpatterns-caption-0ceaefa1-69ba-4598-a22c-09a6ac19f8ca">
Table&nbsp;1: EEG patterns, frequency ranges, and associated behavioral states. Delta, Theta, Alpha, and Beta definitions are from early sleep studies. Slow and fast gamma are associated with cognitive processing. <span class="citation" data-cites="Vibell:2023">(Vibell in prep)</span>
</figcaption>
<div aria-describedby="tbl-eegpatterns-caption-0ceaefa1-69ba-4598-a22c-09a6ac19f8ca">
<table class="caption-top table">
<colgroup>
<col style="width: 18%">
<col style="width: 18%">
<col style="width: 64%">
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr class="header">
<th>EEG pattern</th>
<th>Frequency (Hz)</th>
<th>Behavioral/Psychological State</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr class="odd">
<td>Delta</td>
<td>0.5-3.5</td>
<td>Deep, restful sleep; vague dream states.</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>Theta</td>
<td>3.5-7</td>
<td>Visual imagery, imagery when falling asleep or just before awakening; light sleep.</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>Alpha</td>
<td>7-13</td>
<td>Awake, non-focused, relaxed, drowsy, or non-vigilant; Low level of environmental stimulation (for example when eyes are closed).</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>Beta</td>
<td>13-30</td>
<td>Awake, alert, focused attention or problem-solving; dream/REM sleep; high level of environmental stimulation (for example when eyes are open).</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>Gamma</td>
<td>30-70, &gt;70</td>
<td>Associated with cognitive processing, correlated with large-scale brain networking.</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</div>
</figure>
</div>
<p><strong>Alpha waves</strong> (8-12 Hz) can be measured spontaneously and are prominent over the occipital (visual) region of the brain. <em>When our eyes are open and are in an alert state</em>, alpha waves tend to be <strong>suppressed</strong>. They are <strong>prominent</strong> when <em>the eyes are closed and we are relaxed</em> (Table&nbsp;1). You will do an “eyes open/eyes closed” experiment today. <strong>Beta waves</strong> <em>increase when we are alert</em> and are associated with <em>focus or problem-solving</em>. <strong>Gamma waves</strong> are associated with <em>cognitive processing</em>.</p>
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-tip callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
It is important to note that
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<p>Brain function is extremely complicated and not perfectly understood. In particular, <strong>there is no easy one-to-one interpretation of brain frequencies with particular cogntive functions.</strong> In other words, there are likely to be countless processes that generate similar wave frequencies.</p>
<p><em>However, EEG is very good at detecting brain activity at great temporal and spatial resolution</em>. The most sophisticated systems use 64-256 electrodes mapped across the brain and can provide spatial and temporal resolution in 3D.</p>
<p>We will be using only two sets of electrodes targeting the frontal cortex and the occipital cortex, <em>enough to detect some spatial differences</em> (i.e., frontal vs.&nbsp;occipital lobes), <em>but we will have much better temporal resolution</em> (allowing you to correlate brain activity with events, and hopefully you can obtain clean signals if you can keep the level of noise down).</p>
</div>
</div>
<p><em>Recently, there has been a lot of interest in using EEG to measure brain activity in an educational context.</em> Many studies have established the benefits to learning of taking notes by hand or drawing over typing by computer <span class="citation" data-cites="Meer:2017 Ose-Askvik:2020">(see studies cited in Meer and Weel 2017; Ose Askvik, Weel, and Meer 2020)</span>. However, whether these can be connected to brain activity is less clear.</p>
<ul>
<li><span class="citation" data-cites="Meer:2017">Meer and Weel (2017)</span> found that a decrease of lower frequency waves in the theta/alpha bands when drawing over typing, implying that the brain is more receptive to learning.</li>
<li>Describing words (paraphrasing) was associated with an increase in the upper alpha/beta/gamma range (higher frequency waves), especially during ideation (the formatiom of ideas).</li>
<li><span class="citation" data-cites="Ose-Askvik:2020">Ose Askvik, Weel, and Meer (2020)</span> explored brain activity while writing in cursive vs.&nbsp;drawing vs.&nbsp;typing.</li>
</ul>
<p>Your task today is to explore brain activity in the frontal and occipital cortex while the subject performs different tasks. Can you see changes in EEG pattern?</p>
<section id="what-you-will-do-in-the-laboratory" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="what-you-will-do-in-the-laboratory">What you will do in the laboratory</h3>
<ol type="1">
<li><em>Setup</em>. Check that the equipment are set up correctly and ready to record.</li>
<li><em>Detecting artifacts</em>. You will learn how to indentify artifacts produced by unwanted electrical acticity.</li>
<li><em>Brain activity by notetaking strategy</em>. You will explore the types of brain waves generated while copy text verbatim vs.&nbsp;taking notes in your own words vs.&nbsp;doodling, all of which are modes of interacting with learning materials. You will also compare printing vs.&nbsp;cursive writing vs.&nbsp;typing on a keyboard as well as reading silently (with no notes).</li>
<li><em>Your own experiments</em>.</li>
</ol>
</section>
<section id="equipment" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="equipment">Equipment</h2>
<ul>
<li>PowerLab data acquisition system</li>
<li>LabChart 8 or later</li>
<li>5 Lead Shielded Bio Amp Cable</li>
<li>EEG Flat Electrodes</li>
<li>Electrode Cream or Paste</li>
<li>Alcohol Swabs</li>
<li>Ace Bandgage</li>
<li>Tape</li>
</ul>
</section>
</section>
<section id="procedure" class="level1">
<h1>Procedure</h1>
<section id="subject-preparation" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="subject-preparation">Subject preparation</h2>
<ol type="1">
<li><p>Make sure the PowerLab is turned off and the USB cable is connected to the computer.</p></li>
<li><p>Connect the 5 Lead Shielded Bio Amp Cable to the Bio Amp Connector on the front panel of the PowerLab (Figure&nbsp;3). The hardware needs to be connected <strong>before</strong> you open the settings file.</p></li>
<li><p>Remove any jewelry from the volunteer’s face, ears, and neck.</p></li>
<li><p>Unwind and straighten all of the flat electrodes. Attach the leads of the EEG Flat Electrodes the pins closest to the labled side of the Bio Amp Cable. You will need all 5 leads.</p></li>
<li><p>Refer to (Figure&nbsp;3) for proper electrode placement, but note that we will be using 5 electrodes: two on the frontal lobe and two on the occipital lobe, and a ground.</p></li>
</ol>
<ul>
<li><strong>Frontal lobe</strong>: Channel 1 “positive” and “negative” electrodes will be 3-4cm apart on either side of the forehead.</li>
<li><strong>Occipital lobe</strong>: Channel 2 “positive” and “negative” electrodes will be 3-4cm apart on the back of the head (where the skull bulges out). Place the</li>
<li><strong>Earth electrode</strong> on the bare skin on the bone just behind the ear on the left side.</li>
</ul>
<ol start="6" type="1">
<li><p>For the occipital lobe, it helps to part the hair across the back of the head from side to side to expose the electrode area for the occipital lobe and use hair pins to keep the hair out of the way. For long-haired subjects, rubber bands to make a top-knot ponytail may help.</p></li>
<li><p>You can use a ballpoint pen to lightly mark the skin if you wish. Let the subject abrade their own skin with a fingernail or an alcohol swab to remove dead skin cells. Abrasion helps reduce the skinʻs resistance.</p></li>
<li><p>Apply electrode Paste to the EEG Flat Electrodes. When the skin is dry stick the electrodes to the skin (Figure&nbsp;3) and keep the electrodes and wires in place with the medical tape. Avoid air gaps. Wrap the ACE bandage around the head to press the flat electrodes snugly on the head in good contact with the skin.</p></li>
<li><p>Have the volunteer seated in a comfortable position at the table with paper and pen and a laptop in front of them. During the experiment is important to minimize muscle movement and ensure that none of the electrodes are disturbed or compressed.</p></li>
<li><p>Check that all five electrodes are properly connected to the volunteer and the Bio Amp Cable before proceeding. Make sure the electrode wires do not cross over any power cables or electronic equipment. Turn on the PowerLab. (Figure&nbsp;3).</p></li>
</ol>
<div id="fig-setup" class="quarto-float quarto-figure quarto-figure-center anchored">
<figure class="quarto-float quarto-float-fig figure">
<div aria-describedby="fig-setup-caption-0ceaefa1-69ba-4598-a22c-09a6ac19f8ca">
<img src="https://mbutler808.github.io/animalphys-2025/images/lab11-eeg-setup.png" class="img-fluid figure-img">
</div>
<figcaption class="quarto-float-caption-bottom quarto-float-caption quarto-float-fig" id="fig-setup-caption-0ceaefa1-69ba-4598-a22c-09a6ac19f8ca">
Figure&nbsp;3: Electrodes and cable setup. We will use five electrodes to record from two channels and a ground. Follow instructions provided by your TA for electrode placement.
</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</section>
<section id="software-setup" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="software-setup">Software Setup</h2>
<ol type="1">
<li><p>Start Chart using the EEG lab settings file. Four channels should appear: the <strong>EEG frontal</strong> and <strong>EEG occipital</strong>, <strong>Alpha power frontal</strong>, and <strong>Alpha power occipital</strong>.</p></li>
<li><p>Make sure that the EEG channels are set to the “Bioamp”. Make sure the settings are as follows: Range 200 <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%5Cmu">V, High Pass 0.5 Hz, and Low Pass 50 Hz (Figure&nbsp;4). Check that the spectral input is reading the channels for the EEG. You may have to change the inputs to match the correct channel number. If you are using the new setup, you may have to change and restart Chart (several times) with the Bioamp cable connected for it to appear in the menu. If you are using the old setup, the little green light on the front of the Bioamp should be on. Ask your TA for help if needed.</p></li>
</ol>
<div id="fig-bioamp" class="quarto-float quarto-figure quarto-figure-center anchored">
<figure class="quarto-float quarto-float-fig figure">
<div aria-describedby="fig-bioamp-caption-0ceaefa1-69ba-4598-a22c-09a6ac19f8ca">
<img src="https://mbutler808.github.io/animalphys-2025/images/lab11-bioamp-dialog.png" class="img-fluid figure-img">
</div>
<figcaption class="quarto-float-caption-bottom quarto-float-caption quarto-float-fig" id="fig-bioamp-caption-0ceaefa1-69ba-4598-a22c-09a6ac19f8ca">
Figure&nbsp;4: Check your recording and filter settings in the Bioamp dialog box.
</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</section>
</section>
<section id="exercise-1-recognizing-artifacts" class="level1">
<h1>Exercise 1: Recognizing Artifacts</h1>
<ol type="1">
<li><p>Start recording. Ask the volunteer to blink repeatedly and add a comment “blinking”. Stop recording after 10 seconds.</p></li>
<li><p>Record the volunteer making eye movements. Add a comment “eye movements.” Have the volunteer gaze up-and-down and left-and-right in a repeated pattern. Make sure the volunteer is keeping their head still and only moving their eyes.</p></li>
<li><p>Record the volunteer making head movements.</p></li>
<li><p>Record the volunteer making jaw movements.</p></li>
<li><p>Record the volunteer swallowing.</p></li>
<li><p>Save your data, and open a new file with the same settings.</p></li>
</ol>
<section id="analysis-exercise-1-recognizing-artifacts" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="analysis-exercise-1-recognizing-artifacts">Analysis Exercise 1: Recognizing Artifacts</h3>
<ol type="1">
<li><p>Examine the vertical scale at the left of the Chart View, and note the positions corresponding to +50 <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%5Cmu">V and –50 <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%5Cmu">V. True EEG signals rarely exceed these limits.</p></li>
<li><p>Examine the entire data trace and Autoscale, if necessary. There may be some large signals outside the ±75 <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%5Cmu">V range. Such large signals are artifacts.</p></li>
</ol>
</section>
</section>
<section id="exercise-2-alpha-waves-in-the-eeg" class="level1">
<h1>Exercise 2: Alpha Waves in the EEG</h1>
<p>In this exercise, you will examine the effects of relaxation and eye movement on alpha waves in the EEG.</p>
<ol type="1">
<li><p>Make sure the volunteer is relaxed and comfortable. Have the volunteer close his/her eyes and remain quiet. Keep noise to a minimum and keep all distractions away from the volunteer.</p></li>
<li><p>Start recording. Record for 30 seconds. Prepare a comment with “open;” do not enter it yet.</p></li>
<li><p>Tell the volunteer to open both eyes. Immediately press Return/Enter to add the comment. <em>The subject should not be reading anything or moving their eyes around. Keep head, neck, and eyes very still with the gaze focused on a single point in front of them.</em> Record with the volunteer’s eyes open for 10 seconds. Do not stop recording.</p></li>
<li><p>Prepare a comment with “shut.” When the 10 seconds are complete, tell the volunteer to close both eyes. Immediately press Return/Enter to add the comment.</p></li>
<li><p>Repeat steps 3 and 4 twice, to give you three sets of results. Save your data.</p></li>
</ol>
<section id="analysis-exercise-2-alpha-waves-in-the-eeg" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="analysis-exercise-2-alpha-waves-in-the-eeg">Analysis Exercise 2: Alpha Waves in the EEG</h3>
<ol type="1">
<li>Examine the entire data trace. Use the View Buttons to change the horizontal compression to see data with eyes open and shut. Make a data selection that includes some data from both eyes open and eyes shut conditions. View this selection in Zoom View. This should make it easier to see the alpha wave activity (Figure&nbsp;5). Now Autoscale, if necessary.</li>
</ol>
<div id="fig-eeg-raw" class="quarto-float quarto-figure quarto-figure-center anchored">
<figure class="quarto-float quarto-float-fig figure">
<div aria-describedby="fig-eeg-raw-caption-0ceaefa1-69ba-4598-a22c-09a6ac19f8ca">
<img src="https://mbutler808.github.io/animalphys-2025/images/lab11-eeg-raw.png" class="img-fluid figure-img">
</div>
<figcaption class="quarto-float-caption-bottom quarto-float-caption quarto-float-fig" id="fig-eeg-raw-caption-0ceaefa1-69ba-4598-a22c-09a6ac19f8ca">
Figure&nbsp;5: EEG signal with eyes shut and open. Note alpha waves during eyes shut.
</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<ol start="2" type="1">
<li>In Chart View scroll through the “eyes shut” recording to look for alpha waves. Use the View Buttons to change the horizontal compression if necessary. The alpha waves can be recognized by their amplitude (usually 30 to 50 <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%5Cmu">V peak-to-trough, although it can be quite variable) and their frequency. Each cycle of an alpha wave should last approximately 0.1 s.</li>
</ol>
<p><strong>Note: If you cannot find brain activity that matches the alpha rhythm, re-attach the electrodes and repeat this exercise.</strong></p>
<ol start="3" type="1">
<li><p>Use the Marker and Waveform Cursor to measure the amplitude of the alpha waves. Place the Marker at the lowest point of the wave and move the Waveform Cursor to the peak of the wave. Measure the amplitudes of four waves from when the volunteer’s eyes were closed. Record the values in Table&nbsp;2.</p></li>
<li><p>Now measure wave amplitudes when the volunteer’s eyes were open. Record these values in Table&nbsp;3.</p></li>
<li><p>The amplitude of the waves is affected by the quality of the EEG signal. Therefore, it is useful to examine the frequency and power of the wave activity. Spectral analysis can be used to examine these features of a signal. Before examining your EEG signal you will complete a short tutorial on Spectral Analysis.</p></li>
</ol>
<div id="tbl-alpha" class="quarto-float quarto-figure quarto-figure-center anchored">
<figure class="quarto-float quarto-float-tbl figure">
<figcaption class="quarto-float-caption-top quarto-float-caption quarto-float-tbl" id="tbl-alpha-caption-0ceaefa1-69ba-4598-a22c-09a6ac19f8ca">
Table&nbsp;2: Alpha waves in eyes closed condition
</figcaption>
<div aria-describedby="tbl-alpha-caption-0ceaefa1-69ba-4598-a22c-09a6ac19f8ca">
<table class="caption-top table">
<thead>
<tr class="header">
<th></th>
<th>Amplitude</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr class="odd">
<td>Wave 1</td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>Wave 2</td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>Wave 3</td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>Wave 4</td>
<td></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</div>
</figure>
</div>
<div id="tbl-noalpha" class="quarto-float quarto-figure quarto-figure-center anchored">
<figure class="quarto-float quarto-float-tbl figure">
<figcaption class="quarto-float-caption-top quarto-float-caption quarto-float-tbl" id="tbl-noalpha-caption-0ceaefa1-69ba-4598-a22c-09a6ac19f8ca">
Table&nbsp;3: Representative wave amplitude in the eyes open condition (should have fewer alpha waves)
</figcaption>
<div aria-describedby="tbl-noalpha-caption-0ceaefa1-69ba-4598-a22c-09a6ac19f8ca">
<table class="caption-top table">
<thead>
<tr class="header">
<th></th>
<th>Amplitude</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr class="odd">
<td>Wave 1</td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>Wave 2</td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>Wave 3</td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>Wave 4</td>
<td></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</div>
</figure>
</div>
</section>
</section>
<section id="spectral-analysis-tutorial" class="level1">
<h1>Spectral Analysis Tutorial</h1>
<p>LabChart provides a module called <strong>Spectrum View</strong> that allows you to observe the <strong>frequency distribution of EEG data</strong> that might not otherwise be easily seen. For example, it could be used to break down an EEG waveform into its various components: beta waves, alpha waves, theta waves and delta waves. Spectrum view conducts a spectral analysis of the data by separting the complex EEG signal into its component waveforms which differ by frequency.</p>
<p>Specifically we will use the <strong><em>fast Fourier transform</em></strong>, which is one method of conducting a spectral analysis on the raw EEG data. It is more important, however, is for you to understand what this method is accomplishing. If we think of the EEG as the sum of many <em>sine waves of many different frequencies</em>, the spectral analysis splits the complex wave into individual wave forms and adds up the numbers of waves of each frequency.</p>
<p>What we see as a result is a plot of the <strong>power</strong> (y-axis) of different frequencies (x-axis) relative to each other in the input signal. Here <em>power</em> is equivalent to <em>amplitude</em> or a <em>count of the numbers</em> of waves at the given frequency along the x-axis. This is called a <strong>Power Spectrum Density (PSD)</strong> plot. The data can also be displayed as 3-dimensional color plot of spectral power, frequency, and time called a <strong>Spectrogram</strong>. (Donʻt get confused, <em>frequency</em> in this context refers to how many Hertz or cycles per second characterize each waveform, not the numbers of waves of each Hz we are counting - the <em>power</em>.)</p>
<ol type="1">
<li><p>Open the <strong>EEG Spectral Analysis Tutorial</strong>. It is in the Welcome Center, under the Experiments tab. It is also on the Animal Physiology Settings Folder.</p></li>
<li><p>Examine the Chart View. Use the View Buttons to view each block. You should see five blocks of data. The first record is a slowly oscillating sine wave</p></li>
<li><p>Open Spectrum view by clicking on the Spectrum View button in the Toolbar (Figure&nbsp;6).</p></li>
</ol>
<div id="fig-button" class="quarto-float quarto-figure quarto-figure-center anchored">
<figure class="quarto-float quarto-float-fig figure">
<div aria-describedby="fig-button-caption-0ceaefa1-69ba-4598-a22c-09a6ac19f8ca">
<img src="https://mbutler808.github.io/animalphys-2025/images/lab11-spectral-button.png" class="img-fluid figure-img">
</div>
<figcaption class="quarto-float-caption-bottom quarto-float-caption quarto-float-fig" id="fig-button-caption-0ceaefa1-69ba-4598-a22c-09a6ac19f8ca">
Figure&nbsp;6: Spectrum View Toolbar button.
</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<ol start="4" type="1">
<li><p>Click the Smart Tile button in the LabChart Toolbar to display both windows in full screen mode.</p></li>
<li><p>In Chart View Select the first record by double clicking in the Time axis. This will perform a spectral analysis for this record and displays the result in the Spectrum view. Adjust the horizontal scaling of plots to view the results:</p></li>
</ol>
<ul>
<li>Set the horizontal scaling for the Power Spectrum Density (PSD) plot to 50 Hz (Figure&nbsp;7). Use the horizontal scroll bar to display the 0 Hz to 50 Hz region of the plot.</li>
</ul>
<div id="fig-eeg-hz" class="quarto-float quarto-figure quarto-figure-center anchored">
<figure class="quarto-float quarto-float-fig figure">
<div aria-describedby="fig-eeg-hz-caption-0ceaefa1-69ba-4598-a22c-09a6ac19f8ca">
<img src="https://mbutler808.github.io/animalphys-2025/images/lab11-eeg-hz.png" class="img-fluid figure-img">
</div>
<figcaption class="quarto-float-caption-bottom quarto-float-caption quarto-float-fig" id="fig-eeg-hz-caption-0ceaefa1-69ba-4598-a22c-09a6ac19f8ca">
Figure&nbsp;7: Spectrum PSD Scale.
</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<ul>
<li>Set the horizontal scaling for the Spectrogram to 50:1.</li>
</ul>
<ol start="6" type="1">
<li>Examine the PSD plot and then the first section of the Spectrogram. Expand the vertical axes if necessary. Use the waveform cursor to identify the frequency in Hertz (Hz) of the peak in the PSD plot and the band in the Spectrogram. Values are displayed at the top of each plot.</li>
</ol>
<ul>
<li>What is the frequency in Hertz (Hz) of this sine wave? ______</li>
</ul>
<ol start="7" type="1">
<li>Select the second record and again view the result in the Spectrum view.</li>
</ol>
<ul>
<li>What is the frequency in Hertz (Hz) of this second sine wave? _____</li>
</ul>
<ol start="8" type="1">
<li>Select the third record and again view the result in the Spectrum view. You should now see two prominent peaks (PSD plot) and bands (Spectrogram) in the result.</li>
</ol>
<ul>
<li>Are these two peaks/bands the same as for the first two records? _____</li>
</ul>
<ol start="9" type="1">
<li>Select the fourth record and again view the result in the Spectrum view.</li>
</ol>
<ul>
<li>Is there any regular signal within this record? _____</li>
</ul>
<ol start="10" type="1">
<li><p>In Chart View compare the signal amplitudes of the fourth and fifth records. Note that the fifth record has lower amplitude compared with the fourth record.</p></li>
<li><p>Select the fourth record again. In the Spectrum view examine the PSD plot. Move the Waveform Cursor to the prominent peak.</p></li>
</ol>
<ul>
<li><p>What is the frequency (Hz) of this signal? _____</p></li>
<li><p>What is the power (mV2) of this signal? _____</p></li>
</ul>
<ol start="12" type="1">
<li>Select the fifth record and examine the PSD plot. Move the Waveform Cursor to the peak.</li>
</ol>
<ul>
<li><p>What is the frequency (Hz) of this signal? _____</p></li>
<li><p>What is the power (mV2) of this signal? _____</p></li>
</ul>
<ol start="13" type="1">
<li>Examine the Spectrogram. Note that the band corresponding to the signal’s frequency appears to missing. This is because the power of the signal is small compared with the previous four records. Expand the scale on the right hand side of the Spectrogram by setting the scale closer to the power of the signal (e.g., 0 to 0.004 V<img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%5E2">) (Figure&nbsp;8, Figure&nbsp;9). Note that the band is now visible at the expected frequency.</li>
</ol>
<div>

</div>
<div class="quarto-layout-panel" data-layout-ncol="2">
<div class="quarto-layout-row">
<div class="quarto-layout-cell" style="flex-basis: 50.0%;justify-content: flex-start;">
<div id="fig-6a" class="quarto-float quarto-figure quarto-figure-center anchored">
<figure class="quarto-float quarto-float-fig figure">
<div aria-describedby="fig-6a-caption-0ceaefa1-69ba-4598-a22c-09a6ac19f8ca">
<img src="https://mbutler808.github.io/animalphys-2025/images/lab11-6a.png" class="img-fluid figure-img">
</div>
<figcaption class="quarto-float-caption-bottom quarto-float-caption quarto-float-fig" id="fig-6a-caption-0ceaefa1-69ba-4598-a22c-09a6ac19f8ca">
Figure&nbsp;8: Spectrogram drop-down menu
</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</div>
<div class="quarto-layout-cell" style="flex-basis: 50.0%;justify-content: flex-start;">
<div id="fig-6b" class="quarto-float quarto-figure quarto-figure-center anchored">
<figure class="quarto-float quarto-float-fig figure">
<div aria-describedby="fig-6b-caption-0ceaefa1-69ba-4598-a22c-09a6ac19f8ca">
<img src="https://mbutler808.github.io/animalphys-2025/images/lab11-6b.png" class="img-fluid figure-img">
</div>
<figcaption class="quarto-float-caption-bottom quarto-float-caption quarto-float-fig" id="fig-6b-caption-0ceaefa1-69ba-4598-a22c-09a6ac19f8ca">
Figure&nbsp;9: Set scale dialog box
</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<ol start="14" type="1">
<li>The fifth record is the same signal as the fourth record, except that the quality of the raw signal has been affected. Compare your features (amplitude, power, frequency) of the fourth and fifth record.</li>
</ol>
<ul>
<li>How has the quality of the signal affected the wave features? _____</li>
</ul>
<section id="analysis-excercise-2-alpha-waves-in-the-eeg" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="analysis-excercise-2-alpha-waves-in-the-eeg">Analysis Excercise 2: Alpha waves in the EEG</h3>
<p>Now you will use Spectral Analysis to examine the EEG you recorded.</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>Use the View Buttons to change the horizontal compression to 10:1 (Figure&nbsp;10).</li>
</ol>
<div id="fig-eeg" class="quarto-float quarto-figure quarto-figure-center anchored">
<figure class="quarto-float quarto-float-fig figure">
<div aria-describedby="fig-eeg-caption-0ceaefa1-69ba-4598-a22c-09a6ac19f8ca">
<img src="https://mbutler808.github.io/animalphys-2025/images/lab11-eeg.png" class="img-fluid figure-img">
</div>
<figcaption class="quarto-float-caption-bottom quarto-float-caption quarto-float-fig" id="fig-eeg-caption-0ceaefa1-69ba-4598-a22c-09a6ac19f8ca">
Figure&nbsp;10: Alpha Waves with 10:1 Compression
</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<ol start="2" type="1">
<li>Find the part of the recording when the volunteer had his/her eyes shut. Click-and-drag across this part of the raw data trace to select it. From the Window menu, select Spectrum. In the Spectrum View choose Selected (Figure&nbsp;11).</li>
</ol>
<div id="fig-alpha" class="quarto-float quarto-figure quarto-figure-center anchored">
<figure class="quarto-float quarto-float-fig figure">
<div aria-describedby="fig-alpha-caption-0ceaefa1-69ba-4598-a22c-09a6ac19f8ca">
<img src="https://mbutler808.github.io/animalphys-2025/images/lab11-alpha.png" class="img-fluid figure-img">
</div>
<figcaption class="quarto-float-caption-bottom quarto-float-caption quarto-float-fig" id="fig-alpha-caption-0ceaefa1-69ba-4598-a22c-09a6ac19f8ca">
Figure&nbsp;11: Spectrum of an EEG
</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<ol start="3" type="1">
<li><p>Alpha activity shows up in the PSD plot as a clear peak in the 8-12 Hz range. Then print the PSD plot.</p></li>
<li><p>Alpha activity shows up in the Spectrogram as a band of color in the 8-12 Hz range. If you cannot see the alpha activity as a clear peak in the 8-12 Hz range, scale the horizontal and vertical axes. Note that Spectrogram displays all the recorded data and that the selection you have made is highlighted in a darker blue color.</p></li>
<li><p>Make a data selection of several seconds from when the volunteer had their eyes open. Select Spectrum. Note that in the PSD plot the peak in the alpha activity range of 8-12 Hz is small or absent and in the Spectrogram the band of color in the alpha activity range of 8-12 Hz is weak or absent. Print the PSD plot.</p></li>
<li><p>In the Spectrogram scale the horizontal axis so that all the data is visible. Note the presence and absence of the band of color in the alpha activity range of 8-12 Hz which correspond with the eyes shut and eyes open conditions. Save a screenshot of the Spectrogram. You may want to include a representative spectrogram i upur lab report.</p></li>
</ol>
</section>
</section>
<section id="exercise-3-note-taking-strategies" class="level1">
<h1>Exercise 3: Note Taking Strategies</h1>
<p>In this exercise, you will compare abundance of different wave frequencies during various methods of note taking. We record from the frontal and occipital lobes.</p>
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-note callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
Information processing strategies
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<ol type="1">
<li><strong>copying</strong>: reproducing information verbatim. Word-for-word.</li>
<li><strong>note taking</strong>: depicting the information content in your own words, whether in sentences, bullet points, or some more flexible format.</li>
<li><strong>drawing</strong>: doodling, drawimg, or making diagrams of the information, which can be labelled.</li>
<li><strong>reading only</strong>: The control. No note taking.</li>
</ol>
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-note callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
Modes of note taking
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<ul>
<li>handwriting (print)</li>
<li>cursive writing</li>
<li>typing</li>
</ul>
</div>
</div>
<ol type="1">
<li><p>On the desk in front of the subject, there will be a paper with prompts for your learning activities. The experimentor will use a top sheet to cover the prompts, moving it down to expose the next line as you move through each experiment.</p></li>
<li><p>With the subject seated comfortably, start the recording and drop a comment saying <em>“begin hand movement control”</em>. As before during the eyes open/closed trials, the subject will open their eyes, not reading anything and holding very still. This time, have the subject gently move their hand as if they are writing/typing. Record for 30 seconds and drop a comment when done.</p></li>
<li><p>Position the pen and blank paper in front of the subject. Start the recording and drop a comment that says <em>“begin handwritten copying”</em>. Expose the first line on the prompt sheet and have the subject copy it using regular handwriting. Try to only move the hand and wrist while writing. Drop another comment when they have finished writing.</p></li>
<li><p>While still recording, drop another comment saying <em>“begin handwritten notetaking”</em>. Have the subject read the second prompt and take notes (in their own words) using the pen and paper. Drop a comment when finished.</p></li>
<li><p>Repeat steps 3 &amp; 4 two more times. Instead of handwriting print, the subject will run through each trial (copy, note-taking) using cursive handwriting and then typing on a keyboard. Move through the prompts in order, ensuring each is new. Comment appropriately for each exercise (begin cursive copying, begin typing copying, etc.).</p></li>
<li><p>For the 7th prompt on the sheet, have the subject read the sentence and draw a diagram/picture to illustrate what the sentence describes.</p></li>
<li><p>For the 8th prompt on the sheet, have the subject only read the sentence (in their head) without doing any note-taking activity.</p></li>
<li><p>Design your own experiment to test another factor in note taking strategies. For example, having the sentence read aloud to the subject. Record this trial with appropriate commenting.</p></li>
</ol>
<section id="analysis-excercise-3-note-taking-strategies" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="analysis-excercise-3-note-taking-strategies">Analysis Excercise 3: Note Taking Strategies</h3>
<p>Steps 1-3 <strong>must</strong> be done in class. You can not do this on your home version of LabChart.</p>
<ol type="1">
<li><p>Select a clean section of data in the Chart Window from the first experiment (without any major artifacts). Open the Spectrum view and change the settings to display both <em>“EEG Frontal”</em> and <em>“EEG Occipital”</em> channels.</p></li>
<li><p>In the top menu, select File -&gt; Export -&gt; Spectrum PSD Text file. This will create a text file with the relative abundance of waves at different frequencies for both the frontal and occipital regions. Save this file with a name corresponding to which treatment the data came from, for example, “Handwritten_Copying.txt”.</p></li>
<li><p>Repeat this exporting process for each combination of note taking mode (handwriting, cursive, typing), strategy (copying, note-taking, your choice) as well as drawing and reading only. Also do this process for <em>“eyes open”</em> and <em>“eyes closed”</em> data for control. You should have at least 12 text files total.</p></li>
<li><p>Make a copy of <a href="https://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/1NszouoafNYPwEMO5w8iF_cYApgp0K3NM04JTTBrygWI/edit?usp=sharing">this Google sheet</a> and share with your group members. Select the columns in each text file, copy, and paste them into Sheet 1 under the appropriate heading. If inserted correctly, formulas in Sheet 2 will populate with summed values for waves in the <strong>delta</strong>, <strong>theta</strong>, <strong>alpha</strong>, <strong>beta</strong>, and <strong>gamma</strong> frequency ranges. <em>These values tell you the relative abundance, or power, of each type of wave during each experiment.</em> By comparing wave type powers, you can see what types of brain activity are more prevalent in each region.</p></li>
<li><p>Now you can compare the abundance of different wave types in different areas of the brain for each activity. With your group, <strong>come up with at least 6 questions</strong> regarding brain activity during different modes of note taking and show us with appropriate comparisons of your data.</p>
<ol type="i">
<li>One of your questions <strong>must</strong> include comparisons between <em>alpha and beta waves</em> in <em>both brain regions</em> during eyes closed and eyes open.
<ol type="A">
<li>For example, <em>“Do we see a decrease in alpha waves and an increase in beta waves with eyes open?”</em></li>
<li>Make a bar plot for eyes open treatments grouped by brain region versus alpha wave power. If parentheses indicates which bars are side-by-side, it would look like this: Along the x-axis you will have (frontal-eyes open, frontal-eyes closed) a gap, then (occipital-eyes open, occipital eyes closed). Make the same type of bar plot for beta wave power. Arrange the two plots with alpha wave power above the beta wave power so that the brain regions and treatments line up vertically.</li>
</ol></li>
<li>Your second question <strong>must</strong> involve comparing across <em>handwriting, cursive, and typing</em>.
<ol type="A">
<li>For example, <em>“Is there any difference in gamma waves in the frontal lobe across the modes of handwriting, cursive, or typing for the notetaking strategy?”</em></li>
</ol></li>
<li>Come up with two additional questions to address with this dataset. This is a large dataset, we will demonstrate some ways you can manipulate the data by subsetting the larger table to make comparisons easier. We encourage you to explore many aspects of your data to find interesting patterns before deciding on which comparisons to present in your final report.</li>
</ol></li>
</ol>
</section>
</section>
<section id="food-for-thought" class="level1">
<h1>Food for thought</h1>
<ol type="1">
<li><p>How does the human anatomy make it difficult to record and electroencephalogram or EEG?</p></li>
<li><p>What are common causes of the artifacts you recorded in Exercise 1? Name at least 3.</p></li>
<li><p>In exercise 2, under what conditions did you see alpha waves more clearly? What are alpha waves thought to indicate?</p></li>
<li><p>Where do you think motor activity would appear in your data?</p></li>
<li><p>Look at your Spectral Analysis from when the volunteer had their eyes shut. At what range do you have the greatest peak? What type of brain waves does the Spectral Analysis suggest is active? Compare this with the same for the eyes open treatment.</p></li>
<li><p>What is the purpose of taking a control measurement with hand movement only?</p></li>
<li><p>Which activities were easier or more difficult for the subject to perform? Which types of waves are more abundant during more difficult activities?</p></li>
</ol>
</section>
<section id="after-lab" class="level1">
<h1>After Lab:</h1>
<ul>
<li>This will be a group lab report.</li>
<li>Please divide the work of writing the report <strong>by experiment</strong>, so that each person benefits from the experience of writing the intro, methods, results, and discussion. This will also ensure that the ideas are better connected between sections.</li>
<li>Please think about effective figures for this interesting lab, and the results will jump out at you. It will also be easier to write the discussion. In the discussion circle back to the hypothesis and really try to interpret your results in light of physiological mechanisms.</li>
<li>In the discussion end by synthesizing what you learned. Try to bring together aspects of the separate experiments to reflect back on what you learned. What did you learn about the processing of different notetaking strategies or scribing modalities, and anything else you may have tested?</li>
<li>Please remember to include respective contributions.</li>
</ul>



</section>

<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-bibliography"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">References</h2><div id="refs" class="references csl-bib-body hanging-indent" data-entry-spacing="0">
<div id="ref-Bekkers:2011" class="csl-entry">
Bekkers, John M. 2011. <span>“Pyramidal Neurons.”</span> <em>Curr Biol</em> 21 (24): R975. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.cub.2011.10.037">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.cub.2011.10.037</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-Meer:2017" class="csl-entry">
Meer, Audrey L. H. van der, and F. R. (Ruud) van der Weel. 2017. <span>“Only Three Fingers Write, but the Whole Brain Works†: A High-Density EEG Study Showing Advantages of Drawing over Typing for Learning.”</span> <em>Frontiers in Psychology</em> 8. <a href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fpsyg.2017.00706">https://doi.org/10.3389/fpsyg.2017.00706</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-Ose-Askvik:2020" class="csl-entry">
Ose Askvik, Eva, F. R. (Ruud) van der Weel, and Audrey L. H. van der Meer. 2020. <span>“The Importance of Cursive Handwriting over Typewriting for Learning in the Classroom: A High-Density EEG Study of 12-Year-Old Children and Young Adults.”</span> <em>Frontiers in Psychology</em> 11. <a href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fpsyg.2020.01810">https://doi.org/10.3389/fpsyg.2020.01810</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-Vibell:2023" class="csl-entry">
Vibell, Jonas. in prep. <span>“Ch. 3 Electroencephalography.”</span> In.
</div>
</div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>week 13</category>
  <category>labs</category>
  <category>electrical activity</category>
  <category>electrophysiology</category>
  <category>human</category>
  <category>EEG</category>
  <category>brain waves</category>
  <category>synapses</category>
  <guid>https://mbutler808.github.io/animalphys-2025/labs/Lab11-human-eeg/Lab11.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 14 Nov 2024 10:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Labs 9 and 10: Vertebrate Skeletal Muscle</title>
  <dc:creator>Marguerite Butler</dc:creator>
  <link>https://mbutler808.github.io/animalphys-2025/labs/Lab9-10-toad-muscle/Lab9-10.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<section id="before-lab" class="level1">
<h1>Before Lab</h1>
<p>The first week will be a group lab on toad muscle. You should develop a hypothesis that you will test the following week for your <strong>independent lab</strong>.</p>
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-note callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
Prepare for lab by:
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<ul>
<li>Read the lab manual for this weekʻs experiment [<a href="Lab9-10-toad-muscle-protocol.pdf">Lab 9/10</a>]<br>
</li>
<li>Outline the [<a href="../../labs-misc/lab-notebook.html#sec-prelab">Prelab</a>] in your lab notebook. <strong>Summarize</strong> the important points for this experiment.</li>
<li>Draft hypotheses for each experiment</li>
<li>Time permitting, outline (write a topic setence and bullet point any supporting points that come to mind):
<ul>
<li>Umbrella idea</li>
<li>Mechanism 1</li>
<li>Mechanism 2</li>
<li>…</li>
<li>end with a paragraph of your hypotheses</li>
</ul></li>
<li>For the <strong>methods</strong>, outline:
<ul>
<li>subjects</li>
<li>equiptment</li>
<li>experimental treatments (be sure to note what <strong>variables</strong> are changing) and controls or comparisons</li>
<li>analysis</li>
</ul></li>
<li>Do Quiz on Laulima (open 24 hrs before lab) for lab 9. No quiz for lab 10.</li>
<li>Please bring a laptop with you to lab, if possible, to analyze your experimental results.</li>
<li><strong>Draft hypotheses for your independent lab</strong> (next week Lab 10). Get approval from your TA during lab 9.</li>
<li><strong>For lab 10</strong>, you will help your group members collect their data, but you will <em>design, execute, and write up your own independent lab report</em>.<br>
</li>
</ul>
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-tip callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
Donʻt get confused!
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<ul>
<li>EMGs measure muscle electrical activity</li>
<li>Donʻt confuse depolarization with FORCE DEVELOPMENT</li>
<li>Explain in your intro how force is developed by the binding of actin with myosin (via crossbridge formation)</li>
<li>[<a href="lab_muscle.pdf">Helpful slides</a>]</li>
</ul>
</div>
</div>
<section id="in-lab" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="in-lab">In Lab:</h2>
<ul>
<li>Lab 9 manual [<a href="Lab9-10-toad-muscle-protocol.pdf">pdf</a>] . Record data in your lab notebook.</li>
<li>You should have plenty of time to complete the data collection and your figures during lab.<br>
</li>
<li>This will be a Group Lab. Begin planning with your partners as you work.</li>
<li>Start an outline with your lab partners and start outlining your discussion points, and the rest of the report. Use your time wisely to brainstorm as you work.<br>
</li>
<li>Get your <strong>hypothesis for your independent lab</strong> approved by your TA prior to leaving.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="after-lab" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="after-lab">After Lab:</h2>
<ul>
<li>Group lab report due next week. See the guidance at the end of the manual [<a href="Lab9-10-toad-muscle-protocol.pdf">pdf</a>]<br>
</li>
<li>Always follow the content guidelines: [<a href="../../labs-misc/handouts/Revised_Zool430L_lab_report_guidelines.pdf">grading guidelines</a>] [<a href="../../labs-misc/handouts/Zool430lab_report_guidelines.pdf">old style</a>]</li>
<li>It is a good idea to divide up the work of writing the lab <strong>by experiment</strong>. That way, <em>each person writes a portion of the intro, methods, results, and discussion for their <strong>hypothesis</strong></em>.</li>
<li>Work out your timeline with your lab partners during lab (and plan a face-to-face meet up <strong><em>so that everyone has a chance to comment and edit</em></strong> before the lab is submitted.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="next-week-independent-labs" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="next-week-independent-labs">Next Week: Independent labs!</h2>
<ul>
<li>You will help each other collect the data, but your hypothesis, analysis, and report will be your own.</li>
<li>For those of you wishing to look at muscle architecture, it is a good idea to compute the Physiological Cross-Sectional Area (the CSA through the perpendicular direction through the muscle fibers). To do so, take the mass of the dissected muscle (use the analytical balance upstairs, ask your TA), and bisect the muscle to look at the pennation angle of the fibers. Take a clear photo of your bisected muscle next to a ruler to measure fiber length (average) and pennation angle.</li>
<li>You can calculate Physiological Cross Sectional Area as:</li>
</ul>
<p><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%0APCSA%20=%20%5Cfrac%7B%5Ctext%7Bmuscle%20volume%7D%7D%7B%5Ctext%7Bfiber%20length%7D%7D%20=%20%5Cfrac%7B%5Ctext%7Bmuscle%20mass%7D%7D%7B%5Crho%5Ccdot%20%5Ctext%7Bfiber%20length%7D%7D%0A"></p>
<p>Where <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%5Crho"> is the density of the muscle and is 1.06 g/ml.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://mbutler808.github.io/animalphys-2025/images/256px-Fiederung.svg.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>Figure 1: Pennate muscle fiber arrangements. The green lines represent PCSA; the blue lines represent ACSA. Image credit: Uwe Gille, CC BY-SA 3.0 <a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/3.0" class="uri">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/3.0</a>, via Wikimedia Commons</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>


</section>
</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>week 9</category>
  <category>week 10</category>
  <category>labs</category>
  <category>muscle</category>
  <category>in situ</category>
  <category>force</category>
  <category>stretch</category>
  <category>recruitment</category>
  <category>twitch</category>
  <category>tetanus</category>
  <category>temperature</category>
  <guid>https://mbutler808.github.io/animalphys-2025/labs/Lab9-10-toad-muscle/Lab9-10.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 05 Nov 2024 10:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://mbutler808.github.io/animalphys-2025/images/lab8-muscle.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="67" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Lab 8: Human Electromyography (EMG)</title>
  <dc:creator>Marguerite Butler</dc:creator>
  <link>https://mbutler808.github.io/animalphys-2025/labs/Lab8-human-emg/Lab8.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<section id="acknowledgements" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="acknowledgements">Acknowledgements</h3>
<p>Material for this lab was borrowed and adopted from</p>
<ul>
<li>Electromyography Protocol. Written by Staff of ADInstruments for LabChart 8.</li>
</ul>
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-note callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
Prepare for lab by:
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<ul>
<li>Watch the Muscle [<a href="https://youtu.be/6Z39ZqgixfY">podcast</a>].</li>
<li>Read the lab manual below.<br>
</li>
<li>Read from Eckert ch.&nbsp;10 [<a href="https://drive.google.com/drive/folders/1BSLdFEnnLw0N6z-ouBI-Y50ZeY_5FItl?usp=share_link">readings</a>]: Mechanics of Muscle Contraction 375-379, Active State, Twitch and Tetanus 391- 392, Motor Control vertebrate 410 - 411</li>
<li>Write the [<a href="../../labs-misc/lab-notebook.html#sec-prelab">Prelab</a>] in your lab notebook. <em><strong>Please DO NOT copy the lab manual word for word.</strong> Your task is to <strong>summarize</strong> the important points for this experiment.</em></li>
<li>This week, draft hypotheses for each experiment, then outline the structure of the introdution for your future lab report. Your outline of paragraphs for the <strong>introduction</strong> should come together like this:
<ul>
<li>Umbrella idea</li>
<li>introduce mechanism 1</li>
<li>introduce mechanism 2</li>
<li>…</li>
<li>end with a paragraph of your hypotheses</li>
<li><strong>For the prelab please have the hypotheses, figuring out how many ideas you have to cover, and writing a topic sentence for each paragraph.</strong><br>
</li>
</ul></li>
<li>For the <strong>methods</strong>, outline:
<ul>
<li>subjects</li>
<li>equiptment</li>
<li>experimental treatments (be sure to note what <strong>variables</strong> are changing) and controls or comparisons</li>
<li>analysis</li>
</ul></li>
<li>Do Quiz on Laulima (open 24 hrs before lab).</li>
<li>Please bring a laptop with you to lab, if possible, to analyze your experimental results.</li>
</ul>
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-note callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
Summary
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<ul>
<li>We will explore the electrical activity of skeletal muscle in relation to the generation of force and movement. In this experiment you will record electromyograms in human subjects during voluntary muscle action. We will explore various properties of motor control and the activity of opposing muscle groups.</li>
</ul>
</div>
</div>
</section>
<section id="background" class="level1">
<h1>Background</h1>
<p>Skeletal muscles do the majority of the work for locomotion and support of the animal skeleton. Some of the functions that skeletal muscles perform include: producing movement, stiffening the body to maintain posture, and generating heat, among others. Skeletal (striated) muscles attach to the skeleton by tendons (strong bundles of collagen fibers), aponeuroses (flat, sheet like tendons) and fascia (bands of connective tissue), and can cross joints. Muscles have a heirarchichal structure where each muscle (the organ level) is made up of individual muscle fibers organized in fascicles (Figure&nbsp;1). A typical skeletal muscle in a human contains thousands of muscle fibers.</p>
<div id="fig-muscle" class="quarto-float quarto-figure quarto-figure-center anchored">
<figure class="quarto-float quarto-float-fig figure">
<div aria-describedby="fig-muscle-caption-0ceaefa1-69ba-4598-a22c-09a6ac19f8ca">
<img src="https://mbutler808.github.io/animalphys-2025/images/lab8-muscle.png" class="img-fluid figure-img">
</div>
<figcaption class="quarto-float-caption-bottom quarto-float-caption quarto-float-fig" id="fig-muscle-caption-0ceaefa1-69ba-4598-a22c-09a6ac19f8ca">
Figure&nbsp;1: Skeletal muscle organization from muscle to fascicle to fiber to myofibril.
</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Voluntary movements are controlled by instuctions from the central nervous system. Each skeletal muscle fiber is innervated by a branch of a motor axon or neuron. Each motor neuron innervates many muscle fibers. The motor neuron and all of the fibers it innervates is called a “motor unit” (Figure&nbsp;2). All of the motor neurons that innervate a single muscle is called a “motor pool”.</p>
<div id="fig-motor-unit" class="quarto-float quarto-figure quarto-figure-center anchored">
<figure class="quarto-float quarto-float-fig figure">
<div aria-describedby="fig-motor-unit-caption-0ceaefa1-69ba-4598-a22c-09a6ac19f8ca">
<img src="https://mbutler808.github.io/animalphys-2025/images/lab8-motor-unit.png" class="img-fluid figure-img">
</div>
<figcaption class="quarto-float-caption-bottom quarto-float-caption quarto-float-fig" id="fig-motor-unit-caption-0ceaefa1-69ba-4598-a22c-09a6ac19f8ca">
Figure&nbsp;2: Motor neurons descend from the CNS and innervates many muscle fibers. The motor unit = motor neuron + all the fibers it innervates.
</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>When an action potential travels down a motor neuron, the action potential typically activates all of the muscle fibers it innervates, resulting in contraction of all the muscle fibers in the motor unit. This activation process involves (1) the initiation of an action potential, either voluntarily or as a result of electrical stimulation of a peripheral nerve, (2) conduction of the action potential along the nerve fiber, (3) release of neurotransmitter at the neuromuscular junction, and (4) depolarization of the muscle membrane with resultant contraction of the muscle fibers.</p>
<p>During a contraction, therefore, there is synchronous activity in a number of fibers in the same muscle. The electrical signal from a contracting muscle can be recorded using skin surface electrodes. This recording of muscle activity is called an electromyogram or EMG. The raw surface EMG signal reflects the electrical activity of the underlying muscle fibers active at that time. Motor units fire asynchronously and result in what often looks like a chaotic signal.</p>
<p>The raw EMG signal during voluntary contractions may be processed in various ways to indicate the intensity of EMG activity. In the method we will used here, known as the root mean square (RMS), the EMG signal is squared, averaged, and the square root calculated. This is what is called a geometric mean, and has the effect of counting both the negative and positive deflections of the signal, as well as smoothing out individual spikes, so that the change in muscle activity over time is much clearer.</p>
<p>Activation or “recruitment” of greater numbers of motor units result in greater numbers of fibers contracting, producing a greater density of action potentials (and may represent the electrical activity of perhaps thousands of fibers). With greater recruitment, we also see greater muscle force.</p>
<p>Another way to increase force output is to increase the frequency of firing. A single muscle contraction is transitory and called a “twitch” but a train of action potentials will result in a fused “tetanus” and sustained contraction. In either case, the EMG activity is not a regular series of waves like the ECG, but a chaotic burst of overlapping spike-like signals. <em>Why do you think this is the case?</em></p>
<p>In this experiment, you will record EMG activity during voluntary contractions of skeletal muscle groups, focusing on the biceps and triceps muscles of the arm, which are antagonistic muscles that control movement at the elbow.</p>
<section id="what-you-will-do-in-the-laboratory" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="what-you-will-do-in-the-laboratory">What you will do in the laboratory</h3>
<ol type="1">
<li><em>Setup</em>. Check that the equiptment are set up correctly and ready to record.</li>
<li><em>Muscle activation with increasing load</em>. You will increase the load on the muscle-joint system, and measure changes in electrical activation of the biceps.</li>
<li><em>Alternating activity and coactivation</em>. You will explore the function of antagonistic muscles and demonstrate coactivation.</li>
<li><em>Several of your own experiments</em>. See below for ideas.</li>
</ol>
</section>
<section id="equipment" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="equipment">Equipment</h2>
<ul>
<li>PowerLab data acquisition system</li>
<li>LabChart 8 or later</li>
<li>5 Lead Shielded Bio Amp Cable</li>
<li>Shielded Lead Wires (5 Snap-on)</li>
<li>Dry Earth Strap</li>
<li>(optional) Stimulating Bar Electrode</li>
<li>Electrode Cream or Paste</li>
<li>Abrasive Gel or Pad</li>
<li>Alcohol Swabs</li>
<li>Gauze or cotton ball (or similar material)</li>
<li>Ballpoint pen</li>
<li>Scissors</li>
<li>Four books or objects of similar weight (about 1 kg/2.2 lbs each)</li>
</ul>
</section>
</section>
<section id="procedure" class="level1">
<h1>Procedure</h1>
<section id="subject-preparation" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="subject-preparation">Subject preparation</h2>
<ol type="1">
<li>Make sure the PowerLab is turned off and the USB cable is connected to the computer.</li>
<li>Connect the 5 Lead Shielded Bio Amp Cable to the Bio Amp Connector on the front panel of the PowerLab (Figure&nbsp;3). The hardware needs to be connected before you open the settings file.</li>
<li>Have the subject remove all jewelry or metal objects in contact with their skin. Visually inspect all of the cup electrodes and make sure that the cups are clean and bare for a good electrical signal. If necessary, clean them gently (they are fragile) - ask your TA for help.</li>
<li>Plug the lead of the dry earth strap into the Earth connection of the Bio Amp cable. Firmly attach the dry earth strap (electrode) around the palm or wrist of the volunteer. Ensure that the fuzzy side of the dry earth strap is in full contact with the skin.</li>
<li>Gently abrade the skin or swab with alcohol to make good electrical contact with the electrodes (Figure&nbsp;3).</li>
</ol>
<div id="fig-setup" class="quarto-float quarto-figure quarto-figure-center anchored">
<figure class="quarto-float quarto-float-fig figure">
<div aria-describedby="fig-setup-caption-0ceaefa1-69ba-4598-a22c-09a6ac19f8ca">
<img src="https://mbutler808.github.io/animalphys-2025/images/lab8-setup.png" class="img-fluid figure-img">
</div>
<figcaption class="quarto-float-caption-bottom quarto-float-caption quarto-float-fig" id="fig-setup-caption-0ceaefa1-69ba-4598-a22c-09a6ac19f8ca">
Figure&nbsp;3: Electrode placement and cable setup.
</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<ol start="6" type="1">
<li>With a ballpoint pen, mark two small crosses where the electrodes will be placed on the biceps muscle (Figure&nbsp;4). The crosses should be 2–3 cm apart and aligned with the long axis of the arm (along the length of the muscle). Do the same for the triceps muscle.</li>
<li>Fill each disk electrode with electrode cream. Place the electrodes onto the skin over the crosses, and fasten them firmly in place with masking tape.</li>
<li>Plug the leads of the EMG recording electrodes into the Bio Amp cable, as shown in (Figure&nbsp;3). Polarity doesn’t matter for EMG, but do make sure that the two leads (+ &amp; -) for each channel are attached to the same muscle, and the biceps recording on channel 1, and triceps recording on channel 2. Check that all electrodes are properly connected before proceeding.</li>
</ol>
<div id="fig-antagonists" class="quarto-float quarto-figure quarto-figure-center anchored">
<figure class="quarto-float quarto-float-fig figure">
<div aria-describedby="fig-antagonists-caption-0ceaefa1-69ba-4598-a22c-09a6ac19f8ca">
<img src="https://mbutler808.github.io/animalphys-2025/images/lab8-antagonists.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img">
</div>
<figcaption class="quarto-float-caption-bottom quarto-float-caption quarto-float-fig" id="fig-antagonists-caption-0ceaefa1-69ba-4598-a22c-09a6ac19f8ca">
Figure&nbsp;4: The human biceps and triceps, an antagonistic muscle pair.
</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</section>
<section id="starting-the-software" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="starting-the-software">Starting the software</h2>
<ol type="1">
<li>Start Chart using the EMG lab settings file. Four channels should appear: the <strong>raw EMG signal</strong> and the <strong>RMS activity</strong> (a summation and smoothing of the raw EMG) for each of the mucles, the biceps and triceps.</li>
<li>Make sure that the raw EMG channel is set to the “Bioamp”, and that the computed input (summation of the EMG) is reading the channel for the raw EMG channel. To do this, under the “Setup” menu choose “setup channels” and check that the input is “Bioamp” (and not “Input Amplifier”). You may have to change the inputs to match the correct channel number. If you are using the new setup, you may have to change and restart Chart (several times) with the Bioamp cable connected for it to appear in the menu. If you are using the old setup, the little green light on the front of the Bioamp should be on. In either case, the channel setup window should indicate “Bioamp”. Ask your TA for help if needed.</li>
</ol>
</section>
</section>
<section id="exercise-1-activation-with-increasing-demand" class="level1">
<h1>Exercise 1: Activation with increasing demand</h1>
<p>We will explore voluntary muscle contractions with increasing demand, and how activation of motor neurons changes to meet demand. (Think about what is happening in terms of muscle physiology).</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>The volunteer should sit in a relaxed position, with elbow bent to 90° with the palm facing upwards. He or she should use the other hand to grasp the wrist of the recorded arm.</li>
<li>Choose the Bio Amplifier… command from the raw EMG Channel pop-up menu and make sure the range is set to 2mV, High Pass to 10Hz, and Low Pass to 200Hz.</li>
<li>Ask the volunteer to make a strong contraction of their muscle. For biceps muscle, a strong contraction can be generated by trying to bend the recorded arm further and resisting this movement with his or her other arm. (For triceps muscle, a strong contraction can be produced by trying to straighten out the recorded arm and resisting this movement with his or her other arm.) Observe the signal (Figure&nbsp;5) and adjust the value in the range pop-up menu so that the maximal electrical response occupies about one half to two-thirds of the full scale. Do the same range adjustment for the triceps recording channel.</li>
</ol>
<div id="fig-emg" class="quarto-float quarto-figure quarto-figure-center anchored">
<figure class="quarto-float quarto-float-fig figure">
<div aria-describedby="fig-emg-caption-0ceaefa1-69ba-4598-a22c-09a6ac19f8ca">
<img src="https://mbutler808.github.io/animalphys-2025/images/lab8-emg.png" class="img-fluid figure-img">
</div>
<figcaption class="quarto-float-caption-bottom quarto-float-caption quarto-float-fig" id="fig-emg-caption-0ceaefa1-69ba-4598-a22c-09a6ac19f8ca">
Figure&nbsp;5: Raw EMG signal from a strong muscle contractions in the biceps
</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<ol start="4" type="1">
<li>Start recording. The volunteer should perform a maximum contraction of the biceps and then the triceps with the EMG electrodes attached. <strong>Comment</strong> on each muscle contraction. Stop recording, and check that the integrated signal traces are clearly visible in the Chart window and look something like (Figure&nbsp;6). If not, use the Amplitude Axis controls in their channels to adjust the vertical scale so that they are visible.</li>
<li>The volunteer should once more sit in a relaxed position, with his or her elbow unsupported and bent to 90° with the palm facing upwards.</li>
<li>Resume recording. Prepare a comment “one book”. After a few seconds, place one weight (a book) on the hand of the subject and comment. Leave it on for three seconds to record the change in the EMG, then remove the weight. Repeat this process for two, then three, then four books, for a series of increasing weights. Stop recording and save your data.</li>
</ol>
<div id="fig-rms" class="quarto-float quarto-figure quarto-figure-center anchored">
<figure class="quarto-float quarto-float-fig figure">
<div aria-describedby="fig-rms-caption-0ceaefa1-69ba-4598-a22c-09a6ac19f8ca">
<img src="https://mbutler808.github.io/animalphys-2025/images/lab8-rms-EMG.png" class="img-fluid figure-img">
</div>
<figcaption class="quarto-float-caption-bottom quarto-float-caption quarto-float-fig" id="fig-rms-caption-0ceaefa1-69ba-4598-a22c-09a6ac19f8ca">
Figure&nbsp;6: Burst of EMG activity in biceps muscle while supporting a weight, along with the RMS activity.
</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<section id="analysis-change-in-contractile-activity" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="analysis-change-in-contractile-activity">Analysis: Change in contractile activity</h2>
<ol type="1">
<li>Scroll through the recorded data and note the changes in activity in the raw biceps channel. Note also that placing weights on the hand gives rise to little or no activity in the triceps muscle. Select a small part of the “Biceps” activity and examine it in Zoom View. The raw EMG signal is composed of many up-and-down spikes (Figure&nbsp;5).</li>
<li>Note the relationship between the “Biceps” channel and the “RMS Biceps” channel. The height of the RMS trace reflects the overall activity of the raw EMG signal and gives a simpler view of the muscle’s electrical activity. Note the changes in the RMS trace as books were added and removed.<br>
</li>
<li>Select data points from “RMS Biceps” when books were added. Enter these values in Table&nbsp;1. In this experiment, the height of the trace correlates with the force produced by the muscle. (why?)</li>
</ol>
<div id="tbl-book-force" class="quarto-float quarto-figure quarto-figure-center anchored">
<figure class="quarto-float quarto-float-tbl figure">
<figcaption class="quarto-float-caption-top quarto-float-caption quarto-float-tbl" id="tbl-book-force-caption-0ceaefa1-69ba-4598-a22c-09a6ac19f8ca">
Table&nbsp;1: Electrical activity produced by adding books
</figcaption>
<div aria-describedby="tbl-book-force-caption-0ceaefa1-69ba-4598-a22c-09a6ac19f8ca">
<table class="caption-top table">
<thead>
<tr class="header">
<th>N books</th>
<th>RMS biceps amplitude (mV.s)</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr class="odd">
<td>1</td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>2</td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>3</td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>4</td>
<td></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</div>
</figure>
</div>
</section>
</section>
<section id="excercise-2-alternating-activity-and-coactivation" class="level1">
<h1>Excercise 2: Alternating activity and coactivation</h1>
<p>We will examine the activity of antagonist muscles and the phenomenon of coactivation.</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>Use the following settings: sampling rate = 200 m/s, digital filter (low pass) = 100Hz. Connect the push button switch to one of the channels on the PowerLab to record the start and end of each muscle flexion.</li>
<li>The volunteer should sit in a relaxed position, with his or her elbow bent to 90° with the palm facing upwards. He or she should use the other hand to grasp the wrist of the recorded arm.</li>
<li>Ask the volunteer to activate the biceps and triceps alternately. The biceps muscle can be activated by trying to bend the recorded arm further and resisting this movement with the other arm. The triceps muscle can be activated by trying to straighten out the recorded arm and resisting this movement with the other arm. The volunteer should practice this alternating pattern until it feels like both muscles are being equally activated in turn. Pause breifly after each activation; this makes the data cleaner for analysis.</li>
<li>Begin recording. Record a baseline for 30sec.<br>
</li>
<li>Add a comment “activation”, and have the volunteer use the alternating patttern of activation for 30 sec.&nbsp;Have the volunteer call out which muscle and comment at each activation. Stop recording and save the data file.</li>
</ol>
<section id="analysis-alternating-activity-and-coactivation" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="analysis-alternating-activity-and-coactivation">Analysis: Alternating activity and coactivation</h2>
<ol type="1">
<li>Scroll through the recorded data and observe the EMG traces for both the biceps and triceps. Note the large-scale alternation of activity in the biceps and triceps relative to the marker at the start of each muscle contraction.</li>
<li>Note also that when the biceps muscle is activated forcefully, there is a minor increase of activity in the triceps. Correspondingly, there is a minor increase of activity in the biceps trace when the triceps is activated. This phenomenon is called ‘coactivation’. <em>How might this stabilize the elbow joint?</em></li>
<li>Collect data from the RMS EMG peaks for each muscle during contracton of the biceps and triceps (Table&nbsp;2).</li>
</ol>
<div id="tbl-coactivation" class="quarto-float quarto-figure quarto-figure-center anchored">
<figure class="quarto-float quarto-float-tbl figure">
<figcaption class="quarto-float-caption-top quarto-float-caption quarto-float-tbl" id="tbl-coactivation-caption-0ceaefa1-69ba-4598-a22c-09a6ac19f8ca">
Table&nbsp;2: Electrical activity produced during coactivation
</figcaption>
<div aria-describedby="tbl-coactivation-caption-0ceaefa1-69ba-4598-a22c-09a6ac19f8ca">
<table class="caption-top table">
<thead>
<tr class="header">
<th>Muscle contracting</th>
<th>RMS biceps amplitude (mV.s)</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr class="odd">
<td>biceps</td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>triceps</td>
<td></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</div>
</figure>
</div>
</section>
</section>
<section id="additional-exercises" class="level1">
<h1>Additional Exercises</h1>
<p>Below is a list of additional exercises to do. Pick several of these (at least 3) and develop appropriate experimental approaches to understanding how muscle EMGs vary as a result of each of these factors.</p>
<ul>
<li>Isometric vs.&nbsp;isotonic contraction (no change in muscle length vs.&nbsp;no change in muscle force [approximately])</li>
<li>EMG during exercise of a muscle group to exhaustion (and after recovery)</li>
<li>EMGs from different volunteers with different muscle mass or build (donʻt forget to take some measurement of the muscle differences for the comparison)</li>
<li>EMGs during muscle contraction of different speeds (e.g.&nbsp;lifting book slowly vs quickly)</li>
<li>Your own exercise</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="food-for-thought" class="level1">
<h1>Food For Thought</h1>
<ul>
<li>Unlike the discrete waveform from an electrocardiogram, the electromyogram waveform is irregular. Why do you suppose that is?</li>
<li>How did the EMG trace change when you added weights (increased load)? What do your results indicate? Would this be an example of isometric or isotonic contraction?</li>
<li>What is coactivation? Why do you think this phenomenon occurs?</li>
<li>What happened to the triceps EMG trace when the biceps was activated? Does the data support the phenomenon of coactivation?</li>
<li>What do you expect to see during isotonic vs.&nbsp;isometric contraction? How do your data illustrate these major results in muscle physiology. Why do you suppose these patterns exist?</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="after-lab" class="level1">
<h1>After Lab:</h1>
<ul>
<li>This will be a group lab report.</li>
<li>Please divide the work of writing the report <strong>by experiment</strong>, so that each person benefits from the experience of writing the intro, methods, results, and discussion. This will also ensure that the ideas are better connected between sections.</li>
<li>Please think about effective figures for this interesting lab, and the results will jump out at you. It will also be easier to write the discussion. In the discussion circle back to the hypothesis and really try to interpret your results in light of muscle physiology mechanisms.</li>
<li>Please remember to include respective contributions.</li>
</ul>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>week 10</category>
  <category>labs</category>
  <category>muscle</category>
  <category>human</category>
  <category>EMG</category>
  <category>electromyography</category>
  <category>force</category>
  <category>motion</category>
  <category>electrical activity</category>
  <guid>https://mbutler808.github.io/animalphys-2025/labs/Lab8-human-emg/Lab8.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 29 Oct 2024 10:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Lab 7: Compound Action Potentials in the Toad Sciatic Nerve</title>
  <dc:creator>Marguerite Butler</dc:creator>
  <link>https://mbutler808.github.io/animalphys-2025/labs/Lab7-toad-nerve/Lab7.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<section id="acknowledgements" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="acknowledgements">Acknowledgements</h3>
<p>Material for this lab was borrowed and adopted from</p>
<ul>
<li>Frog Nerve Compound Action Potentials Protocol. Written by Staff of ADInstruments, Dr.&nbsp;Duncan MacKenzie, and Dr.&nbsp;Valerie G. Kalter.</li>
</ul>
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-note callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
Prepare for lab by:
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<ul>
<li>Watch the Neurons and Signal Propagation [<a href="../../posts/2023-10-02-neurons">podcasts</a>].</li>
<li>Read the lab manual below.<br>
</li>
<li>Write the [<a href="../../labs-misc/lab-notebook.html#sec-prelab">Prelab</a>] in your lab notebook.</li>
<li>Do Quiz on Laulima (open 24 hrs before lab).</li>
<li>Please bring a laptop with you to lab, if possible, to analyze your experimental results.</li>
</ul>
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-note callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
Summary
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<ul>
<li>This week, dissect the toadʻs sciatic nerve, one of the longest motor neurons. Stimulating the frogʻs sciatic nerve will fire a large number of individual nerve fibers (neurons). You will measure the aggregate electrical activity of the nerve known as compound action potentials (CAPs) to explore various properties of nerve function.</li>
</ul>
</div>
</div>
</section>
<section id="background" class="level1 page-columns page-full">
<h1>Background</h1>
<p>The fundamental unit of the nervous system is the <strong>neuron</strong>. Neurons and other <strong>excitable cells</strong> produce <strong>action potentials</strong> when they receive electrical or chemical stimulation. The action potential begins an electrical signal reaches specialized voltage-sensitive membrane sodium (Na<img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%5E+">) ion channels. When these voltages are above threshhold, these sodium channels open. The large increase in sodium permeability results in membrane depolarization (in other words, the opening of the channels results in Na<img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%5E+"> ions flooding inwards, changing the voltage across the membrane). This is followed by repolarization as the sodium permeability returns to its low baseline value and potassium (K<img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%5E+">) ion permeability is transiently increased. Note that the actual numbers of ions moving during each action potential, however, are very small and cell ion concentrations are not altered measurably.</p>
<p>Action potentials are “all-or-none” events. Once an action potential begins, it propagates down the length of the <strong>axon</strong>. When the action potential reaches the end of the axon, a <strong>neurotransmitter</strong> is typically released into the <strong>synapse</strong>. Measuring action potentials from single neurons requires highly specialized equipment. Instead, you will record <strong>compound action potentials</strong> (or <strong>CAP</strong>) from an isolated peripheral nerve, the frog sciatic nerve, which contains hundreds of axons (Figure&nbsp;1).</p>

<div class="no-row-height column-margin column-container"><div class="">
<div id="fig-nerve-pizza" class="quarto-float quarto-figure quarto-figure-center anchored">
<figure class="quarto-float quarto-float-fig figure">
<div aria-describedby="fig-nerve-pizza-caption-0ceaefa1-69ba-4598-a22c-09a6ac19f8ca">
<img src="https://mbutler808.github.io/animalphys-2025/images/lab7-nerve-pizza.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img">
</div>
<figcaption class="quarto-float-caption-bottom quarto-float-caption quarto-float-fig" id="fig-nerve-pizza-caption-0ceaefa1-69ba-4598-a22c-09a6ac19f8ca">
Figure&nbsp;1: Vertebrate nerves bundles of many individual neurons. This is an idealized cross-section of a peripheral nerve, for example the sciatic nerve that runs from the spinal column to all of the muscles of the hind limb (a motor nerve).
</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</div></div><p>Peripheral nerves include <em>afferent</em> (sensory) nerves and <em>efferent</em> (motor and autonomic) nerves. The individual axons within the nerve vary in diameter and myelination. It is important to appreciate that <em>the threshold voltage required to produce an action potential in each axon reflects the <strong>diameter</strong> of the individual axon</em> – <strong>large diameter axons are stimulated at lower voltages than smaller diameter axons</strong>. The <strong>myelin sheath</strong> is composed of lipid bylayer (fatty substances) and acts as electrical insulation or membrane resistance, which will greatly increase the speed of electrical impulses. <em>Thus, variation in diameter and myelination will in turn influence excitability, threshold, and speed of conduction.</em></p>
<p>Therefore, the nerve <strong>compound action potentials (CAPs) you will record at any stimulus voltage represent the summed “all or nothing” action potentials only from those axons that are excited at that voltage.</strong> As the stimulus voltage is increased, more and more axons will be excited until eventually all of the axons within the nerve are excited. Thus, the magnitude of the CAP will increase with increased stimulus strength. After that point (the maximal response), <strong>supramaximal</strong> stimuli will have no further effect on the magnitude of the CAP. Also, because axons of different diameters have different conduction velocities, as more and more axons are excited, the peaks of the CAP will often broaden in shape as the waveforms with slightly different timings are averaged together).</p>
<p>Note that CAPs arise from <strong>extracellular</strong> stimulation of the nerve and are recorded by extracellular electrodes, and therefore it will not look like the classical pictures that you see of single nerve action potentials recorded using an <strong>intracellular</strong> electrode. Your experimental setup will be similar to that in Figure&nbsp;2. What you are recording here is the <em>difference in potential between two extracellular electrodes</em> (the voltage difference between the recording electrodes in Figure&nbsp;2).</p>
<p><em>Take a moment to understand the signal.</em> Remember that you are measuring from the outside of the nerve (<em>outside</em> is <em>positive</em> at rest, inside is negative). In the absence of a stimulus, there is no difference, and you have a baseline recording; but following a stimulus, a wave of depolarization passes down the nerve (a in Figure&nbsp;2). As this wave crosses the first recording electrode, it becomes negative to the more distal electrode. By convention this difference is shown as a positive defection in the recording (red voltage - black voltage, b in Figure&nbsp;2). Then, when this wave reaches the second electrode, that electrode now becomes negative to the more proximal electrode and this results in a negative deflection in the recording (d in Figure&nbsp;2). Nerve propagation therefore results in a biphasic recording.</p>
<div id="fig-nerve-biphasic" class="quarto-float quarto-figure quarto-figure-center anchored">
<figure class="quarto-float quarto-float-fig figure">
<div aria-describedby="fig-nerve-biphasic-caption-0ceaefa1-69ba-4598-a22c-09a6ac19f8ca">
<img src="https://mbutler808.github.io/animalphys-2025/images/lab7-biphasic-frog-nerve.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img">
</div>
<figcaption class="quarto-float-caption-bottom quarto-float-caption quarto-float-fig" id="fig-nerve-biphasic-caption-0ceaefa1-69ba-4598-a22c-09a6ac19f8ca">
Figure&nbsp;2: Extracellular recording of an action potential conducted along the anuran sciatic nerve.
</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Because peripheral nerves are bundles of neurons, we can observe refractory periods in them as well. From the beginning of the CAP to the restoration of the <strong>resting membrane potentials</strong>, neurons are incapable of producing another action potential. This period is referred to as the <strong>refractory period</strong>, which can be divided into two phases. Initially there is the <strong>absolute</strong> refractory period, where it is impossible to initiate a second action potential. This is followed by the <strong>relative</strong> refractory period, where a stimulus of greater than normal intensity can elicit a response. (Why? What is happening during these periods?)</p>
<p>The importance of the CAP lies simply in the fact that it enables us to experimentally demonstrate aspects of nerve physiology. Clinically, CAPs are measured in patients to explore the peripheral nerve lesions and diseases.</p>
<section id="what-you-will-do-in-the-laboratory" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="what-you-will-do-in-the-laboratory">What you will do in the laboratory</h3>
<ol type="1">
<li><em>Setup and calibration of equipment</em>. In this exercise, you will check that the stimulating and recording connections are set up correctly.</li>
<li><em>Determination of threshold voltage and maximal CAP amplitude</em>. Here you will give the nerve a series of stimuli, each increasing in amplitude. You will then be able to calculate the threshold voltage for the nerve, as well as the voltage required for maximum CAP amplitude.</li>
<li><em>Determination of the refractory period</em>. In this part of the laboratory, you will deliver paired supramaximal stimuli to the nerve. The interval between these stimuli will be progressively decreased. The results will enable you to determine the relative and absolute refractory periods of your nerve.</li>
<li><em>Determination of nerve conduction velocity</em>. Here you will calculate the velocity of the CAP as it travels down the nerve.</li>
<li><em>Bi-Directionality of Nerve Conduction</em>. You will demonstrate the ability of a nerve to conduct signals in both directions.</li>
<li><em>Strength-Duration Relationships</em>. You will measure ability of a stimulus to elicit a response by changing the stimulus duration as well as its intensity (strength).</li>
</ol>
</section>
<section id="equipment" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="equipment">Equipment</h2>
<ul>
<li>PowerLab data acquisition system</li>
<li>LabChart 8 or later</li>
<li>Nerve Chamber</li>
<li>Stimulator Cable (BNC to Alligator Clips) (Note: These are the stimulating electrodes.)</li>
<li>Two Differential Pod Input Cables (DIN to Alligator Clips) (Note: These are the recording electrodes.)</li>
<li>One isolated frog sciatic nerve (<em>Rhinella marinus</em>)</li>
<li>Frog Ringer’s solution</li>
<li>Pasteur pipette</li>
<li>Filter paper, moistened with Ringer’s solution</li>
<li>Thread</li>
<li>Ruler</li>
<li>Dissection tools:
<ul>
<li>Petri dish</li>
<li>Sharp scissors or scalpel</li>
<li>Glass probe and hook for handling nerve</li>
<li>Bone shears</li>
<li>Blunt probe</li>
<li>Dissection tray with wax or pad</li>
<li>Dissection pins</li>
</ul></li>
</ul>
</section>
</section>
<section id="procedure" class="level1 page-columns page-full">
<h1>Procedure</h1>
<section id="setup-and-calibration-of-equiptment" class="level2 page-columns page-full">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="setup-and-calibration-of-equiptment">Setup and calibration of equiptment</h2>
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-tip callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
Important - wire hygiene!
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<ul>
<li>Before you begin, unwind (straigthen) all of your cables and wires so that there are <em>no coils</em>.</li>
<li>Ensure your power cables <strong>do not cross</strong> any information (USB or otherwise) or electrode wires.</li>
<li>Try to avoid crossing your electrode wires, and especially <strong>make sure your stimulating electrode wires do not touch the recording wires</strong>.</li>
<li>Good electrical contact while minimizing electrical noise is key to obtaining a clean and strong signal.</li>
</ul>
</div>
</div>
<ol type="1">
<li>Connect the red and black clips from the stimulator electrodes to two of the metal rungs on opposite sides of the Nerve Bath (Figure&nbsp;3). The distance between the electrodes should be 0.5 cm. It is not necessary to connect the green (ground) clip.</li>
<li>Connect the red (positive) BNC connector from the stimulator electrode to the positive (+) analog output connector on the PowerLab. Connect the black (negative) BNC connector from the stimulator electrode to the negative (–) analog output connector.</li>
<li>Connect the red and black leads from the first recording electrode to two of the metal rungs of the Nerve Bath (Figure&nbsp;3). Connect the 8-pin DIN connector to Input 1 of the PowerLab.</li>
<li>Connect the leads for the second recording electrode (black closer to stimulator, red farther), but place the microhooks further away from the stimulus electrode (Figure&nbsp;3). Attach the DIN connector to Input 2 on the PowerLab.</li>
</ol>
<div id="fig-setup" class="quarto-float quarto-figure quarto-figure-center anchored">
<figure class="quarto-float quarto-float-fig figure">
<div aria-describedby="fig-setup-caption-0ceaefa1-69ba-4598-a22c-09a6ac19f8ca">
<img src="https://mbutler808.github.io/animalphys-2025/images/lab7-setup.png" class="img-fluid figure-img">
</div>
<figcaption class="quarto-float-caption-bottom quarto-float-caption quarto-float-fig" id="fig-setup-caption-0ceaefa1-69ba-4598-a22c-09a6ac19f8ca">
Figure&nbsp;3: Proper set up of recording and stimulating leads. Note: we will be using alligator clips not hook electrodes
</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<ol start="5" type="1">
<li>Using a Pasteur pipette, fill the lower reservoir of the Nerve Bath with frog Ringer’s solution. Fluid in the lower reservoir must not come in contact with the metal electrode rungs. <em><strong>Note:</strong> Overfilling the Nerve Bath in this manner will cause a short circuit in your experiment.</em></li>
<li>Cut a strip of filter paper and lay it over the wires in the nerve bath so that it touches both stimulating electrodes and both sets of recording electrodes. Moisten the paper strip with frog Ringer’s solution, and place the cover on the nerve bath. This arrangement will be used to test the connections.</li>
<li>Before turning on the PowerLab, make sure it is connected to the computer via a USB cable.</li>
<li>Launch LabChart from your computer using the settings file called <strong>Toad Nerve Lab settings</strong>.<br>
</li>
<li>Go to the Setup menu, select the Stimulator, and then select the waveform Test Connection (Figure&nbsp;4).</li>
</ol>

<div class="no-row-height column-margin column-container"><div class="">
<div id="fig-select-waveform" class="quarto-float quarto-figure quarto-figure-center anchored">
<figure class="quarto-float quarto-float-fig figure">
<div aria-describedby="fig-select-waveform-caption-0ceaefa1-69ba-4598-a22c-09a6ac19f8ca">
<img src="https://mbutler808.github.io/animalphys-2025/images/lab7-select-waveform.png" class="img-fluid figure-img">
</div>
<figcaption class="quarto-float-caption-bottom quarto-float-caption quarto-float-fig" id="fig-select-waveform-caption-0ceaefa1-69ba-4598-a22c-09a6ac19f8ca">
Figure&nbsp;4: Select waveform - test connection.
</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</div></div><ol start="10" type="1">
<li>Open LabChart in Scope View. Click Start. LabChart will now automatically record data for 10ms. A series of stimulus pulses will be recorded (Figure&nbsp;5). You may need to adjust the axes or auto scale to see the signal. <em>If no signal is recorded, check to make sure the microhooks are secure and the filter paper is moist and draped over all the active wires in the Nerve Bath.</em></li>
</ol>
<div id="fig-connection" class="quarto-float quarto-figure quarto-figure-center anchored">
<figure class="quarto-float quarto-float-fig figure">
<div aria-describedby="fig-connection-caption-0ceaefa1-69ba-4598-a22c-09a6ac19f8ca">
<img src="https://mbutler808.github.io/animalphys-2025/images/lab7-test-connection.png" class="img-fluid figure-img">
</div>
<figcaption class="quarto-float-caption-bottom quarto-float-caption quarto-float-fig" id="fig-connection-caption-0ceaefa1-69ba-4598-a22c-09a6ac19f8ca">
Figure&nbsp;5: Stimulus Artifacts that indicate the equipment is set up properly. Note what the spike of the stimulus voltage looks like, so that you can tell them apart from the CAPs when you run your experiments below.
</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<ol start="11" type="1">
<li>Once the connections are tested and working, remove the filter paper and proceed to next step.</li>
</ol>
</section>
<section id="nerve-dissection-procedure" class="level2 page-columns page-full">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="nerve-dissection-procedure">Nerve dissection procedure</h2>
<ol type="1">
<li>Remove the skin from the legs and abdomen of a double-pithed toad obtained from your TA. Cut the skin around the abdomen, and deglove the skin from the lower half of the body (Figure&nbsp;6).</li>
</ol>

<div class="no-row-height column-margin column-container"><div class="">
<div id="fig-deglove" class="quarto-float quarto-figure quarto-figure-center anchored">
<figure class="quarto-float quarto-float-fig figure">
<div aria-describedby="fig-deglove-caption-0ceaefa1-69ba-4598-a22c-09a6ac19f8ca">
<img src="https://mbutler808.github.io/animalphys-2025/images/lab7-frog-remove-skin.png" class="img-fluid figure-img">
</div>
<figcaption class="quarto-float-caption-bottom quarto-float-caption quarto-float-fig" id="fig-deglove-caption-0ceaefa1-69ba-4598-a22c-09a6ac19f8ca">
Figure&nbsp;6: Degloving a frog.
</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</div></div><ol start="2" type="1">
<li>Keep the exposed tissue moist at all times with frog Ringer’s solution.</li>
<li>Grasp the urostyle (a bony element of the pelvis) with forceps and cut it free; you should be able to observe the nerve plexus below it (Figure&nbsp;7), being careful not to damage the nerve plexus.</li>
</ol>

<div class="no-row-height column-margin column-container"><div class="">
<div id="fig-sciatic-nerve" class="quarto-float quarto-figure quarto-figure-center anchored">
<figure class="quarto-float quarto-float-fig figure">
<div aria-describedby="fig-sciatic-nerve-caption-0ceaefa1-69ba-4598-a22c-09a6ac19f8ca">
<img src="https://mbutler808.github.io/animalphys-2025/images/lab7-sciatic-nerve.png" class="img-fluid figure-img">
</div>
<figcaption class="quarto-float-caption-bottom quarto-float-caption quarto-float-fig" id="fig-sciatic-nerve-caption-0ceaefa1-69ba-4598-a22c-09a6ac19f8ca">
Figure&nbsp;7: Exposing the sciatic nerve.
</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</div></div><ol start="4" type="1">
<li>From the dorsal side, using a glass hook and/or glass probe, locate and lift the sciatic nerve free from the associated fascia and the sciatic artery. Use blunt dissection techniques, <span style="color: red"><strong>and do not pull or damage the nerve. Also do not touch the nerve with metal.</strong></span></li>
<li>You will want to dissect a long piece of sciatic nerve that can span many electrodes in the nerve chamber.<br>
</li>
<li>Tie a piece of thread around the nerve as high up on the nerve as you can reach (near the spinal cord). The string will be used as a “leash”, so that you can handle the nerve gently (touching it as little as possible).</li>
<li>Using scissors, cut the nerve from the spinal cord and reflect the nerve back onto the leg. (Only use metal to cut the ends of the nerve).</li>
</ol>

<div class="no-row-height column-margin column-container"><div class="">
<div id="fig-sciatic-nerve-isolation" class="quarto-float quarto-figure quarto-figure-center anchored">
<figure class="quarto-float quarto-float-fig figure">
<div aria-describedby="fig-sciatic-nerve-isolation-caption-0ceaefa1-69ba-4598-a22c-09a6ac19f8ca">
<img src="https://mbutler808.github.io/animalphys-2025/images/lab7-sciatic-nerve-isolation.png" class="img-fluid figure-img">
</div>
<figcaption class="quarto-float-caption-bottom quarto-float-caption quarto-float-fig" id="fig-sciatic-nerve-isolation-caption-0ceaefa1-69ba-4598-a22c-09a6ac19f8ca">
Figure&nbsp;8: Removing the nerve.
</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</div></div><ol start="8" type="1">
<li>Using forceps (on muscle) and the glass hook (to touch the nerve), expose the nerve down to the gastrocnemius muscle. Cut the nerve free (Figure&nbsp;8).</li>
<li>Immediately place the isolated nerve into a petri plate with ringers solution. Let the nerve rest in ringers for a few seconds, and gently clear away any debris from the nerve using the glass tools. <span style="color:red"><strong>Note: DO NOT GRASP THE NERVE WITH METAL FORCEPS!</strong></span>)<br>
</li>
<li>Lay the nerve across the electrodes of the Nerve Chamber (Figure&nbsp;3) using the string leash and the glass hook. Place the thicker end of the nerve toward the stimulating electrodes, and make sure that the position where the nerve is tied (the damaged part) is before both stimulating electrodes.</li>
<li>If necessary gently blot the nerve on a piece of tissue or filter paper to remove any excess Ringer’s solution.</li>
<li>Make sure the nerve is in contact with each of the active connections, but that no portion of the nerve is touching the fluid or the bottom of the chamber.<br>
</li>
<li>If the nerve is too short to span the second pair of recording electrodes, adjust the position of the recording electrodes as necessary. Place the cover back on the Nerve Bath.</li>
</ol>
</section>
</section>
<section id="exercise-1-finding-the-threshold-voltage-and-maximum-cap-amplitude" class="level1">
<h1>Exercise 1: Finding the threshold voltage and maximum CAP amplitude</h1>
<p>A series of stimuli will be given to the nerve, each increasing in amplitude. From these recordings the threshold voltage for the nerve will be calculated, as well as the voltage required for maximum CAP amplitude.</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>In the Setup menu, open the Stimulator… dialog, and select Waveform: Threshold.</li>
<li>From the Setup menu, open the Stimulator Panel.</li>
<li>In the Stimulator Panel, (Figure&nbsp;9) set the Pulse Height amplitude to 20mV; do not adjust any other parameters.</li>
</ol>
<div id="fig-threshold" class="quarto-float quarto-figure quarto-figure-center anchored">
<figure class="quarto-float quarto-float-fig figure">
<div aria-describedby="fig-threshold-caption-0ceaefa1-69ba-4598-a22c-09a6ac19f8ca">
<img src="https://mbutler808.github.io/animalphys-2025/images/lab7-threshold.png" class="img-fluid figure-img">
</div>
<figcaption class="quarto-float-caption-bottom quarto-float-caption quarto-float-fig" id="fig-threshold-caption-0ceaefa1-69ba-4598-a22c-09a6ac19f8ca">
Figure&nbsp;9: Stimulator Panel
</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<ol start="4" type="1">
<li>Click Start. LabChart will stimulate the nerve and record 20 blocks of data.</li>
<li>Increase the pulse height by 20mV, and record again.</li>
<li>Repeat this until a response is seen or you reach 400mV. If you do not see a response, consult your instructor.</li>
<li>Enter the stimulus amplitude (pulse height) that elicits the minimum observable response in to the Stimulator Panel dialog. This is the threshold voltage.</li>
<li>Find the voltage required for maximum CAP amplitude. Increase the stimulus by 10mV steps until the CAP does not increase on three consecutive stimulus amplitude increases or you reach 400mV.</li>
<li>Save the data file.</li>
</ol>
<section id="analysis-determination-of-threshold-voltage-and-maximum-cap-amplitude" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="analysis-determination-of-threshold-voltage-and-maximum-cap-amplitude">Analysis: Determination of threshold voltage and maximum CAP amplitude</h2>
<ol type="1">
<li>Check the Overlay box in the Scope view but leave the slider set at zero.</li>
<li>Select the 20 pages that represent the threshold voltage test, then click on the button to lock the selected pages in overlay.</li>
<li>Place the Marker on the baseline just before the stimulus.</li>
<li>Adjust the horizontal compression as necessary.</li>
<li>Looking at the data in Channel 1, use the up and down arrows to scroll through the pages.</li>
</ol>
<div id="fig-cap-scope" class="quarto-float quarto-figure quarto-figure-center anchored">
<figure class="quarto-float quarto-float-fig figure">
<div aria-describedby="fig-cap-scope-caption-0ceaefa1-69ba-4598-a22c-09a6ac19f8ca">
<img src="https://mbutler808.github.io/animalphys-2025/images/lab7-cap-scope-crop1.png" class="img-fluid figure-img">
</div>
<figcaption class="quarto-float-caption-bottom quarto-float-caption quarto-float-fig" id="fig-cap-scope-caption-0ceaefa1-69ba-4598-a22c-09a6ac19f8ca">
Figure&nbsp;10: Using the Scope view to show increasing CAP amplitude.
</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<ol start="6" type="1">
<li>Use the <span style="color:green"><strong>Waveform Cursor</strong></span> to measure CAP amplitude at each stimulus voltage. Fill in Table&nbsp;1. Each block of data is represented as a page and has a different stimulus voltage shown in channel 3. Note the stimulus level where the first CAP is seen, and where maximum CAP is reached.</li>
</ol>
<div id="fig-cap-amplitude" class="quarto-float quarto-figure quarto-figure-center anchored">
<figure class="quarto-float quarto-float-fig figure">
<div aria-describedby="fig-cap-amplitude-caption-0ceaefa1-69ba-4598-a22c-09a6ac19f8ca">
<img src="https://mbutler808.github.io/animalphys-2025/images/lab7-cap-amplitude.png" class="img-fluid figure-img">
</div>
<figcaption class="quarto-float-caption-bottom quarto-float-caption quarto-float-fig" id="fig-cap-amplitude-caption-0ceaefa1-69ba-4598-a22c-09a6ac19f8ca">
Figure&nbsp;11: UWaveform cursor on the maximum CAP amplitude.
</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div id="tbl-cap-amp" class="quarto-float quarto-figure quarto-figure-center anchored">
<figure class="quarto-float quarto-float-tbl figure">
<figcaption class="quarto-float-caption-top quarto-float-caption quarto-float-tbl" id="tbl-cap-amp-caption-0ceaefa1-69ba-4598-a22c-09a6ac19f8ca">
Table&nbsp;1: CAP amplitude versus stimulus intensity.
</figcaption>
<div aria-describedby="tbl-cap-amp-caption-0ceaefa1-69ba-4598-a22c-09a6ac19f8ca">
<table class="caption-top table">
<colgroup>
<col style="width: 25%">
<col style="width: 25%">
<col style="width: 25%">
<col style="width: 25%">
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr class="header">
<th>Stimulus amplitude (mV)</th>
<th>CAP amplitude (mV)</th>
<th>Stimulus amplitude (mV)</th>
<th>CAP amplitude (mV)</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr class="odd">
<td>20</td>
<td></td>
<td>220</td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>40</td>
<td></td>
<td>240</td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>60</td>
<td></td>
<td>260</td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>80</td>
<td></td>
<td>280</td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>100</td>
<td></td>
<td>300</td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>120</td>
<td></td>
<td>320</td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>140</td>
<td></td>
<td>340</td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>160</td>
<td></td>
<td>360</td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>180</td>
<td></td>
<td>380</td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>200</td>
<td></td>
<td>400</td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>Threshold stimulus voltage:</td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
<td>mV</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>Min Voltage for Max. CAP Amplitude:</td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
<td>mV</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</div>
</figure>
</div>
</section>
</section>
<section id="exercise-2-determination-of-the-refractory-period" class="level1">
<h1>Exercise 2: Determination of the refractory period</h1>
<p>Using the minimum voltage for maximum CAP amplitude, stimulate the nerve with a series of pulses varying in pulse interval. In each block of data, the pulse interval will decrease (i.e., the pulses will get closer together). Use this data to find the the <strong>relative</strong> and <strong>absolute</strong> <em>refractory periods</em> of your nerve. 1. From the results in Table 1, determine <strong>the minimum stimulus voltage</strong> required to elicit a <strong>maximal CAP</strong> from the nerve.<br>
2. From the Stimulator dialog, select waveform&gt; <strong>Refractory Period</strong>, and close the Stimulator dialog. 3. Open the Stimulator Panel if you have closed it and enter the voltage above in the pulse height for both pulses.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://mbutler808.github.io/animalphys-2025/images/lab7-refractory-panel.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>Stimulator panel for determining the refractory period.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<ol start="4" type="1">
<li>Record a series of 15 data blocks (displayed as pages). During each page, two pulses are presented to the nerve. You will decrease the time interval between the pulses decreases with each successive page.</li>
<li>Click <strong>Start</strong>, LabChart will stimulate the nerve 2 times 4 milliseconds apart.</li>
<li>Add a comment stating the interval between pulses (4 ms) for the record.</li>
<li>Change the interval between pulses to 3.5 ms, click <strong>Start</strong>. Add a comment stating the interval period (3.5 ms) for the record.</li>
<li>Repeat for each specified interval Table 2 in the Data Notebook, adding a comment stating the interval period for each record.</li>
<li><strong>Save your data</strong>, do not close the file.</li>
</ol>
<section id="analysis" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="analysis">Analysis</h3>
<section id="determination-of-refractory-period" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="determination-of-refractory-period">Determination of refractory period</h4>
<p><span style="color:green"><strong>Select</strong></span> the 15 data pages recorded in Exercise 2, and lock them into Overlay mode. Place the <span style="color:green"><strong>Marker</strong></span> on the baseline and use the <span style="color:green"><strong>Waveform Cursor</strong></span> to measure the amplitude for the second CAP. Record these values in Table&nbsp;2. Determine the stimulus interval where the amplitude of the second CAP first shows a decrease. This is the <span style="color:blue"><strong>relative refractory period</strong></span>. Determine the stimulus interval where the second CAP completely disappears. This is the <span style="color:blue"><strong>absolute refractory period</strong></span>. Record both of these values in Table&nbsp;2.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://mbutler808.github.io/animalphys-2025/images/lab7-refractory-period.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>Scope View showing paired pulses for determining the refractory period.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div id="tbl-refractory" class="quarto-float quarto-figure quarto-figure-center anchored">
<figure class="quarto-float quarto-float-tbl figure">
<figcaption class="quarto-float-caption-top quarto-float-caption quarto-float-tbl" id="tbl-refractory-caption-0ceaefa1-69ba-4598-a22c-09a6ac19f8ca">
Table&nbsp;2: CAP amplitude versus stimulus intensity.
</figcaption>
<div aria-describedby="tbl-refractory-caption-0ceaefa1-69ba-4598-a22c-09a6ac19f8ca">
<table class="caption-top table">
<colgroup>
<col style="width: 25%">
<col style="width: 25%">
<col style="width: 25%">
<col style="width: 25%">
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr class="header">
<th>Stimulus interval (ms)</th>
<th>Amplitude of second CAP</th>
<th>Stimulus interval (ms)</th>
<th>Amplitude of second CAP</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr class="odd">
<td>4.0</td>
<td></td>
<td>1.6</td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>3.5</td>
<td></td>
<td>1.5</td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>3.0</td>
<td></td>
<td>1.4</td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>2.5</td>
<td></td>
<td>1.3</td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>2.0</td>
<td></td>
<td>1.2</td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>1.9</td>
<td></td>
<td>1.1</td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>1.8</td>
<td></td>
<td>1.0</td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>1.7</td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>Relative refractory period (ms)</td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>Absolute refractory period (ms)</td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</div>
</figure>
</div>
</section>
</section>
</section>
<section id="exercise-3-nerve-conduction-velocity-and-temperature-sensitivity" class="level1">
<h1>Exercise 3: Nerve conduction velocity and temperature sensitivity</h1>
<section id="analysis-1" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="analysis-1">Analysis</h3>
<section id="calculating-conduction-velocity" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="calculating-conduction-velocity">Calculating conduction velocity</h4>
<ol type="1">
<li><p>Room temperature. Using the data in Exercise 1, make a <span style="color:green"><strong>selection</strong></span> in channels 1 and 2 that includes the CAP. Open the <span style="color:green"><strong>Zoom window</strong></span>, and use the <span style="color:green"><strong>Marker</strong></span> and <span style="color:green"><strong>Waveform Cursor</strong></span> to determine the time interval for the CAP to travel between the two recording electrodes (Figure&nbsp;12). Place the marker on the first CAP peak.</p></li>
<li><p>Place the waveform cursor over the second CAP peak. Record the value for time differential (<img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%5CDelta">t) in milliseconds in Table 3.</p></li>
<li><p>Using a ruler, measure the distance in millimeters between the black negative leads of each of the two recording electrodes. Record in Table&nbsp;3.</p></li>
<li><p>Calculate the <strong>conduction velocity</strong> from the <strong>distance between the electrodes</strong> and <strong>time interval between CAPs</strong>:</p></li>
</ol>
<p>Conduction velocity (m/sec) = <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%5Cfrac%7BDistance(mm)%7D%7BTime(ms)%7D"></p>
<div id="fig-velocity" class="quarto-float quarto-figure quarto-figure-center anchored">
<figure class="quarto-float quarto-float-fig figure">
<div aria-describedby="fig-velocity-caption-0ceaefa1-69ba-4598-a22c-09a6ac19f8ca">
<img src="https://mbutler808.github.io/animalphys-2025/images/lab7-conduction2.png" class="img-fluid figure-img">
</div>
<figcaption class="quarto-float-caption-bottom quarto-float-caption quarto-float-fig" id="fig-velocity-caption-0ceaefa1-69ba-4598-a22c-09a6ac19f8ca">
Figure&nbsp;12: Zoom window in overlay mode showing analysis procedure for calculating conduction velocity. Waveform Cursor information is displayed at the top of the window.
</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div id="tbl-velocity" class="quarto-float quarto-figure quarto-figure-center anchored">
<figure class="quarto-float quarto-float-tbl figure">
<figcaption class="quarto-float-caption-top quarto-float-caption quarto-float-tbl" id="tbl-velocity-caption-0ceaefa1-69ba-4598-a22c-09a6ac19f8ca">
Table&nbsp;3: Calculation of conduction velocity.
</figcaption>
<div aria-describedby="tbl-velocity-caption-0ceaefa1-69ba-4598-a22c-09a6ac19f8ca">
<table class="caption-top table">
<thead>
<tr class="header">
<th>Parameter</th>
<th>cold</th>
<th>room temperature</th>
<th>warm</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr class="odd">
<td>Temperature (C)</td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>Distance between recording electrodes (mm)</td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>Time interval between CAP1 and CAP2 (ms)</td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>Conduction velcoity (m/s)</td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</div>
</figure>
</div>
<ol start="5" type="1">
<li>Chill the nerve by placing it in a Petri dish with cold Ringer’s (~4°C). Replace the Ringerʻs in the nerve chamber with cold Ringerʻs.</li>
<li>Place the nerve in the chamber and quickly run the Conduction Velocity macro.<br>
</li>
<li>Repeat with warm Ringer’s (~35°C) and complete Table&nbsp;3.</li>
</ol>
</section>
</section>
</section>
<section id="exercise-4-bi-directionality-of-nerve-conduction" class="level1">
<h1>Exercise 4: Bi-Directionality of Nerve Conduction</h1>
<p>The ability of a nerve to conduct signals in both directions can be observed by changing the recording and stimulating leads.</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>The thicker end of the nerve originates closer to the spinal cord, and the thinner end is more distal.</li>
<li>Change the position of the leads to stimulate starting from the thinner end (Figure&nbsp;13).</li>
</ol>
<div id="fig-nerve-reverse" class="quarto-float quarto-figure quarto-figure-center anchored">
<figure class="quarto-float quarto-float-fig figure">
<div aria-describedby="fig-nerve-reverse-caption-0ceaefa1-69ba-4598-a22c-09a6ac19f8ca">
<img src="https://mbutler808.github.io/animalphys-2025/images/lab7-nerve-reverse.png" class="img-fluid figure-img">
</div>
<figcaption class="quarto-float-caption-bottom quarto-float-caption quarto-float-fig" id="fig-nerve-reverse-caption-0ceaefa1-69ba-4598-a22c-09a6ac19f8ca">
Figure&nbsp;13: Reverse the stimulating and channel 2 recording leads to show bi-directionality.
</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<ol start="3" type="1">
<li>Run the Threshold macro as in Exercise 1. Stimulator dialog, select Waveform: Threshold. Pulse Height amplitude 20 mV.</li>
<li>Right click in the first data block of this exercise and enter the <strong>comment</strong> “Bi-Directionality” and save your data file.</li>
</ol>
<section id="analysis-2" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="analysis-2">Analysis</h3>
<p>Compare the threshold voltage necessary to elicit a maximum response from the nerve when stimulating from the thick end of the nerve (Exercise 1) vs.&nbsp;stimulating from the distal (thinner) end of the nerve (Table&nbsp;4).</p>
<div id="tbl-cap-amp-rev" class="quarto-float quarto-figure quarto-figure-center anchored">
<figure class="quarto-float quarto-float-tbl figure">
<figcaption class="quarto-float-caption-top quarto-float-caption quarto-float-tbl" id="tbl-cap-amp-rev-caption-0ceaefa1-69ba-4598-a22c-09a6ac19f8ca">
Table&nbsp;4: CAP amplitude versus stimulus intensity stimulating from the distal end of the nerve.
</figcaption>
<div aria-describedby="tbl-cap-amp-rev-caption-0ceaefa1-69ba-4598-a22c-09a6ac19f8ca">
<table class="caption-top table">
<colgroup>
<col style="width: 25%">
<col style="width: 25%">
<col style="width: 25%">
<col style="width: 25%">
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr class="header">
<th>Stimulus amplitude (mV)</th>
<th>CAP amplitude (mV)</th>
<th>Stimulus amplitude (mV)</th>
<th>CAP amplitude (mV)</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr class="odd">
<td>20</td>
<td></td>
<td>220</td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>40</td>
<td></td>
<td>240</td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>60</td>
<td></td>
<td>260</td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>80</td>
<td></td>
<td>280</td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>100</td>
<td></td>
<td>300</td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>120</td>
<td></td>
<td>320</td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>140</td>
<td></td>
<td>340</td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>160</td>
<td></td>
<td>360</td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>180</td>
<td></td>
<td>380</td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>200</td>
<td></td>
<td>400</td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>Threshold stimulus voltage:</td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
<td>mV</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>Min Voltage for Max. CAP Amplitude:</td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
<td>mV</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</div>
</figure>
</div>
</section>
</section>
<section id="exercise-5-stimulus-strength-duration-relationships" class="level1">
<h1>Exercise 5: Stimulus Strength-Duration Relationships</h1>
<p>The ability of a stimulus to elicit a response is dependent on the <strong>stimulus duration</strong> as well as its <strong>strength</strong> (intensity). The relationship between strength and duration can be derived empirically for your sciatic nerve preparation. Strength-duration curves are often used by physiologists as a relative measure of a nerve’s <strong>excitability</strong>.</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>Change the stimulator leads back so that you are stimulating the proximal (thick) end of the sciatic nerve.</li>
<li>Open the Stimulator dialog and select Waveform: Threshold.</li>
<li>In the Stimulator Panel, set the Pulse Height amplitude to 20 mV, and select a pulse duration of 50 <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%5Cmu">s. Click <strong>Start</strong>.</li>
<li>Right click in the first data block of this exercise and enter the <strong>comment</strong> “strength-duration”.</li>
<li>Increase the stimulus by 20 mV and repeat until a CAP is observed.</li>
<li>Now return the stimulus pulse height to 20 mV, and repeat with durations of 100 <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%5Cmu">s, 250 <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%5Cmu">s, 500 <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%5Cmu">s, 750 <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%5Cmu">s, 1000 <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%5Cmu">s (you used 150 <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%5Cmu">s for the first exercise).</li>
<li>Save your data file.</li>
</ol>
<section id="analysis-3" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="analysis-3">Analysis</h3>
<ol type="1">
<li>Use the overlay to determine when reaching threshold by comparing your trace to previous subthreshold traces. The voltage where the CAP is barely detectable in Channel 1 is the suprathreshold stimulus voltage.</li>
<li>Record the effective stimulus amplitude at which you first reach threshold for each duration (Table&nbsp;5).</li>
</ol>
<div id="tbl-strength" class="quarto-float quarto-figure quarto-figure-center anchored">
<figure class="quarto-float quarto-float-tbl figure">
<figcaption class="quarto-float-caption-top quarto-float-caption quarto-float-tbl" id="tbl-strength-caption-0ceaefa1-69ba-4598-a22c-09a6ac19f8ca">
Table&nbsp;5: CAP threshold vs.&nbsp;stimulus duration.
</figcaption>
<div aria-describedby="tbl-strength-caption-0ceaefa1-69ba-4598-a22c-09a6ac19f8ca">
<table class="caption-top table">
<thead>
<tr class="header">
<th>Duration (<img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%5Cmu">s)</th>
<th>Threshold Voltage (mV)</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr class="odd">
<td>50</td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>100</td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>150</td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>250</td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>500</td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>750</td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>1000</td>
<td></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</div>
</figure>
</div>
<ol start="3" type="1">
<li>Graph these data with Threshold Voltage (mV) on the ordinate and duration (msec) on the abscissa.</li>
<li>Find rheobase on your plot. <strong>Rheobase</strong> is the <em>minimum stimulus intensity</em> that will elicit a <em>response at infinite duration</em> (where stimulus intensity reaches an asymptote with respect to duration). If you have printed a copy you may wish to mark this with an arrow.</li>
<li>Find chronaxie on your plot. Chronaxie is the stimulus duration required at a stimulus strength of 2x rheobase. If you have printed a copy you may wish to mark this with an arrow.</li>
</ol>
</section>
</section>
<section id="suggestions-for-the-results-section" class="level1">
<h1>Suggestions for the Results Section</h1>
<p>Conduct the appropriate analyses on your data and present your findings in paragraph form with the aid of graphs and/or tables as needed. Typically, for this type of experiment one would report:</p>
<ul>
<li>Determination of threshold voltage</li>
<li>The maximum CAP amplitude</li>
<li>Determination of the refractory period</li>
<li>Calculation of conduction velocity</li>
<li>Sensitivity of conduction velocity on Temperature (with Q10)</li>
<li>Threshold voltage for forward vs reverse stimulation (bidirectionality)<br>
</li>
<li>Stimulus strength vs.&nbsp;duration relationship</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="questions-for-thought" class="level1">
<h1>Questions for Thought:</h1>
<ol type="1">
<li>How does a CAP differ from a single action potential? Would you see any differences in your data between the two?</li>
<li>What is the cause of the relative refractory period? Briefly describe the cellular events that occur during the refractory period (Hint: Discuss the mechanism of repolarization). Explain the difference between the relative and absolute refractory periods. What evidence do you see of these phenomena in your data?</li>
<li>Action potentials are said to be “all or none” responses. Why does the toad sciatic nerve give what looks like a graded response?</li>
<li>What was the smallest voltage required to produce the maximum CAP? What proportion of the nerve fibers was excited to produce this response?</li>
<li>Based on your calculation for CAP conduction velocity, how long would it take the CAP to travel the length of the sciatic nerve? Assume a total length of 10 cm. How could this be important for the animal?</li>
<li>How does the temperature sensitivity of nerve conduction velocity compare to other physiological processes in the toad? If there is a difference, what are possible mechanisms that might cause the differences? Hint: You have already determined Q10 for cardiac (muscle) function in the toad.</li>
<li>Why were you still able to elicit a CAP after reversing the direction of stimulation? How did the appearance of the frog CAP change in comparison to when it was in its original orientation? How do you explain this?</li>
<li>What is happening in the nerve at the voltage-duration combinations that you are identifying as threshold? (Strength-duration experiment)</li>
<li>Based on what you learned, what are the major factors involved in signal propagation through peripheral nerves in the toad? In vertebrates generally?</li>
</ol>
</section>
<section id="after-lab" class="level1">
<h1>After Lab:</h1>
<ul>
<li>This will be a group lab report.</li>
<li>Please divide the work of writing the report <strong>by experiment</strong>, so that each person benefits from the experience of writing the intro, methods, results, and discussion. This will also ensure that the ideas are better connected between sections.</li>
<li>Please think about effective figures for this interesting lab, and the results will jump out at you. It will also be easier to write the discussion.</li>
<li>Please remember to include respective contributions.</li>
</ul>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>week 8</category>
  <category>labs</category>
  <category>nerve</category>
  <category>neuron</category>
  <category>signal propagation</category>
  <category>refractory period</category>
  <category>conduction velocity</category>
  <category>compound action potential</category>
  <category>action potential Q10</category>
  <guid>https://mbutler808.github.io/animalphys-2025/labs/Lab7-toad-nerve/Lab7.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 22 Oct 2024 10:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Lab 6: The Neurogenic Crustacean Heart</title>
  <dc:creator>Marguerite Butler</dc:creator>
  <link>https://mbutler808.github.io/animalphys-2025/labs/Lab6-lobster-heart/Lab6.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<section id="before-lab" class="level1">
<h1>Before Lab</h1>
<p>This will be our first invertebrate lab. We will be studying the control of the neurogenic heart of crustaceans using the lobster as a model.</p>
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-note callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
Prepare for lab by:
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<ul>
<li>Read the lab manual for this weekʻs experiment [<a href="Lab6-lobster-heart.pdf">Lab 6</a>] exploring the physiology of the toad heart using ECG and a force transducer.<br>
</li>
<li>Write the [<a href="../../labs-misc/lab-notebook.html#sec-prelab">Prelab</a>] in your lab notebook.
<ul>
<li>For the <strong>Intro</strong>, focus on identifying the physiological mechanisms (outline them), and end with a paragraph of hypotheses/expectations (like the worksheet).</li>
<li>Think about <strong>strong hypotheses</strong>! <em>Strong hypotheses lead to excellent reports.</em></li>
<li><strong>Methods</strong>: subjects, experimental methods and analyses (how you will compare to address the hypotheses – <em>you should start thinking about how you will plot the data for the results to make these answers pop</em>).</li>
</ul></li>
<li>Do prelab Quiz on Laulima (open 24 hrs before lab).</li>
<li>Please check out the [<a href="../../powerpoints/Lab6.HeartControlLobster.pdf">powerpoint notes</a>] and the review paper on the [<a href="Cooke02.pdf">crustacean cardiac ganglion</a>] by our very own Dr.&nbsp;Ian Cooke who was an emeritus faculty from the Zoology Department and PBRC, a pioneer in invertebrate neurophysiology!</li>
</ul>
</div>
</div>
<section id="in-lab" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="in-lab">In Lab:</h2>
<ul>
<li><em>Plan to Work quickly!</em> <strong>You will have 30 min (and very lucky if you have an hour)</strong> once you open the carapace.</li>
<li>Keep your animal chilled (they are Maine lobsters!) and irrigated with ice-cold Lobster ringers at all times.</li>
<li>Lab 6 manual [<a href="Lab6-lobster-heart.pdf">pdf</a>] . Record data in your lab notebook.</li>
<li>You should have plenty of time to complete the data collection and your figures during lab.<br>
</li>
<li>This will be a Group Lab. Begin planning with your partners as you work.</li>
<li>Start an outline with your lab partners and start outlining your discussion points, and the rest of the report. Use your time wisely to brainstorm as you work.<br>
</li>
<li>Lobster external anatomy [<a href="lobster-dorsal-view.jpg">jpg</a>]</li>
<li>Lobster internal anatomy [<a href="lobster-internal-anatomy.jpg">jpg</a>]</li>
</ul>
<p><img src="https://mbutler808.github.io/animalphys-2025/labs/Lab6-lobster-heart/lobster-dorsal-view.jpg" style="width:6in;height:4in"><br>
<img src="https://mbutler808.github.io/animalphys-2025/labs/Lab6-lobster-heart/lobster-internal-anatomy.jpg" style="width:6in;height:4in"></p>
</section>
<section id="after-lab" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="after-lab">After Lab:</h2>
<ul>
<li>Group lab report due next week. See the guidance at the end of the [<a href="Lab6-lobster-heart.pdf">Lobster Heart lab manual</a>]. You may also want to look over the guidance at the end of the [<a href="../Lab5-toad-heart/Lab5-toad-heart.pdf">Toad Heart Lab</a>].<br>
</li>
<li>Always follow the content guidelines: [<a href="../../labs-misc/handouts/Zool430lab_report_guidelines.pdf">grading guidelines</a>]</li>
<li>It is a good idea to divide up the work of writing the lab <strong>by experiment</strong>. That way, <em>each person writes a portion of the intro, methods, results, and discussion for their <strong>hypothesis</strong></em>.</li>
<li>Work out your timeline with your lab partners during lab (and plan a face-to-face meet up [hey! you can do your lab EC]) <em>so that everyone has a chance to comment and edit</em> before the lab is submitted.</li>
</ul>


</section>
</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>week 7</category>
  <category>labs</category>
  <category>cardiac cycle</category>
  <category>invertebrate</category>
  <category>heart</category>
  <category>in situ</category>
  <category>lobster</category>
  <category>Starlingʻs law</category>
  <category>sympathetic</category>
  <category>parasympathetic</category>
  <category>ions</category>
  <category>temperature</category>
  <guid>https://mbutler808.github.io/animalphys-2025/labs/Lab6-lobster-heart/Lab6.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 08 Oct 2024 10:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://mbutler808.github.io/animalphys-2025/labs/Lab6-lobster-heart/lobster-internal-anatomy.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Lab 5: Physiology of the in situ Toad Heart</title>
  <dc:creator>Marguerite Butler</dc:creator>
  <link>https://mbutler808.github.io/animalphys-2025/labs/Lab5-toad-heart/Lab5.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<section id="before-lab" class="level1">
<h1>Before Lab</h1>
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-note callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
Prepare for lab by:
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<ul>
<li>This will be our first dissection lab. Itʻs really cool!</li>
<li><strong>Wear shoes to lab</strong>, and bring your dissecting kit (if you have one, otherwise we have supplies). Lab coat is not required but you are welcome to wear one if you wish.</li>
<li>Read the lab manual for this weekʻs experiment [<a href="Lab5-toad-heart.pdf">Lab 5</a>] exploring the physiology of the toad heart using ECG and a force transducer.<br>
</li>
<li>Write the [<a href="../../labs-misc/lab-notebook.html#sec-prelab">Prelab</a>] in your lab notebook.</li>
<li>Do Quiz on Laulima (open 24 hrs before lab).</li>
</ul>
</div>
</div>
<section id="in-lab" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="in-lab">In Lab:</h2>
<ul>
<li>Lab 5 manual [<a href="Lab5-toad-heart.pdf">pdf</a>] [<a href="Lab5-toad-heart.docx">docx</a>]. Record data in your lab notebook. Use the guidance at the end of the lab manual to analyze your data in preparation for your results and discussion.</li>
<li>Dissection guide [<a href="DissectionGuide.pdf">pdf</a>]</li>
<li>Toad heart anatomy. Note that amphibians have a 3-chambered heart! Two atria and one ventricle. [<a href="HeartAnatomy.pdf">pdf</a>]</li>
</ul>
<p><img src="https://mbutler808.github.io/animalphys-2025/images/ToadDissectionGuide.png" style="width:4in;height:5.25in"> <img src="https://mbutler808.github.io/animalphys-2025/images/ToadHeartAnatomy.png" style="width:4in;height:5.25in"></p>
</section>
<section id="after-lab" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="after-lab">After Lab:</h2>
<ul>
<li>Individual Work Sheet due next week [<a href="Lab5IWS-toad-heart.pdf">pdf</a>] [<a href="Lab5IWS-toad-heart.docx">docx</a>]</li>
<li>You will include statements of purpose (section 1), concept check (section) 2), mini results (section 3), and a regular discussion. On this lab WS, put a little more effort into the discussion. For each section we ask for, always follow the content guidelines: [<a href="../../labs-misc/handouts/Zool430lab_report_guidelines.pdf">grading guidelines</a>]</li>
<li>You are encouraged to analyze data with your lab members, and may develop figures together, but all writing must be your own work.</li>
</ul>


</section>
</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>week 5</category>
  <category>labs</category>
  <category>ecg</category>
  <category>cardiac cycle</category>
  <category>heart</category>
  <category>in situ</category>
  <category>toad</category>
  <category>electical impulse</category>
  <category>Starlingʻs law</category>
  <category>sympathetic</category>
  <category>parasympathetic</category>
  <category>ions</category>
  <category>temperature</category>
  <guid>https://mbutler808.github.io/animalphys-2025/labs/Lab5-toad-heart/Lab5.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 01 Oct 2024 10:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://mbutler808.github.io/animalphys-2025/labs/Lab5-toad-heart/HeartAnatomy.pdf" medium="image"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Lab 4: Electrocardiogram (ECG/EKG) and Cardiac Response to Exercise</title>
  <dc:creator>Marguerite Butler</dc:creator>
  <link>https://mbutler808.github.io/animalphys-2025/labs/Lab4-human-ecg/Lab4.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<section id="before-lab" class="level1">
<h1>Before Lab</h1>
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-note callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
Prepare for lab by:
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<ul>
<li><strong>Wear comfortable shoes to lab</strong> (you will be running up and down the stairs).</li>
<li>Watch cardiac cycle podcast.</li>
<li>Read human ecg protocol [<a href="../Protocols/p3-human-ecg.pdf">Protocol 3</a>].</li>
<li>Read the lab manual for this weekʻs experiment [<a href="Lab4-Human-Heart-ECG.pdf">Lab 4</a>] exploring the cardiac cycle and effects of exercise using ECG.<br>
</li>
<li>Write the [<a href="../../labs-misc/lab-notebook.html#sec-prelab">Prelab</a>] in your lab notebook.</li>
<li>Do Quiz 4 on Laulima (open 24 hrs before lab).</li>
</ul>
<div class="quarto-video ratio ratio-16x9"><iframe data-external="1" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/dWZqO2XHo2Y" title="" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen=""></iframe></div>
</div>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://mbutler808.github.io/animalphys-2025/images/detail_ecg.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" style="width:90.0%"></p>
<figcaption>The ECG is the summation of cardiac potentials throughout the heart</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<section id="in-lab" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="in-lab">In Lab:</h2>
<ul>
<li>Practical based on <a href="../../labs/Lab1-heart-rate-and-data-analysis/Lab1.html">Lab 1</a>.</li>
<li>Lab 4 exercises 1-3. Record data in your lab notebook. [<a href="Lab4-data-tables.pdf">example data tables</a>] [<a href="Lab4-data-tables.docx">docx</a>]</li>
<li>Note: the data tables are to assist you in collecting data and should be included in your notebook. Present the results in your lab report</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="after-lab" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="after-lab">After Lab:</h2>
<ul>
<li>Group lab report due next week</li>
<li>Use the guidance to structure your full lab report. [<a href="Lab4-ECG-Report.pdf">pdf</a>] [<a href="Lab4-ECG-Report.docx">docx</a>]</li>
<li>This will be a full lab report with intro, methods, results, discussion, literature cited, and respective contributions. [<a href="../../labs-misc/handouts/Zool430lab_report_guidelines.pdf">grading guidelines</a>]</li>
</ul>
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-important callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
Important
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<ul>
<li>Be sure to solicit feedback from lab partners, <em>but do not delete or rewrite the words of others</em>. Leave comments and allow author to revise (or not).</li>
</ul>
</div>
</div>


</section>
</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>week 4</category>
  <category>labs</category>
  <category>ecg</category>
  <category>cardiac cycle</category>
  <category>heart</category>
  <category>exercise</category>
  <category>electrical response</category>
  <category>heart sounds</category>
  <category>pulse</category>
  <guid>https://mbutler808.github.io/animalphys-2025/labs/Lab4-human-ecg/Lab4.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 17 Sep 2024 10:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://mbutler808.github.io/animalphys-2025/images/detail_ecg.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Lab 3: Peripheral Circulation and The Dive Response</title>
  <dc:creator>Marguerite Butler</dc:creator>
  <link>https://mbutler808.github.io/animalphys-2025/labs/Lab3-human-peripheral-circulation-dive-response/Lab3.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<section id="before-lab" class="level1">
<h1>Before Lab</h1>
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-note callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
Prepare for lab by:
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<ul>
<li>Watch Peripheral Circulation Podcast.</li>
<li>Read [<a href="../Protocols/p2-measuring-blood-pressure.pdf">Protocol 2</a>] on measuring blood pressure.</li>
<li>Read the lab manual below.<br>
</li>
<li>Write the [<a href="../../labs-misc/lab-notebook.html#sec-prelab">Prelab</a>] in your lab notebook. For the introduction, focus on the hypotheses you are asked to develop on peripheral circulation and the dive response. Select only the relevant background you need for those hypotheses.</li>
<li>Do Quiz on Laulima (open 24 hrs before lab).</li>
</ul>
<div class="quarto-video ratio ratio-16x9"><iframe data-external="1" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/h47oQH-w6F8" title="" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen=""></iframe></div>
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-note callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
Exercises
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<ul>
<li>Measuring blood pressure</li>
<li>Peripheral circulation experiment
<ul>
<li>Develop a simple experiment to demonstrate a principle of peripheral circulation of choice.</li>
</ul></li>
<li>Dive response experiment
<ul>
<li>Develop a hypothesis for a potential trigger for the dive response.</li>
</ul></li>
</ul>
</div>
</div>
</section>
<section id="general-background-blood-pressure-and-peripheral-circulation" class="level1 page-columns page-full">
<h1>General Background: Blood pressure and peripheral circulation</h1>
<p>Vertebrates have a <strong>closed circulatory system</strong> where the blood is always enclosed within blood vessels or the heart. Blood is pumped from the <strong>heart</strong> (the central pump) to the <strong>vasculature</strong>: the <strong>arteries</strong>, <strong>capillary beds</strong> (sites of delivery to tissues), <strong>the veins</strong>, and back to heart. There are several important consequences of this design: (1) blood pressure varies across species according to oxygen demand and morphology (especially animal height), (2) <strong>blood pressure varies along the circuit</strong>, (3) <strong>blood pressure can be regulated at points along the circuit</strong>, and (4) <strong>blood pressure can be modified situationally</strong> depending the state of the animal.</p>
<section id="blood-pressure-varies-across-species" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="blood-pressure-varies-across-species">Blood pressure varies across species</h3>
<p>For <strong>very active</strong> animals (e.g., mammals and birds) or <strong>very large animals</strong> (especially very tall animals that have more gravity to resist), the ability to regulate blood pressure is critical — active animals will <em>need more oxygen delivered at a faster rate</em>, especially to the most metabolically active tissues, and <em>larger animals will require much more pressure</em> to reach all of their tissues.</p>
</section>
<section id="blood-pressure-varies-during-the-cardiac-cycle." class="level3 page-columns page-full">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="blood-pressure-varies-during-the-cardiac-cycle.">Blood pressure varies during the cardiac cycle.</h3>
<p>The <strong>cardiac cycle</strong> is a complete cycle of the heart beat, comprised of <strong>systole</strong> (Figure&nbsp;1; the phase involving contraction and ejection) and <strong>diastole</strong> (Figure&nbsp;2; relaxation and filling) of the atria and ventricles. We will learn more about the cardiac cycle in the EKG lab. In this lab we are focusing on the blood pressure changes. The largest muscles of the heart are in the <strong>ventricles</strong>. Blood pressure is at its highest immediately after the ventricles contract to push blood into the arterial system (Figure&nbsp;3; <strong>systolic pressure</strong>) and declines as the ventricles relax to fill with blood before pumping again. Just before the ventricles contract, blood pressure is at its lowest (<strong>diastolic pressure</strong>).</p>
<div class="cell page-columns page-full" data-url="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Heart_systole.svg">

<div class="no-row-height column-margin column-container"><div class="cell-output-display">
<div id="fig-systole" class="quarto-float quarto-figure quarto-figure-center anchored">
<figure class="quarto-float quarto-float-fig figure">
<div aria-describedby="fig-systole-caption-0ceaefa1-69ba-4598-a22c-09a6ac19f8ca">
<img src="https://mbutler808.github.io/animalphys-2025/images/Heart_systole.svg" class="img-fluid figure-img">
</div>
<figcaption class="quarto-float-caption-bottom quarto-float-caption quarto-float-fig" id="fig-systole-caption-0ceaefa1-69ba-4598-a22c-09a6ac19f8ca">
Figure&nbsp;1: The human heart during the ventricular <strong>systole</strong> phase of the <strong>cardiac cycle</strong>. Image by <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/User:Wapcaplet">Wapcaplet</a>, <a href="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/User:Reytan">Reytan</a>, <a href="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/User:Mtcv">Mtcv</a> / <a href="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Heart_systole.svg">Heart systole</a>/<a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/3.0/">CC BY-SA 3.0</a>
</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</div></div></div>
<div class="cell page-columns page-full" data-url="https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/0/0f/Heart_diasystole.svg">

<div class="no-row-height column-margin column-container"><div class="cell-output-display">
<div id="fig-diastole" class="quarto-float quarto-figure quarto-figure-center anchored">
<figure class="quarto-float quarto-float-fig figure">
<div aria-describedby="fig-diastole-caption-0ceaefa1-69ba-4598-a22c-09a6ac19f8ca">
<img src="https://mbutler808.github.io/animalphys-2025/images/Heart_diasystole.svg" class="img-fluid figure-img">
</div>
<figcaption class="quarto-float-caption-bottom quarto-float-caption quarto-float-fig" id="fig-diastole-caption-0ceaefa1-69ba-4598-a22c-09a6ac19f8ca">
Figure&nbsp;2: The heart relaxes and the ventricles fill during the <strong>diastole</strong> phase of the <strong>cardiac cycle</strong>. Image by <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/User:Wapcaplet">Wapcaplet</a>, <a href="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/User:Reytan">Reytan</a>, Vector:<a href="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/User:Sjef">Sjef</a> / <a href="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Heart_diasystole.svg">Heart diastole</a>/ <a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/3.0/">CC BY-SA 3.0</a>
</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</div></div></div>
<div class="cell" data-url="https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/9/91/Wiggers_Diagram_2.svg">
<div class="cell-output-display">
<div id="fig-wiggers" class="quarto-float quarto-figure quarto-figure-center anchored">
<figure class="quarto-float quarto-float-fig figure">
<div aria-describedby="fig-wiggers-caption-0ceaefa1-69ba-4598-a22c-09a6ac19f8ca">
<img src="https://mbutler808.github.io/animalphys-2025/images/Wiggers_Diagram_2.svg" class="img-fluid figure-img">
</div>
<figcaption class="quarto-float-caption-bottom quarto-float-caption quarto-float-fig" id="fig-wiggers-caption-0ceaefa1-69ba-4598-a22c-09a6ac19f8ca">
Figure&nbsp;3: Volume and pressure changes during the <strong>cardiac cycle</strong>, as shown in a Wiggers diagram. Note that aortic and ventricular pressures are both lowest and the end of diastole, just before the beginning of systole. adh30 revised work by DanielChangMD who revised original work of DestinyQx; Redrawn as SVG by xavax, <a href="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Wiggers_Diagram_2.svg">Wiggers Diagram 2</a>, <a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/legalcode">CC BY-SA 4.0</a>
</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</section>
<section id="blood-pressure-varies-along-the-vascular-circuit." class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="blood-pressure-varies-along-the-vascular-circuit.">Blood pressure varies along the vascular circuit.</h3>
<p>Blood in the arteries leaving the heart is always at very high pressure as compared to the low pressure in the veins in the legs or the even lower pressure in capillary beds at the tissues. Blood pressure drops as the blood vessels branch again and again, increasing the cross-sectional area of the circuit, until it reaches the capillaries where the tissues experience relatively constant, low pressure to facilitate <strong>diffusion</strong>.</p>
<p>The slow blood flow at the capillaries facilitates diffusion of oxygen, nutrients, and carbon dioxide and other wastes between the blood and the tissues that are bathed by the capillaries. Therefore, <strong>pressure varies</strong> depending on <strong>distance from the heart</strong>, the <strong>cross-sectional area of the blood vessels</strong>, as well as <strong>gravity</strong>. However, at any given point along the circuit, blood pressure remains fairly constant.</p>
</section>
<section id="circulation-can-be-adjusted-situationally." class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="circulation-can-be-adjusted-situationally.">Circulation can be adjusted situationally.</h3>
<p>At most times, blood pressure is regulated to <strong>maintain a relatively constant pressure</strong>, however, there are times when <strong>circulation needs to be adjusted</strong>.</p>
<p>A well-known example is the <strong>Fight-or-Flight response</strong>, which occurs, for example, when an animal sees a predator or anticipates a fight. The <strong>sympathetic nervous system</strong> dominates and causes a ramp-up of circulation to deliver more energy to the skeletal muscles: increased <strong>cardiac output</strong> (= <strong>heart rate</strong> x <strong>stroke volume</strong>) and <strong>blood pressure</strong>, and increased blood flow to the lungs and skeletal muscles. In contrast, the <strong>rest-and-digest</strong> response occurs after an animal has had a large meal. The <strong>parasympathetic nervous system</strong> dominates, lowering heart rate, concentrates blood flow to the gut, and promotes a resting state.</p>
<p>A famous circulatory adjustment to the distribution of blood flow is the <strong>dive response</strong> of air breathing vertebrates <span class="citation" data-cites="Withers:1992">(pp.&nbsp;721-723, Withers 1992)</span>. We will explore this response in this lab. The dive response is characterized by a <strong>diving bradycardia</strong> (slowing of the heart rate) and <strong>peripheral vasoconstriction</strong> which drives the blood away from the extremities and toward the central organs (brain, heart). The diving bradycardia is a reflexive response that can cause a dramatic drop in heart rate but does not necessarily cause a drop in blood pressure because there is a simultaneous peripheral vasoconstriction. With more blood returned to the heart, you may see an increase in stroke volume, and no change or even a rise in blood pressure.</p>
<p>As we can see from these examples, adjustments to blood flow are not simply an adjustment of heart function, but also <strong>constriction or relaxation of the vasculature</strong> (blood vessels: arteries, veins, capillaries). <strong>Constricting blood vessels</strong> will reduce their <strong>cross-sectional area</strong> and <strong>increase blood pressure and flow</strong>.</p>
<p>Local changes in circulation are under both <strong>nervous</strong> and <strong>hormonal</strong> control. Regulation of blood flow in the vertebrate circulatory system occurs by three primary mechanisms: 1) <strong>local receptors</strong> (<em>nervous system</em>) to detect levels of metabolic activity (e.g., carbon dioxide receptors), 2) <strong>sympathetic</strong> and <strong>parasympathetic</strong> (<em>autonomic nervous system</em>) control of the vasculature including capillary beds at the tissues, and 3) <strong>endocrine</strong> (<em>hormonal</em>) control of the vasculature.</p>
<p>In this lab, we will measure blood pressure of volunteers using a finger pulse transducer, a stethoscope, a blood pressure cuff (sphygnomanometer), and changes in peripheral circulation by measuring the volume of the extremities using a respiratory belt with a force transducer. We will do a series of learning exercises and then conduct an experiment on factors affecting peripheral circulation and as well as during simulated dives (the dive response).</p>
</section>
<section id="equipment" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="equipment">Equipment</h2>
<ul>
<li>PowerLab data acquisition system</li>
<li>Finger pulse transducer</li>
<li>Stethoscope</li>
<li>Blood pressure cuff</li>
<li>Blood pressure gauge (sphygnomanometer) with pod or BNC port</li>
<li>Respiratory belt transducer</li>
<li>LabChart software, note Blood Pressure settings</li>
</ul>
</section>
</section>
<section id="exercise-1-measuring-blood-pressure" class="level1">
<h1>Exercise 1: Measuring Blood Pressure</h1>
<p>Traditionally, systemic arterial blood pressure is measured using a <strong>stethoscope</strong> and a <strong>blood pressure cuff</strong> connected to a blood pressure gauge called a <strong>sphygnomanometer</strong> (<em>sss-fig-no-ma-nom-eter</em>). The sphygnomanometer is calibrated in pressure units of mmHg (millimeters of mercury). Modern instruments use compressed air as a hydraulic fluid to transmit the force of your pulsing blood.</p>
<p>Refer to [<a href="../Protocols/p2-measuring-blood-pressure.pdf">Protocol 2.1 and 2.2</a>] for how to measure blood pressure.</p>
<section id="setup" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="setup">Setup</h2>
<ol type="1">
<li>Use “Lab 3-Blood Pressure” settings to start Chart software.</li>
<li>Check the channel settings: from the menu bar <strong>Setup &gt; Channel Settings</strong>. Is Pulse Flow on Input 1 or 2?</li>
<li>Attach Finger Pulse transducer.</li>
<li>Attach sphygmomanometer transducer.</li>
<li>Restart the LabChart software with the transducers attached to the correct inputs.</li>
</ol>
</section>
<section id="data-collection" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="data-collection">Data Collection</h2>
<ol type="1">
<li>Measure blood pressure on a human volunteer using <strong>auscultation</strong> (listening through a stethoscope) and a <strong>sphygnamonometer</strong> .</li>
<li>Measure blood pressure using the PowerLab system and LabChart. Check that the <strong>channel settings</strong> are correctly set for each channel.</li>
<li>Repeat (1) and (2) on each group member, making sure to comment your data trace.</li>
</ol>
<section id="questions-for-thought" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="questions-for-thought">Questions for thought…</h3>
<ol type="1">
<li>Does the time of the first <strong>Korotkoff sound</strong> (systolic pressure heard through the stethoscope), correspond with the first appearance of blood flow (as measured by the finger pulse)? Why or why not?</li>
<li>Would slowing the rate of pressure release from the cuff make your readings of the first appearance of blood flow more accurate? What problems might be caused by slowing pressure release?</li>
<li>Does the time that diastolic pressure is heard through the stethoscope correspond with anything particular in the blood flow signal? Can you, therefore, use pulse measurement to replace the stethoscope?</li>
<li>How much variation in measurement of diastolic and systolic pressures was observed within and between individuals? What are potential sources of variation in these estimates?</li>
</ol>
</section>
</section>
</section>
<section id="exercise-2-exploring-peripheral-circulation" class="level1">
<h1>Exercise 2: Exploring Peripheral Circulation</h1>
<section id="objectives" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="objectives">Objectives</h2>
<p>To demonstrate basic principles of peripheral circulation using blood pressure data from the extremities. What you would expect based on relative distance from the heart and gravity (and whether the location is above or below the heart)?</p>
</section>
<section id="procedure" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="procedure">Procedure</h2>
<ol type="1">
<li><em>Brainstorm with your lab group to develop some simple experiments to demonstrate principles of peripheral circulation.</em> What are some good hypotheses for peripheral blood pressure?</li>
<li>What are some good locations to measure (or other simple manipulations) for comparison? Make sure you place the stethoscope on a major artery or vein such as the radial artery on the forearm, or the small saphenous vein on the calf. Ask for help if you don’t know where they are. Be specific when you write up your methods or we will not understand what you did.</li>
<li>For each experiment, <strong>determine both systolic and diastolic blood pressure</strong>.</li>
</ol>
<section id="notes" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="notes">Notes</h3>
<ol type="1">
<li>If needed, recalibrate the blood pressure force transducer after each time you move the cuff.</li>
<li>Place the instruments directly on the skin (not through clothes).<br>
</li>
<li>If measuring from foot, please wash toe before attaching pulse transducer to prevent any fungal contamination.</li>
<li><strong>Always Release the cuff pressure <em>completely</em> as soon as you are done taking data</strong></li>
</ol>
</section>
<section id="analysis" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="analysis">Analysis</h3>
<p>Compare systolic and diastolic pressure for each of your treatments versus an appropriate baseline. Think carefully about appropriate baselines for your ideas to achieve the best test of your hypotheses.</p>
</section>
<section id="questions-for-thought-1" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="questions-for-thought-1">Questions for thought…</h3>
<ol type="1">
<li>How much does blood pressure change for each treatment? What could explain it? Does it seam reasonable?</li>
<li>How much variation is there among members of your group? What are sources of variation in these estimates?</li>
</ol>
</section>
</section>
</section>
<section id="exercise-3-the-dive-response" class="level1 page-columns page-full">
<h1>Exercise 3: The Dive Response</h1>
<p>When an air-breathing animal dives, it voluntarily holds its breath while the tissues continue to use oxygen. The <strong>dive response</strong> is a reflexive response that reorganizes circulation to maintain blood flow to the most essential organs – the brain, eyes, and myocardium (heart muscle), while reducing blood flow to the peripheral tissues including musculature of the limbs and thorax, lungs, and renal system. Remarkably, all vertebrates have a dive response. The responses vary greatly between taxa, with some of the most pronounced being in whales and diving seals.</p>
<p>Primary features of the human <strong>dive response</strong> are the rapid onset of <strong>bradycardia</strong> (slowing of the <em>heart rate</em>), which works together with <strong>peripheral vasoconstriction</strong> to shunt blood toward the bodyʻs core <span class="citation" data-cites="Withers:1992">(Withers 1992)</span>. This causes an increase in the volume of blood returning to the <strong>heart</strong> and an increase in <strong>stroke volume</strong>. Thus, although there is a drop in <em>heart rate</em>, there may be no change or even an increase in <strong>arterial blood pressure</strong>.</p>
<p>The dive response is thought to be adaptive for either reducing heat loss and/or preserving circulation around the vital organs while reducing circulation to the peripheral tissues. Oxygen becomes depleted and carbon dioxide and lactate build up in the tissues during a dive. When the animal resurfaces, there is a recovery period characterized by more rapid heart rate and ventilation to absorb more oxygen and flush out lactate and carbon dioxide.</p>
<p>The dive response is triggered by sudden submergence of the face in cold water, which stimulate the <em>trigeminal nerve receptors</em> around the face. Stimulation is enhanced with colder temperature, which inhibits the cardiovascular center, as well as increasing parasympathetic output and reducing sympathetic output, both of which reduce heart rate.</p>
<section id="objectives-1" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="objectives-1">Objectives</h2>
<p>You will investigate the effects of the diving response on heart rate and peripheral circulation in humans during simulated dives. First, you will examine the effect of holding your breath, then you will examine the effects of simulated dives, and an experiment to determine which environmental stimuli contribute to triggering the dive response. One person will serve as the experimental subject.</p>
</section>
<section id="additional-required-equipment" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="additional-required-equipment">Additional Required Equipment</h2>
<ul>
<li>Respiratory Belt Transducer</li>
<li>Wash basin, Ice, Thermometer</li>
<li>Duct tape</li>
<li>Use the Dive settings file</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="sec-divesetup" class="level2 page-columns page-full">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="sec-divesetup">A. Set up and testing</h2>

<div class="no-row-height column-margin column-container"><div class="">
<div id="fig-calf" class="quarto-float quarto-figure quarto-figure-center anchored">
<figure class="quarto-float quarto-float-fig figure">
<div aria-describedby="fig-calf-caption-0ceaefa1-69ba-4598-a22c-09a6ac19f8ca">
<img src="https://mbutler808.github.io/animalphys-2025/images/calf_belt.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img">
</div>
<figcaption class="quarto-float-caption-bottom quarto-float-caption quarto-float-fig" id="fig-calf-caption-0ceaefa1-69ba-4598-a22c-09a6ac19f8ca">
Figure&nbsp;4: Attachment of the respiratory belt transducer to the calf for leg volume measurement.
</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</div></div><ol type="1">
<li>Attach the respiratory belt transducer to Input 1, and the pulse transducer to Input 2.</li>
<li>Use “Lab 3-Dive Response…” settings to start Chart software.</li>
<li>Add 2 channels for Pulse Flow and Heart Rate.</li>
</ol>
<ul>
<li>From the menu bar, choose <strong>Setup &gt; Channel Settings</strong>. At the bottom of the menu, increase the number of channels to 3.<br>
</li>
<li>If you attached the pulse transducer before you opened the software, it should detect the pulse transducer and say so in the Input Amplifier column. If not, quit the software and reopen it via the settings file now that all the sensors are attached.</li>
<li>Name channel 2 “Pulse Flow”. In the box that pops up change the source to Channel 2 (to match the sensor input). Under Calculation, select Integral, (the default Standard Integral) and OK. This will tell us the relative volume of blood flowing through our pulse.</li>
<li>Name channle 3 “Heart Rate (BPM)”. Select Calculation &gt; Cyclic Measurements. Change the source to Channel 2 (calculating from the pulse transducer data), and ensure Measurement is set to Rate.</li>
<li><em>In this experiment, the sphygnamanometer is attached to a thigh cuff and used only to restrict blood flow to the thigh and not plugged in to PowerLab.</em></li>
</ul>
<ol start="4" type="1">
<li>Set up and maintain a wash basin with icewater deep enough to submerge your face up to your temples. Use a thermometer to monitor temperature at 10-15C (50-60F), replenish with ice as needed.</li>
<li>Attach the respiratory belt snugly to the calf (Figure&nbsp;4). <em>It should feel tight and the sensor fabric should be slightly stretched.</em></li>
<li>Place the thigh cuff around the subject’s thigh. You may or many not need to use <em>duct tape if the cuff does not remain securely pressurized to restrict blood flow</em>. If needed, apply tape to <em>secure both the top and the bottom</em> of the cuff.</li>
<li>Record for 10 seconds and stop. Scale the Pulse channel and the Leg Volume channel to fully display the data.</li>
<li>Record again and test by flexing and relaxing your calf. <em>You should be able to see a clear deflection on the leg volume channel.</em> If it is very small, try tightening the respiratory belt a little. Check with your TA that you are receiving a good signal before moving on.</li>
<li>For all experiments, <em>resting position for the subject is sitting while leaning over the basin with the face just above water.</em></li>
<li>Use a timer to time the treatments (a cell phone or a web browser will do).</li>
<li>You will want to use a compressed timescale to see the dive response. Try 100:1, 200:1, etc.</li>
<li>Always fully deflate the cuff (you may have to squeeze out the air) after depressurizing.</li>
</ol>
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-note callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
The idea behind measuring peripheral circulation using leg volume changes
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<p>We can quantify the volume in your peripheral circulation (specifically your lower leg) by assessing <strong>venous pooling</strong> for a standard time interval. By constricting blood flow to the lower limb, we will prevent venous return of the blood. Because the veins have little smooth muscle, it is relatively easy to stop venous return.</p>
</div>
</div>
<div id="prot-legvol" class="callout callout-style-default callout-tip callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
Protocol: Basic Leg volume measurement
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<p>You will use the sphygnomanometer cuff to cut off circulation in the leg for 20 sec.&nbsp;at the upper thigh. The respiratory belt transducer senses stretch and can be used to measure <strong>calf volume</strong> (Figure&nbsp;4) <strong>before</strong>, <strong>during inflation</strong>, and <strong>after deflating</strong> the cuff (recovery).</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>Record the subject’s <strong>resting</strong> recording for 10 seconds.</li>
<li>Rapidly <strong>Inflate</strong> the cuff to <strong>60 mmHg</strong> (or whatever pressure feels tight enough to restrict blood flow for the subject [I used 80 mmHg], the pressure should be same for all measurements),</li>
<li><strong>Hold pressure</strong> for <strong>exactly 20 seconds</strong> (<em>NOTE: You may have to gently squeeze the bulb to keep pressure constant.</em>)</li>
<li><strong>Quickly and COMPLETELY release</strong> the pressure (Figure&nbsp;5) by ripping off the velcro without moving the subject.</li>
<li><strong>Recovery:</strong> Record for 30 sec or until the leg volume returns to baseline.</li>
</ol>
<section id="notes-1" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="notes-1">NOTES:</h4>
<ul>
<li><span style="color: blue">Be sure to Comment at the <strong>start of each new treatment</strong> (start of baseline, start of dive response, etc.)</span></li>
<li>It is critical to have <span style="color: blue">accurate comments</span> for each manipulation above (resting, inflate, at pressure, release, dive, breathing, etc.)</li>
<li><em>Be sure to have the comments pre-typed in the comment box and hit enter at the start of each event to accurately place comments in time.</em></li>
<li><strong>Inflate</strong> and <strong>release</strong> the cuff as fast as possible.</li>
<li>Practice ripping off the cuff without moving the subject. The experimenter should do it.<br>
</li>
<li>When doing <em>repeated measurements</em>, ensure you have <strong>baseline data</strong> for <em>at least 15 sec</em> before inflating the cuff again.</li>
<li>The subject will have to hold their breath for about 30 sec.&nbsp;</li>
<li>Make <strong>good comments</strong> and <strong>minimize movement</strong> in the Finger Pulse Transducer.</li>
</ul>
</section>
</div>
</div>
</section>
<section id="b.-baseline-experiment" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="b.-baseline-experiment">B. Baseline experiment</h2>
<ol type="1">
<li>Use the <a href="@sec-divesetup">Section A setup</a> with the respiratory belt on the calf (Figure&nbsp;4) and the cuff on the upper thigh.</li>
<li>Subject leans over basin with face just above water.</li>
<li>Start recording and comment <span style="color:blue">“baseline control experiment, resting”</span>, record for 10sec.</li>
<li>Rapidly inflate the cuff to 60mmHg, comment <span style="color:blue">“cuff inflated”</span>, and record for 20sec.<br>
</li>
<li>Rip off the cuff, releasing pressure, and comment <span style="color:blue">“deflated”</span>. Record for 30 sec or until leg volume and HR stabilizes.</li>
</ol>
<p><span style="color: blue">Make sure to <strong>comment at each step</strong> and always <strong>DEFLATE CUFF COMPLETELY</strong> before reapplying the cuff.</span></p>
</section>
<section id="c.-dive-response-experiment" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="c.-dive-response-experiment">C. Dive response experiment</h2>
<p><em>Note: It is critical that the face be well submerged up to the temples in order to see the dive response.</em></p>
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-note callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
NOTES:
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<ul>
<li><strong>Make sure everything is very clear before beginning</strong> to avoid repeating this experiment.</li>
<li>It is a good idea to practice a dry run of the simulated dive procedure (without submerging face).</li>
<li>Work out in advance what your signals will be for resurfacing, or any other signals you need.</li>
<li><em>Do not force the subject to remain submerged</em>.<br>
</li>
</ul>
</div>
</div>
<ol type="1">
<li>Use the <a href="@sec-divesetup">Section A setup</a>. The basin should be in front of the subject and at 10-15C.</li>
<li>Before beginning, allow the subject to find a comforable chair height and leg posture to allow them to sit and <em>remain as motionless as possible with their face above the basin</em>.<br>
</li>
<li><strong>Simulated dive:</strong>
<ol type="a">
<li><strong>Rest:</strong> Start recording and comment <span style="color:blue">“dive experiment, resting”</span>, record for 10 sec</li>
<li><strong>Rapidly</strong> inflate cuff to 60mmHg, comment <span style="color:blue">“cuff inflated”</span>.<br>
</li>
<li>Have the subject take a deep breath, exhale partially, and then hold their breath while immersing their face up to their temples in the pan of water. Comment <span style="color:blue">“dive”</span>, record for 20 sec.&nbsp;</li>
<li><strong>Rapidly</strong> release all cuff pressure. Comment <span style="color:blue">“deflated”</span>, record for 10 sec.<br>
</li>
<li>Signal to the subject to <strong>resurface</strong> and breathe normally with face just above water. Comment <span style="color:blue">“normal breathing”</span> record for at least 10 sec (ok to keep recording through recovery).</li>
<li>Allow subject to gently dry face.</li>
</ol></li>
</ol>
</section>
<section id="c.-breath-holding-exeriment" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="c.-breath-holding-exeriment">C. Breath holding exeriment</h2>
<ol type="1">
<li>This experiment is very similar to the dive response, but without facial immersion. The subject will remain motionless with their face above the basin.</li>
<li><strong>Breath hold:</strong>
<ol type="a">
<li>Record and comment <span style="color:blue">“breath hold experiment, resting”</span>. Record for 10 sec.&nbsp;</li>
<li>Rapidly inflate cuff to 60mmHg, comment <span style="color:blue">“cuff inflated”</span>.<br>
</li>
<li>Have the subject take a deep breath, exhale partially, and then hold their breath. Comment <span style="color:blue">“breath hold”</span>, record for 20 sec.&nbsp;</li>
<li>Rapidly release all pressure. Comment <span style="color:blue">“deflated”</span>, and record for 10 sec.<br>
</li>
<li>Signal to the subject to <strong>breathe normally</strong> with face just above water. Comment <span style="color:blue">“normal breathing”</span> and record for 10 sec.&nbsp;</li>
</ol></li>
</ol>
</section>
<section id="d.-additional-experiment" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="d.-additional-experiment">D. Additional Experiment</h2>
<p>The simulated dive involves multiple stimuli simultaneously. <strong>Brainstorm</strong> how you might <em>identify the enviromental stimuli which are actually “triggering” the dive response by trying to isolate stimuli.</em> Are these components all necessary? Are they additive?</p>
<p>Each group should <strong>design and perform an experiment to isolate one potential stimulus</strong> responsible for triggering the dive response. Get your idea approved by your TA. Discuss your results with the other groups. <em>Make sure you explain your methods carefully (including your logic) in your lab report.</em></p>
</section>
<section id="analysis-1" class="level2 page-columns page-full">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="analysis-1">Analysis</h2>
<section id="change-in-heart-rate-and-pulse-amplitude" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="change-in-heart-rate-and-pulse-amplitude">Change in Heart Rate and Pulse Amplitude</h3>
<ol type="1">
<li>First analyze the <strong>Control Experiment</strong> and <strong>Dive Response</strong> data.</li>
<li>Open the data in the Chart View and <strong>Autoscale</strong>, if necessary. Change the compression of the data trace so the entire exercise can be viewed at once. Identify the <strong>rest</strong> section of the data and change the compression to find a representative cycle. <em>You can change the compression and scale as often as required.</em></li>
<li>Move the <strong>Waveform Cursor</strong> to a representative cycle on the <strong>pulse</strong> channel during <strong>rest</strong>. Collect the values for <strong>heart rate</strong> and <strong>pulse amplitude</strong> at the pulse peak. We can use pulse amplitude as a proxy for <strong>stroke volume</strong>.<br>
</li>
<li>Collect <strong>heart rate</strong> and <strong>pulse amplitude</strong> for:
<ol type="a">
<li>rest</li>
<li>15 sec into the dive (a representative pulsewave during dive)</li>
<li>10 sec after the end of the dive (recovery)</li>
<li>Tabulate the data in your notebook (for example see Table&nbsp;1)</li>
</ol></li>
<li>For the remaining experiments <strong>Post Dive</strong>, <strong>Breath Hold</strong> experiment, and <strong>Your Experiment</strong>, you only need to collect heart rate and pulse amplitude data for the treatment period (pre-treatment and post-treatment not necessary; Table&nbsp;2)</li>
</ol>
<div id="tbl-hrdata" class="quarto-float quarto-figure quarto-figure-center anchored">
<figure class="quarto-float quarto-float-tbl figure">
<figcaption class="quarto-float-caption-top quarto-float-caption quarto-float-tbl" id="tbl-hrdata-caption-0ceaefa1-69ba-4598-a22c-09a6ac19f8ca">
Table&nbsp;1: Heart rate and pulse amplitude should be recorded at rest, during the treatment, and during the recovery for each experiment.
</figcaption>
<div aria-describedby="tbl-hrdata-caption-0ceaefa1-69ba-4598-a22c-09a6ac19f8ca">
<table class="caption-top table">
<thead>
<tr class="header">
<th>Experiment</th>
<th>Parameter</th>
<th>Rest</th>
<th>Treatment</th>
<th>Recovery</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr class="odd">
<td>Baseline</td>
<td>heart rate (BPM)</td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td></td>
<td>pulse amplitude (mV)</td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>Dive</td>
<td>heart rate (BPM)</td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td></td>
<td>pulse amplitude (mV)</td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</div>
</figure>
</div>
</section>
<section id="change-in-peripheral-circulation" class="level3 page-columns page-full">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="change-in-peripheral-circulation">Change in Peripheral Circulation</h3>

<div class="no-row-height column-margin column-container"><div class="">
<div id="fig-legvol" class="quarto-float quarto-figure quarto-figure-center anchored">
<figure class="quarto-float quarto-float-fig figure">
<div aria-describedby="fig-legvol-caption-0ceaefa1-69ba-4598-a22c-09a6ac19f8ca">
<img src="https://mbutler808.github.io/animalphys-2025/images/legvol.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img">
</div>
<figcaption class="quarto-float-caption-bottom quarto-float-caption quarto-float-fig" id="fig-legvol-caption-0ceaefa1-69ba-4598-a22c-09a6ac19f8ca">
Figure&nbsp;5: Zoom window view of measuring the leg volume change resulting from a simulated dive using a marker at T1 (30sec of cuff inflation) and the waveform cursor at T2 (maximum leg volume drop after releasing the pressure).
</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</div></div><div class="callout callout-style-default callout-tip callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
Collecting leg volume change from the volume trace:
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<p>You will collect the relative signal amplitude change when the cuff pressure is released.</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>Set the <strong>Marker</strong> to the point of maximum leg voluime (a region just prior to cuff deflation in the leg volume channel; Figure&nbsp;5).</li>
<li>Using the <strong>Waveform Cursor</strong>, obtain the <strong>difference in leg volume</strong> between maximum and minimum leg volume (<img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%5CDelta%20LV"> (mV) <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?=%20LV1%20-%20LV2">; Figure&nbsp;5). Note the maximum and minimum should be just before and a little after the cuff is deflated.</li>
<li><strong>Relative leg volume</strong> is the ratio between the experimental and baseline leg volume differences. <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?Rel%20LV%20=%20%5CDelta%20LV_%7Btreatment%7D%20/%20%5CDelta%20LV_%7Bbaseline%7D">.</li>
</ol>
<p><strong>The <em>leg volume</em> difference</strong> is a measure of pooling and therefore peripheral circulation. <strong>Relative leg volume</strong> quantifies <strong>changes</strong> in <em>peripheral circulation</em>.</p>
</div>
</div>
<ol type="1">
<li>Collect the leg volume difference for the <strong>control</strong>, during the <strong>dive</strong>, and <strong>breath hold</strong> ( <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%5CDelta%20LV_%7Bbaseline%7D">, <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%5CDelta%20LV_%7Bdive%7D">, and <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%5CDelta%20LV_%7Bbreath_hold%7D"> ) .</li>
<li>Calculate the relative leg volumes for dive vs.&nbsp;baseline and dive vs.&nbsp;breath hold ( <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%5CDelta%20LV_%7Bdive%7D/%20%5CDelta%20LV_%7Bbaseline%7D">, etc.<br>
</li>
<li>Do the same for your <strong>custom experiment</strong> and tabulate as in Table&nbsp;2.</li>
</ol>
<div id="tbl-lvdata" class="quarto-float quarto-figure quarto-figure-center anchored">
<figure class="quarto-float quarto-float-tbl figure">
<figcaption class="quarto-float-caption-top quarto-float-caption quarto-float-tbl" id="tbl-lvdata-caption-0ceaefa1-69ba-4598-a22c-09a6ac19f8ca">
Table&nbsp;2: Heart rate (HR), pulse amplitude (PA), and leg volume (LV) data to record in your notebook. These are measurements taken during the “treatment” phase of each experiment. You may use the <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?HR_%7Bbaseline%7D">, <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?PA_%7Bbaseline%7D">, and <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%5CDelta%20LV_%7Bbaseline%7D"> for all of your comparisions if your setup has not changed (i.e., you did not reposition your cuff or your transducers).
</figcaption>
<div aria-describedby="tbl-lvdata-caption-0ceaefa1-69ba-4598-a22c-09a6ac19f8ca">
<table class="caption-top table">
<colgroup>
<col style="width: 20%">
<col style="width: 20%">
<col style="width: 20%">
<col style="width: 20%">
<col style="width: 20%">
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr class="header">
<th></th>
<th>Baseline</th>
<th>Dive</th>
<th>Breath Hold</th>
<th>My Expt</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr class="odd">
<td>heart rate (BPM)</td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>pulse amplitude (mv)</td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%5CDelta%20LV"> (mV)</td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td></td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td></td>
<td><strong>Dive/Baseline</strong></td>
<td><strong>Breath Hold/Baseline</strong></td>
<td><strong>My Expt/Baseline</strong></td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>Relative HR</td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>Relative LV</td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</div>
</figure>
</div>
</section>
</section>
<section id="questions-for-thought-.-.-." class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="questions-for-thought-.-.-.">Questions for thought . . .</h2>
<ol type="1">
<li>Compare your results of heart rate during breath holding with those from simulated dives. Are they the same?</li>
<li>What factors could explain differences between breath holding and a “dive”? Have you eliminated any hypotheses with your experiments?</li>
<li>Compare the percent change in heart rate during dives among different people. Is the relative or absolute bradycardia similar?<br>
</li>
<li>Do your results for leg volume suggest that peripheral circulation changes during a dive? during a breath-hold?</li>
<li>Did your peripheral circulation increase or decrease during a “dive”? during a breath hold?</li>
<li>What comparisons can you make to dive deeper into your data? Which numbers would you look at?</li>
<li>Why do you think the diving response is considered advantageous?</li>
</ol>
</section>
</section>
<section id="after-lab-assignment-week-3" class="level1">
<h1>After Lab: Assignment Week 3:</h1>
<ul>
<li>Before you leave, please tidy up and leave the equiptment (sensors, cables) as you found them. Make sure the PowerLab is powered down. Leave computers on but do <strong>make a folder for your lab group</strong> on the desktop and <em>move ALL your FILES into your groupʻs folder</em>.</li>
<li>You will work with your lab group to analyze data, and you may share figures if you wish. However, each person will submit an <strong>Individual WorkSheet</strong> [<a href="../../labs/Lab3-human-peripheral-circulation-dive-response/Lab3ws.html">html</a>]</li>
<li>Reminder: <em>Practical has been moved to next week (week 4) on Lab 1 material</em>. Let us know if you want to come in to practice.</li>
</ul>



</section>

<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-bibliography"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">References</h2><div id="refs" class="references csl-bib-body hanging-indent" data-entry-spacing="0">
<div id="ref-Withers:1992" class="csl-entry">
Withers, Philip C. 1992. <em>Comparative Animal Physiology</em>. Saunders College Publishing.
</div>
</div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>week 3</category>
  <category>labs</category>
  <category>circulation</category>
  <category>peripheral circulation</category>
  <category>blood pressure</category>
  <category>dive response</category>
  <guid>https://mbutler808.github.io/animalphys-2025/labs/Lab3-human-peripheral-circulation-dive-response/Lab3.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 10 Sep 2024 10:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Lab 2: Zoo</title>
  <dc:creator>Marguerite Butler</dc:creator>
  <link>https://mbutler808.github.io/animalphys-2025/labs/Lab2-zoo/Lab2.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<section id="bring-with-you" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="bring-with-you">Bring with you:</h2>
<ul>
<li>Your lab notebook</li>
<li>A timing device (e.g.&nbsp;your phone)</li>
<li>Sun screen, hat, and sunglasses. It will be hot and sunny!</li>
<li>Water</li>
</ul>
<p>Your task this week is to construct an energy budget for an animal of your choice, very similar to modeling the metabolism of your fossil. Each group will choose a different zoo animal (Letʻs try to spread the groups across the large /small, herbivore/predator combinations).</p>
<p><img src="https://mbutler808.github.io/animalphys-2025/images/Zoo-Map.png" class="img-fluid" alt="Map of the Honolulu Zoo"><a href="https://www.honoluluzoo.org" class="uri">https://www.honoluluzoo.org</a></p>
</section>
<section id="observe-animals" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="observe-animals">Observe Animals</h2>
<p>First, walk around the zoo, and do a mental scavengar hunt, noting as many as you can for each of mammals, birds, reptiles, and amphibians. What do you notice, do they tend to be herbivores/predators?, small/large?, sun-loving/shade-loving/nocturnal? (The zoo does not have a large collection of amphibians, so don’t miss the ectotherm house!). Weʻll discuss this at the end of class.</p>
</section>
<section id="focal-observation" class="level1">
<h1>Focal Observation</h1>
<p>As a group choose an animal to observe.</p>
<section id="collect-data" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="collect-data">Collect Data:</h2>
<p><strong>Mass:</strong> Approximate the dimensions of your animal. Approximate the volume of your animal, by whatever geometric approximation seems reasonable to you. Animals are ~70% water. Estimate mass from the density of water (1g/cm^3).</p>
<p>FYI: Volume of a cylinder: V = π<em>r^2</em>length (use metric units!!)</p>
<p><strong>Behavior:</strong> (focus on intensity of effort and time budget)</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>10 min observation focal observation</li>
</ol>
<p>Each group member will collect a 10 min focal observation. Record in your notebook everything your animal does during the 10 min observation period, recording activity and duration.</p>
<p>For example: + Lying on ground 10 min (can add comments or social context, etc.) + Walking slowly 1 min + Etc.</p>
<ol start="2" type="1">
<li>Also record general info: species, male/female/adult/juvenile etc., time of day, habitat and surroundings, any conspecifics nearby?</li>
<li>After your focal observation, write some general impressions. How would you characterize your animalʻs behavior? What seems to be motivating your animal? (note anything relevant, like keeps looking toward a male, trying to reach food, etc.).<br>
</li>
<li>Note any behaviors related to temperature exchange: Basking? Seeking shade? Pressing their body against a cool surface (conduction)? Enjoying strong wind (convection)? Wet? Etc.</li>
<li>Take photos and videos that capture the essence of your animal or show something interesting.</li>
<li>Optional: Your animal may or may not do very much during your observation period. You can also take “scan samples” periodically. Say every hour or half hour, what is your animal doing? Who is nearby?</li>
</ol>
</section>
<section id="analysis" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="analysis"><strong>Analysis:</strong></h2>
<ol type="1">
<li>Construct a mass model for your animal.<br>
</li>
<li><strong>BMR</strong> or <strong>SMR</strong>. Choose an appropriate <a href="https://drive.google.com/file/d/1lmqsS9VXglPjCRkjRofAZKquFPL74qEl/view?usp=sharing">scaling equation</a> for BMR or SMR from Withers 1991 Table 4-5 and calculate the lowest metabolic rate for your animal. If an ectotherm, guestimate what the animal’s Tb is.<br>
</li>
<li><strong>Time Budget:</strong> Analyze your focal observation and use it to estimate a time budget. With your team members, decide on the intensity levels of each type of behavior. Based on your own experience, assign effort levels to each type of behavior. (divide activities into say, 3 categories of effort). Estimate the percent of time spent in each category based on your observation and other information you may know.</li>
<li>Use Table 4-10 to select appropriate activity multipliers for each category. For example, RMR might be 1.2x BMR based on … in Table 4-10. In general, very inactive animals will have a lower RMR (say 1.1. Or 1.2x BMR) than very active animals (say 1.5 x BMR).<br>
</li>
<li><strong>DMR:</strong> Take an educated guess about how many hours your animal spends sleeping or resting, and in each of your active categories. Construct a model for the cost of 1 day. We call this DMR or daily metabolic rate. For example, your animalʻs DMR might be = 16 hrs x RMR + 1 hr x AMR(activity 1) + 7hr x AMR(activity 2). Etc.</li>
</ol>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://mbutler808.github.io/animalphys-2025/images/Table4-10.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>Table 4-10 from Withers 1991</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</section>
</section>
<section id="report" class="level1">
<h1><strong>Report:</strong></h1>
<p>Your assignment is to write a group short lab report with the following sections:</p>
<p><em>Intro:</em></p>
<p>Write a short paragraph describing your animal. What do you think the relevant background should include? End with a statement of purpose.</p>
<p><em>Methods (~2-3 concise paragraphs):</em></p>
<ul>
<li>State how you collected your data. “Focal observations were conducted… “<br>
</li>
<li>State what you modeled. For each model, explain how you calculated it. Remember, you are making it up so you have to explain your logic so that someone outside the class could understand. Include your equations and all the assumptions or estimations you used to model mass, BMR/SMR, one or more AMRs, and DMR.</li>
</ul>
<p><em>Results (probably ~1-2 paragraphs, grouped by topic):</em></p>
<ul>
<li>What did your animal do? What was itʻs primary activity? Look at your results and think about how best to convey the main findings. A table of activities and time? Or perhaps grouped into resting, low intensity, high intensity activities? You decide.<br>
</li>
<li>Report your mass, and all MRʻs. Also report mass-specific BMR and DMR.<br>
</li>
<li>Notes on the observed behavior of the animal.<br>
</li>
<li>Include photos or video clips to help tell the story of your animal.</li>
</ul>
<p><em>Discussion (1 or more paragraphs, depending on how much you have to say - no fluff!):</em></p>
<ul>
<li>A small discussion that sheds light on your findings. All in all, how would you characterize your animal? Is it an active animal or a sedentary animal?<br>
</li>
<li>Any insight into what guides its energy consumption? Based on your observations, what did itʻs main concern seem to be? Here is a good place to add in some of your observations to back up your characterization. The discussion is where you can speculate a little about what your data might mean.<br>
</li>
<li>Comment on any temperature-regulation behaviors.<br>
</li>
<li>Conclusion: What do your findings imply? Do you understand more about your animal? Does it make sense, given that itʻs a large/small predator/herbivore, etc. What could be some fruitful next steps if you were to continue the research? (do you think the behavior of your animal would be different in the wild?, etc. )</li>
</ul>
<p><em>Respective Contributions:</em> Each lab group member is expected to participate meaningfully in data collection, data analysis, lab report writing, and lab report editing. Please identify a project coordinator for this lab.</p>
<section id="submit" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="submit">Submit:</h2>
<p>Create a new folder with the animal you chose in the following parent folder: https://drive.google.com/drive/folders/1o_dXXYk2Hp4chmqorrgKhPu4qzUh4yCZ?usp=sharing Write up your mini-lab report as google doc and upload it into your folder together with the pictures and videos you took. Include your group member names in the report.</p>
<p><strong>Reminder:</strong> Clarity of ideas is highly prized in science, which is more obvious when you are concise. Do include any relevant scientific terms (BMR, DMR, etc.), but other than that, use plain, direct language that gets straight to the point and your writing will be stronger.</p>


</section>
</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>week 2</category>
  <category>labs</category>
  <category>mass</category>
  <category>activity</category>
  <category>energy budget</category>
  <category>time budget</category>
  <category>scaling</category>
  <category>BMR</category>
  <category>AMR</category>
  <category>DMR</category>
  <guid>https://mbutler808.github.io/animalphys-2025/labs/Lab2-zoo/Lab2.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 03 Sep 2024 10:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Lab 3 Worksheet: Peripheral Circulation and The Dive Response</title>
  <dc:creator>Marguerite Butler</dc:creator>
  <link>https://mbutler808.github.io/animalphys-2025/labs/Lab3-human-peripheral-circulation-dive-response/Lab3ws.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-tip callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
Instructions - Individual Worksheet
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<ul>
<li>Please pay attention to the <strong>intellectual content</strong> contained in each section of this <strong>worksheet</strong>.</li>
<li>Our goal here is the practice logically laying out our <strong>ideas</strong> focusing on <strong><em>physiological mechanisms</em></strong>.</li>
<li>Section (1) is designed to guide you to building strong hypotheses, section (2) is essential knowledge for both hypotheses and designing your figures, and guiding your (3) results and (4) discussion sections, respectively. Everything on worksheets are brief.</li>
<li>You may use the Word template or just type up your worksheet for submission. Include the statements of purpose below. For section 2 write a brief sentence for what you would expect to see in the data. Be concise, to the point (no extra words)! Results and Discussion are in paragraph form.</li>
<li>Notice how much we are emphasizing brief, concise, to the point!, and relevant. <em>Right, Relevant, Righteous!</em></li>
</ul>
</div>
</div>
<section id="statements-of-purpose" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="statements-of-purpose"><strong>(1) Statements of Purpose</strong></h3>
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-tip callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
Tip
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<p><em>In a scientific paper, the introduction builds to a statement of purpose (or hypotheses) in the final paragraph of the intro.</em> The statements you see below are examples appropriate for this lab. Study them to guide this assignment, and for future experiments where you will have to write your own. Notice that the physiological mechanisms and the associated variables are clearly stated, along with the hypothesized relationship between them (and experimental design if you can!). In a full paper (or lab report), your introduction would start from the main idea, introduce the mechanisms and connect the dots to the hypotheses in the final paragraph.</p>
</div>
</div>
<p><strong>Use these statements of purpose to frame your thinking about this lab, fill in the blanks:</strong></p>
<p><em>Distance from heart</em> – “We demonstrate the predicted drop in blood pressure with distance from the central pump. We explore whether there is a greater drop in systolic or diastolic pressure with distance” (in a full lab report you would set up your ideas for why it might go either way).</p>
<p><em>Effect of gravity</em> – “We demonstrate the action of gravity on blood pressure. As vertebrates possess a closed circulatory system, vertical height should contribute to blood pressure in predictable ways.”</p>
<p><em>Dive response</em> – “When diving, peripheral circulation should be reorganized to reduce cardiac output and increase peripheral vasoconstriction, called the dive response. We aim to observe the dive response by measuring ________________________.”</p>
<p><em>Stimulus for dive response</em> – “We will test potential triggers for the dive response including ____________________________.””</p>
</section>
<section id="concept-check-demonstrate-your-understanding" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="concept-check-demonstrate-your-understanding"><strong>(2) Concept check: demonstrate your understanding</strong></h3>
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-note callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
How will we evaluate the hypotheses?
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<p><em>What do you expect to see in the data if the hypothesis is true (if these mechanisms are occurring)? Be specific and relate back to observable parameters: (and relate to controls or confounding parameters, if appropriate).</em> Write a brief sentence for each (just for clarification, this is not a formal “section” of a scientific paper nor a lab report, rather these ideas would be woven throughout the manuscript):</p>
<ul>
<li><p>Distance from heart</p></li>
<li><p>Effect of gravity</p></li>
<li><p>Dive response</p></li>
<li><p>Stimulus for dive response</p></li>
</ul>
</div>
</div>
</section>
<section id="mini-results" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="mini-results">(3) Mini Results</h3>
<p><em>Display your results by including either <strong>a figure or a table</strong> for each important result (remember to design each to address a hypothesis).</em> You may work together with your group to produce the figures or tables. <strong>Write a paragraph</strong> for the results with <em><strong>~one sentence</strong> pointing out what your data actually shows for each display item (refer in-text to each figure).</em></p>
</section>
<section id="mini-discussion" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="mini-discussion">(4) Mini Discussion:</h3>
<p><strong>Wrap-up:</strong> In paragraph form, briefly <strong>Discuss</strong> the <strong>main take-aways</strong> that you learned from these experiments on peripheral circulation and the dive response. Use specific results that back up your statements or speculate on the significance of the results. Organize by hypotheses above.</p>
<p><strong>Individual assignment.</strong> Text must be your own, but you may work together with your group to produce figures/tables. You may edit this sheet. Submit by hard copy next week.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>week 3</category>
  <category>labs</category>
  <category>circulation</category>
  <category>peripheral circulation</category>
  <category>blood pressure</category>
  <category>dive response</category>
  <category>worksheet</category>
  <guid>https://mbutler808.github.io/animalphys-2025/labs/Lab3-human-peripheral-circulation-dive-response/Lab3ws.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 10 Sep 2023 10:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Standard Protocols</title>
  <dc:creator>Marguerite Butler</dc:creator>
  <link>https://mbutler808.github.io/animalphys-2025/labs/Protocols/protocols.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p><a href="p1-intro-finger-pulse.pdf">Protocol 1</a> Introduction to the <strong>Data Acquisition System</strong>, use of the <strong>Finger Pulse Transducer</strong>, and <strong>Saving Data</strong>.</p>
<p><a href="p2-measuring-blood-pressure.pdf">Protocol 2</a> Setup for measuring <strong>Blood Pressure</strong> in humans.</p>
<p><a href="p3-human-ecg.pdf">Protocol 3</a> Setup for measuring <strong>Electro Cardiograms (ECG or EKG)</strong> in humans.</p>
<p><a href="LabChart7_1_QRG.pdf">LabChart Quick Reference Guide</a> Very useful for troubleshooting or more details in using the LabChart software.</p>
<section id="general-lab-course-info" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="general-lab-course-info">General Lab Course Info:</h2>
<ul>
<li><a href="../../labs-misc/handouts/Revised_Zool430L_lab_report_guidelines.pdf">Lab Report Guidelines</a></li>
<li><a href="../../labs-misc/handouts/Lab-Expectations.pdf">Lab Expectations</a></li>
<li><a href="../../labs-misc/lab-notebook.html">Notebook Instructions</a></li>
<li><a href="../../labs-misc/handouts/Agreement-for-Group-Lab-Report-Timeline.pdf">Lab Team Timeline Agreement</a></li>
</ul>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>week 1</category>
  <category>week3</category>
  <category>week4</category>
  <category>labs</category>
  <category>protocols</category>
  <category>PowerLab</category>
  <category>LabChart</category>
  <category>finger pulse transducer</category>
  <category>Blood Pressure</category>
  <category>Human ECG</category>
  <category>LabChart Quick Reference Guide</category>
  <guid>https://mbutler808.github.io/animalphys-2025/labs/Protocols/protocols.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 19 Aug 2023 10:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Lab Notebooks and Prelab Instructions</title>
  <link>https://mbutler808.github.io/animalphys-2025/labs/Lab-notebooks/lab-notebook.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>Your <strong>lab notebook</strong> is a record of your labwork. In research, a lab notebook is more than a diary of your work, it is used to write your reports and papers, inspire future research, or even prove the development of ideas in court cases.</p>
<p>For this class, it is bound notebook used exclusively for recording information and notes pertinent to experiments performed in this lab. Your lab notebook will help you to do well on your lab reports, which are typed (i.e., mini scientific papers) that you turn in for grading. It is also a great place to take notes in lab lectures or discussion that may be helpful later.</p>
<section id="format" class="level1">
<h1>Format</h1>
<ul>
<li><strong>Title page</strong>
<ul>
<li>Include your name, email address, lab section and purpose of the notebook on the first page, and the names and contact information (email and phone #) for your lab group.</li>
<li><strong>Table of contents</strong>: update weekly with page numbers for each lab. (Number the pages of the rest of your lab notebook).</li>
</ul></li>
<li><strong>Labs</strong> - Each lab has four sections:
<ul>
<li><strong>Introduction</strong> <em>(prelab)</em></li>
<li><strong>Methods</strong> <em>(prelab)</em></li>
<li><strong>Results</strong> <em>(in lab)</em></li>
<li><strong>Discussion</strong> <em>(in lab)</em></li>
</ul></li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="sec-prelab" class="level1">
<h1>Prelab</h1>
<p><strong>At home</strong>, read through the complete lab exercise. Your lab may also have standard protocols to read. In your notebook, write (or bullet-point) the introduction and methods sections below. This is your pre-lab assignment (5pts), and will be checked by your TA at the start of lab.</p>
<section id="introduction" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="introduction">Introduction</h2>
<ul>
<li>Write the purpose of the week’s experiment. This should be the general idea that is broad enough to cover all of the ideas in the lab (the “umbrella idea”).</li>
<li>Bullet-point the most relevant background in this experiment, and how it might connect to a hypothesis. Organize by major ideas.
<ul>
<li>Start from what we know about the topic, and connect to what we are trying to demonstrate or find out in the current experiment.</li>
<li>Be sure to introduce the physiological mechanisms that go into your hypothesis.</li>
<li>Along the way, try to foreshadow why the current experiment is important.</li>
</ul></li>
<li>A starting hypothesis (or hypotheses if there are multiple parts).</li>
</ul>
<p><em>An introduction just introduces the ideas – just enough so we can understand the hypothesis. Save the deeper dive for later.</em></p>
<p>Your TA will give you feedback during the prelab-check. <em>We particularly want to make sure you have a strong hypothesis.</em></p>
</section>
<section id="methods" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="methods">Methods</h2>
<p>The experiment should be reproducible by a scientist based on your methods. Include:</p>
<ul>
<li>Type of subjects (species) and how many</li>
<li>What physiological parameters you measured and techniques used. (e.g., <em>Human heart rate (HR) was measured using a finger pulse transducer connected to a PowerLab Data Acquistion System following Zool430 Lab Protocol 1)</em>. Note settings (sampling frequency, etc.).
<ul>
<li>Provide enough experimental detail so that a physiologist can replicate the experiment. For example: where were measurements taken? recording for how long?</li>
<li>Specify the controls (or baselines) and treatments</li>
<li>The order of experiments, how many trials, etc.</li>
</ul></li>
</ul>
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-tip callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
Reduce, Reuse, Recycle
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<p>NOTE: You will be using a lot of standard protocols for the instrumentation in this lab.</p>
<ul>
<li>State which ones you used with a citation to which lab manual, protocol, or manufacturerʻs instructions that are already published.</li>
<li>Scientists are precise but avoid repetition by citing published protcols or methods of previous papers.</li>
<li>Do explain any customizations or changes.</li>
</ul>
</div>
</div>
<ul>
<li>How raw data are converted to physiological measurements
<ul>
<li>For example, “<em>systolic pressure was obtained from the blood pressure waveform by taking peak-to-trough measurements of the largest peaks.</em>”</li>
<li>Example: “<em>Heart rate was calculated using the cyclic measurements panel in LabChart softare to measure the time between pulse wave peaks (peak-to-peak measurements) divided by elapsed time.</em>”</li>
<li>Example: “<em>Peripheral circulation volume was measured as the difference between maximum and minimum leg volume measurements (at baseline and after reducing venous return for 30sec, respectively).</em>”</li>
</ul></li>
<li>Analysis
<ul>
<li>How the data will be used to evaluate the hypotheses. In other words, what will we compare to know whether the hypothesis has any support? This usually involves how the treatments will be compared to controls or baseline and can foreshadow the figures presented in the results.</li>
<li>For example, “HR was compared before and during a simulated dive to assess diving bradycardia, and venous pooling …”</li>
</ul></li>
</ul>
</section>
</section>
<section id="in-lab" class="level1">
<h1>In Lab</h1>
<section id="results" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="results">Results</h2>
<p>Include raw data, calculations, equations, and physiological parameters obtained in your notebook.</p>
<ul>
<li>Write all raw results in your notebook obtained from measuring peaks or landmarks, etc.</li>
<li>If your lab manual has any tables, you can fill them in and paste them into your notebook.</li>
<li>Data from the Chart software can be saved as .adicht (Windows chart data), which is a text format. This can be further analyzed at home with LabChart reader 8.0 software.</li>
<li>It is important to record things that go wrong as well as things that go right.</li>
<li>We will have in-lab discussions about how to analyze data and brainstorm what effective figures might look like. It is a great idea to sketch these ideas in your notebook.</li>
</ul>
<p><em>During lab, there should be time to collect the physiological parameters from your raw data, and to play with making figures or tables for your lab report.</em></p>
</section>
<section id="discussion" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="discussion">Discussion</h2>
<p>Summarize your conclusions from the experiment. Discuss what your results mean and interpret in light of the purpose of the lab. Think about what implications your results might have more broadly.</p>
<ul>
<li>Look through your results and at least bullet-point some potential discussion topics.<br>
</li>
<li>Focus on interpretation of your direct results</li>
<li>What do your results mean? Dig into the details of the results.</li>
<li>Note any connections between your results and known physiological mechanisms. What have we learned or demonstrated?</li>
<li>Could your results apply to anything else? End by broadening out.</li>
<li>Include any good ideas that come up during the lab session.</li>
</ul>
</section>
</section>
<section id="checkout" class="level1">
<h1>Checkout</h1>
<p>Before you leave the lab, checkout with your TA.</p>
<ul>
<li>Your TA will give you feedback on your results and discussion, and your hypothesis (which hopefully has been improved).<br>
</li>
<li>Our goal is to ensure you leave lab with all the materials needed to write an excellent report.</li>
</ul>
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-important callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
If you have a good lab notebook, it will be easy to write your lab report because most of it can be taken from your notebook!
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<p><em>If you plan ahead and work efficiently, your group could complete and submit the lab report by the time you leave lab</em></p>
</div>
</div>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <guid>https://mbutler808.github.io/animalphys-2025/labs/Lab-notebooks/lab-notebook.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 26 Aug 2025 22:59:32 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
